<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab Urbe Condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 43-45 - 45</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Schlesinger" role="editor">Alfred C. Schlesinger, Ph.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books XLIII-XLV With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1951: published without copyright notice</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="p.249"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="book">
                <head>Book XLV</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> THE messengers of victory, Quintus Fabius,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note>
                    Lucius Lentulus, and Quintus Metellus, summoned up the <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> utmost possible speed and quickly arrived in Rome.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Yet they found that the joy of their
                    announcement had been anticipated. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the
                    third day <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> As the battle took place on
                        Sept. 4, Livy thinks of these games as occurring on Sept. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> 7 by the then calendar (actually June 25, see above,
                        pp. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> 87-89). It is not possible to
                        establish exactly for this period the date of the Roman Games mentioned
                        below; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> in the time of Augustus, they
                        extended from Sept. 4 to Sept. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> 19, but
                        were probably extended as time went on. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        The story of the mysterious announcement is told also by Plutarch, <hi
                            rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> xxiv, who agrees with Livy <milestone
                            n="10??" unit="section"/> in eliminating the gods from direct action on
                        this occasion; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> according to Cicero, <hi
                            rend="italics">N.D.</hi>
                        <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> ii. 6, Valerius Maximus I. viii. 1, and
                        Pliny, <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi> VII. xxii. 86, the news was proclaimed
                        by Castor and Pollux. </note> after the battle with the king, while games
                    were being celebrated in the circus, a rumour in the audience suddenly swept
                    over the whole auditorium that a battle had been fought in Macedonia and the
                    king beaten; then the buzz increased; finally there arose shouting and clapping,
                    as if a definite report of victory had arrived. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> The magistrates were astonished and sought after the originator of this
                    sudden rejoicing. When no such person was found, the rejoicing as if for an
                    established fact died away, but the happy omen lurked nevertheless in men's
                    minds. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After confirmation came through the
                    genuine report on the arrival of Fabius, Lentulus, and Metellus, men rejoiced
                    both in the actual victory and in the prophetic power of their spirits. The
                    story is told of a second rejoicing by the mob at the circus, which seemed no
                    less genuine. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the sixteenth of <pb
                        n="p.251"/> September, on the second day of the Roman Games, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> it is said
                    that a messenger who said he came from Macedonia handed despatches wreathed with
                    laurel to the consul Gaius Licinius as he was going up to start the
                    chariot-race. When the race was over, the consul mounted his chariot and as he
                    was being driven back to the reserved seats, showed the despatches to the
                    people. At the sight of them the people at once forgot the show and rushed down
                    into the arena. On the spot, the consul summoned the senate, had the despatches
                    read, and on motion of the Fathers, announced to the people before the
                    magistrates' seats that his colleague Lucius Aemilius had fought a pitched
                    battle with King Perseus, that the Macedonian army had been slaughtered and
                    routed, that the king had fled with but few followers, and that all the cities
                    of Macedonia had come under the sway of the Roman people. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> On hearing this, shouting with great clapping of hands
                    began; the games were deserted and most of the people took home the glad news to
                    their wives and children. This was the twelfth day after the battle had taken
                    place in Macedonia. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> II. Next day the senate met in the
                    senate-house, a thanksgiving was voted, and a resolution passed that the consul
                    should discharge men whom he had under oath, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> These men under oath might be volunteers or veterans
                        specially summoned (evocati); Servius, <hi rend="italics">ad Aen.</hi> VIII.
                        1, describes <hi rend="italics">coniuratio</hi> as a process of enrolling
                        such special soldiers, as contrasted with a regular levy. But the reason for
                        large numbers at this time may be the failure of the consul in Italy to
                        qualify as commander of Roman troops (see below, xii. 12) and the consequent
                        holding at Rome of Roman levies intended for him. </note> except soldiers
                    and sailors, and that the question of dismissing soldiers and sailors should be
                    put when the envoys who had sent the messenger ahead should arrive from the
                    consul Lucius Aemilius. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On the twenty-fifth
                    day of September, about the <pb n="p.253"/> second hour the envoys entered the
                    city, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The envoys seem not to have
                        hurried, or to have been delayed by adverse winds in crossing the Adriatic;
                        Paulus went from Brundisium to Phila in eleven days, with a visit to Delphi
                        included, below, xli. 3. </note> and made <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> their way to the forum,
                    drawing after them a huge crowd of people who met them at every point on their
                    way, and proceeded to escort them. The senate happened to be in the
                    senate-house; the consul presented the envoys there. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> They were kept there just long enough to explain how large
                    the king's forces of infantry and cavalry had been, how many thousand of them
                    had been slain and how many captured, with the loss of how few of our men this
                    great slaughter of the enemy had been accomplished, and how hastily the king had
                    fled; it was thought, the envoys said, that he would make for Samothrace; the
                    fleet was ready to pursue, and it would be impossible for him to slip away
                    either by land or sea. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On being brought before
                    a meeting shortly thereafter, the envoys related the same facts. Joy broke out
                    anew when the consul proclaimed that all sacred buildings should be opened;
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> from the meeting, each citizen went of
                    his own accord to offer thanks to the gods, and all over the city the temples of
                    the immortal gods were filled with a huge throng, not only of men, but of women
                    too. </p>
                <p> The senate was recalled to the senate-house, voted that thanksgiving for the
                    glorious achievement of the consul Lucius Aemilius should be observed for five
                    days at all the banquet-tables of the gods, and ordered sacrifice offered with
                    the larger victims. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The ships which were
                    moored in the Tiber ready and equipped to be sent to Macedonia, if circumstances
                        <pb n="p.255"/> demanded it, were to be put ashore and housed in <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> the
                    ship-sheds; the sailors were to be discharged after receiving their year's pay,
                    and with them, all those who had taken the oath before the consul. It was voted
                    to discharge all soldiers who were in Corcyra, at Brundisium, along the
                    Adriatic, or in the territory of Larinum —for an army had been distributed among
                    all these places, to enable Gaius Licinius to bring aid to his colleague, if the
                    situation demanded it. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> At a meeting a
                    thanksgiving was proclaimed to the people for the eleventh of October and the
                    four days following. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From Illyricum two envoys, Gaius Licinius
                    Nerva and Publius Decius, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In XLIV.
                        xxxii. 4, Perpenna is given as the messenger, instead of these two. </note>
                    announced that the army of the Illyrians had been slaughtered, King Gentius was
                    captured, and Illyricum was under the sway of the Roman people. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> For this achievement under the leadership and auspices of
                    the praetor Lucius Anicius, the senate voted thanksgiving for three days. The
                    date was proclaimed by the consul as the tenth, eleventh, and twelfth of
                    November. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some historians <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Apparently Polybius XXIX. 19 (7); in XLIV. xiv. 8-xv,
                        Livy, following a Roman source, places the embassy a year too early. </note>
                    relate that the ambassadors of the Rhodians, who had not yet been dismissed
                    after the announcement of victory, were summoned to the senate, as if in mockery
                    of their foolish pride, and that there Agepolis, their chief, spoke as follows:
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> the envoys had been sent by the Rhodians
                    to bring about peace between the Romans and Perseus, since the war between them
                    was the cause of hardship <pb n="p.257"/> and <milestone n="5??" unit="section"
                    /> injury to all Greece, and of expense and loss to <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> the Romans themselves. The
                    good fortune of the Roman people had been kind to the Rhodians in giving them
                    the opportunity, now that the war had been brought to an end by other means, of
                    congratulating the Romans on their glorious victory. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> This was the speech of the Rhodian. </p>
                <p> The answer of the senate was that the Rhodians had sent that embassy through
                    concern neither for the welfare of Greece nor for the outlays of the Roman
                    People, but on behalf of Perseus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For had
                    their concern been as alleged, their envoys should have been sent when Perseus
                    had led his army into Thessaly and for two years was besieging some Greek cities
                    and alarming others with the threat of attack. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    At that time, there had been not a word about peace from the Rhodians. After
                    they had heard that the Romans had overcome the passes and crossed into
                    Macedonia, and that Perseus was surrounded, then the Rhodians sent an embassy
                    for no other purpose than to snatch Perseus from the impending disaster. With
                    this reply, the envoys were dismissed. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time Marcus Marcellus, on his
                    return from Spain after taking the noted city of Marcolica, also deposited in
                    the treasury ten pounds <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The weight of
                        metal is obviously too small for the value given, but it is not easy to
                        propose an emendation. The lb. of silver probably = 336 sesterces; the lb.
                        of gold probably = 4000 sesterces (cf..Vol. XI. 192, note 4). Could <hi
                            rend="italics">MDC pondo</hi> become <hi rend="italics">decem pondo</hi>
                        by scribal error? I is perhaps easier to assume the loss of the first
                        figures of the correct number; but the number suggested is of the proper
                        order. </note> of gold and silver of a value of one million sesterces. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As the consul Aemilius Paulus was encamped
                    near Sirae in the Odomantian territory, as was mentioned <pb n="p.259"/> above,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The mention of Sirae has been lost
                        at the end of XLIV.</note> despatches from King Perseus were brought <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> to him by
                    three envoys of no rank. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When Paulus perceived
                    them in soiled garb and with tears streaming, it is said that he himself wept
                    for the lot of man, since that king who shortly before, discontented with the
                    kingdom of Macedonia, had attacked the Dardanians and Illyrians and summoned the
                    Bastarnae to his aid, had now lost his army, and, stripped of his kingdom and
                    driven to a small island, was a suppliant, protected by the sanctity of a
                    temple, not by his own powers. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But after he
                    read <quote>King Perseus to the Consul Paulus, greeting,</quote> the folly of
                    the man who did not realize the state of his fortunes erased all pity.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Therefore, although the body of the letter
                    contained entreaties far from royal, yet that embassy was dismissed without an
                    answer and without dispatches. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Perseus
                    understood what title the conquered must forget; therefore other dispatches,
                    sent under his name without title, requested and obtained the sending of certain
                    persons with whom he might discuss the status and the terms of his new lot.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Three envoys were sent, Publius Lentulus,
                    Aulus Postumius Albinus, and Aulus Antonius. Nothing was accomplished by that
                    embassy, since Perseus clung with all his might to the title of king, while
                    Paulus urged him to entrust himself and all he had to the discretion and mercy
                    of the Roman People. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these negotiations were under way, the
                    fleet of Gnaeus Octavius put in at Samothrace. He too was attempting to entice
                    the king to surrender now by menaces, now by hope, while the threat of force was
                    kept imminent, when a matter brought about either by chance or plan lent him
                    assistance in his <pb n="p.261"/> undertaking. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Lucius Atilius, a prominent young <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 168</note> man, noticing that the people of Samothrace
                    were in meeting, requested the magistrates for permission to address the people
                    briefly. Permission being granted, he asked: </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> My hosts of Samothrace, is our understanding correct or false that this
                        island is sacred, and all its soil is revered and unprofaned? </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When all agreed that it was as sacred as he
                    believed, he said, <quote> Why then has a murderer polluted it, profaned it with
                        the blood of King Eumenes, and although the preamble to every rite warns
                        away from the holy things those whose hands are not pure, why do you yet
                        permit your sanctuary to be defiled by the blood-stained person of a
                        brigand? </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The story how Evander had nearly succeeded in
                    murdering King Eumenes at Delphi <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >Described in XLII. xv-xvi.</note> had been bruited abroad throughout all
                    the cities of Greece. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Consequently, the
                    Samothracians decided that, apart from the fact that they saw that they and
                    their whole island and shrine were in the power of the Romans, the reproach
                    against them was a just one. They sent Theondas, the chief magistrate of their
                    community —they call him <quote>king</quote> —to Perseus to announce that
                    Evander the Cretan was being accused of murder; <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> that there was a court of theirs established by ancestral custom to try those
                    who were alleged to have brought unclean hands within the sacred precincts of
                    the temple; and that if Evander trusted that he was innocent of the capital
                    charge brought against him, <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> he should appear
                    to defend himself, whereas, if he dared not entrust himself to the court, he
                    should free the temple of profanation, and provide for his own safety. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.263"/>
                <p> Perseus called Evander aside and said that he by <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> no means advised him to
                    stand trial, for he would have neither a good case nor sufficient influence.
                    (Behind his words was the fear that Evander, if condemned, would reveal the king
                    as the sponsor of the abominable crime.) What was there left, said Perseus,
                    except to die bravely? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Evander made no open
                    refusal, but saying that he preferred to die by poison rather than the steel, he
                    secretly made ready for escape. When this was reported to the king, he feared
                    that the anger of the Samothracians would turn against him, on the ground that
                    he had caused the guilty party to escape punishment; so he ordered Evander
                    killed. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When this murder had been hastily
                    perpetrated, it suddenly occurred to Perseus that he had beyond doubt taken on
                    himself the guilt of Evander. The latter had wounded Eumenes at Delphi, he had
                    killed Evander at Samothrace; and so two of the most sacred shrines on earth had
                    been profaned with human blood at his sole instigation. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> He turned aside accusation on this score by bribing
                    Theondas to report to the people that Evander had committed suicide. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> However, when he committed this terrible crime
                    against his pre-eminent remaining friend, who had been tested in so many
                    vicissitudes and had been betrayed because he had not betrayed the king, Perseus
                    turned all hearts against him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Each one
                    individually deserted to the Romans. </p>
                <p> By fleeing they forced the king too, left almost alone, to adopt some plan of
                    flight; finally he appealed to Oroandes the Cretan, who knew the coast of Thrace
                    from having made trading voyages there, to take him aboard a scout-ship and
                    carry him <pb n="p.265"/> to Cotys. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There is a
                    harbour Demetrium on a <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 168</note> certain headland of Samothrace; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> A temple of Demeter stood there, of. below, sec. 6. The
                        temple is mentioned in I.G. XII. 8. The promontory of Kamariotissa marks the
                        site approximately. </note> the scout-ship was anchored there. At sun-down
                    the needful equipment was carried to the shore; all the money that could be
                    brought secretly was also carried down. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In the
                    middle of the night, the king himself with three companions of his flight went
                    by a back door of the house into a garden next to his bedroom and thence, after
                    scrambling with difficulty over a wall, reached the sea. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Perseus' wife accompanied him, according to Plutarch,
                            <hi rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> xxvi, and was one of the causes of
                        delay, being quite unathletic. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Oroandes had waited just long enough for the
                    money to be brought down, and in the early darkness had weighed anchor and was
                    sailing directly for Crete. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the ship was
                    not found at the harbour, Perseus wandered about for some time on the shore and,
                    finally, fearing the imminent approach of dawn, did not dare to return to the
                    house where he was entertained, but took cover near an out-of-the-way corner on
                    one side of the temple. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Among the Macedonians there were Royal Pages,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">These pages are also described by
                        Curtius VIII. vi. 2.</note> so-called, sons of the chief men chosen to wait
                    upon the king; this troop, having accompanied the king in his flight had not
                    even then left him, until by order of Gnaeus Octavius, announcement was made by
                    a herald that if the Royal <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> Pages and the
                    other Macedonians who were in Samothrace surrendered to the Romans, they would
                    secure their safety, their freedom, and all their possessions which they either
                    had with them, or had left in Macedonia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At
                    this word, they all made their way to the Romans, and reported their names to
                    Gaius Postumius, a military tribune. The king's young children were also handed
                    over to <pb n="p.267"/> Octavius by Ion of Thessalonica, and no one was left
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> with
                    the king except Philip, his oldest son. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then
                    Perseus surrendered himself and his son to Octavius, railing at his fortune and
                    the gods in whose temple he was, who had done nothing to aid their suppliant.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Diodorus XXIX. 28 points out that
                        he had forfeited his claim on the gods by his disloyalty toward his brother. </note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He was ordered to be placed in the flagship,
                    and what was left of the money was brought there. The fleet immediately sailed
                    back to Amphipolis. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Thence Octavius sent the
                    king to the consul's camp, sending ahead dispatches to inform the consul that
                    the king was a prisoner and was being brought to him. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thinking that this was a second victory, as
                    indeed it was, Paulus offered sacrifice at this message; he read the letter of
                    the praetor before his assembled council, sent Quintus Aelius Tubero <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The son-in-law of Paulus, according to
                        Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> v. </note> to meet the king, and
                    ordered the others to remain in full numbers at headquarters. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> So great a crowd never gathered elsewhere for any sight. In
                    the previous generation King Syphax <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >His story is told in XXX. xiii.</note> had been brought as prisoner into a
                    Roman camp, but apart from the fact that he was not comparable either as to his
                    own reputation or that of his nation, he was a mere appendage to the war with
                    Carthage, as Gentius was to this one with Macedonia. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Perseus was the chief enemy, and not only his own
                    reputation and that of his father, grandfather, and the rest to whom he was
                    related by blood and stock made him a cynosure, but the glory of Philip and
                    Alexander the Great, who made the Macedonians masters of the world, radiated <pb
                        n="p.269"/> from him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Perseus entered the
                    camp in dark-coloured <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 168</note> garb, with his son, but unattended by any other of his
                    people whose presence as a sharer of his downfall might have made him more
                    pitiable. He was unable to proceed because of the crowd rushing to gaze at him,
                    until lictors were sent by the consul to clear a path to the headquarters.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consul rose to meet him, though he
                    ordered the others to keep their seats, and advancing a few steps offered his
                    hand to the king as he entered, raised him when he fell at his feet, not
                    allowing him to clasp his knees, brought him into the tent, and bade him be
                    seated opposite the officers called as council. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The first question put was, by what wrong had
                    he been driven to make war on the Roman People with such determined enmity as to
                    bring himself and his kingdom into utmost danger? <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> While all awaited an answer, he gazed silently at the
                    ground for a long time and wept. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then the consul asked again: <quote> If you
                        had received the kingdom as a young man, I should indeed be less surprised
                        that you were unaware how powerful the Roman People is as a friend or as an
                        enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As it is, since you had a part in
                        the war which your father waged with us, and since you were aware of the
                        peace that followed, which we observed with the utmost faithfulness toward
                        him, what reasoning led you to prefer war rather than peace with men whose
                        power in war, whose good faith in peace, you had alike tested? </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When no reply either to the question or the
                    accusation was forthcoming, the consul continued, <quote> However that may be,
                        whether it has occurred through human mistake or chance or law of nature, be
                        of good <pb n="p.271"/> cheer. The misfortunes of many kings and of many
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note>
                        peoples have shown that the mercy of the Roman People offers you not only
                        hope, but an almost positive assurance of safety. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This the consul said in Greek to Perseus; then
                    he continued in Latin to his staff: <quote> You see before you a notable example
                        of the changefulness of human affairs. I say this especially for you, young
                        men. Therefore it is proper to offer no insult or violence to anyone, while
                        one is in favourable circumstances, and not to trust to one's present
                        fortune, since no one knows what evening will bring. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> He will be truly a man, in a word, whose spirit is
                        neither deflected from its course by the breath of prosperity, nor broken by
                        misfortune. </quote>
                </p>
                <p> When the meeting was dismissed, the task of guarding the king was assigned to
                    Quintus Aelius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On that day Perseus was
                    entertained by the consul, and every other token of respect was shown him which
                    could be shown under such circumstances. </p>
                <p> The army was then released to winter quarters. <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Amphipolis received most of the troops, the
                    nearby cities the rest. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This was the end of the war between the Romans
                    and Perseus, after four years of steady campaigning, and also the end of a
                    kingdom famed over a large part of Europe and all of Asia. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> They reckoned Perseus as the twentieth after Caranus, who
                    founded the kingdom. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Justinus XXXII.
                        2. 6 says the thirtieth king, Eusebius (Schöne I, col. 242), the
                        thirty-ninth. Herodotus VIII. 138, names Perdiccas as the founder of the
                        dynasty. </note> Perseus ascended the throne in the consulship of Quintus
                    Fulvius and Lucius Manlius, and was recognized as king by the senate in the
                    consulship of Marcus Junius and Aulus Manlius; his reign lasted eleven years.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Macedonian nation was of no great
                    reputation until the time of <pb n="p.273"/> Philip, son of Amyntas. Later, when
                    it had proceeded <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        168</note> to expand under him, it was still confined within the bounds of
                    Europe, though embracing all Greece and part of Thrace and Illyricum. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Thereafter it overflowed into Asia, and Alexander, in
                    the thirteen years of his reign, first brought under his sway all the well-nigh
                    boundless empire that had belonged to the Persians, and then traversed Arabia
                    and India, where the Indian Ocean embraces the uttermost ends of the earth.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At that time the empire and name of the
                    Macedonians was greatest on earth; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> thereafter
                    at the death of Alexander it was torn into many kingdoms, as each leader
                    snatched at resources for his own account, and its strength was dismembered; yet
                    it endured for a hundred and fifty years <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Polybius XXIX. 21 (6c) gives this figure; it was 155
                        years from the death of Alexander. </note> from the topmost pinnacle of its
                    fortune to its final end. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When a report of the Roman victory penetrated
                    to Asia, Antenor, who was lying off Phanae with his fleet of scout-ships,
                    crossed from there to Cassandria. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">This
                        naval activity was described in XLIV. xxix. 1-5.</note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When Gaius Popilius, who was at Delos to
                    protect ships making for Macedonia, heard that the war had been brought to an
                    end in Macedonia and that the enemy scout-ships had left their post, he for his
                    part dismissed the ships of Attalus and proceeded to sail for Egypt to complete
                    the mission <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> on which he had started, so that
                    he might be able to meet Antiochus before he reached the walls of Alexandria.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As the ambassadors were sailing past Asia
                    and came to Loryma, a harbour slightly more than twenty miles from Rhodes and
                    situated <pb n="p.275"/> exactly opposite to the city, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> On the peninsula northward from Rhodes; mentioned by
                        Thucydides VIII. 43, and Strabo XIV. ii. 4 and 14 (652, 655). </note> the
                    chief men of Rhodes <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        168</note> met them (for the report of the victory had by now been brought
                    to that city also) with the request that they put in at Rhodes; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> for, said the Rhodians, it was a matter touching the
                    reputation and safety of their city that the envoys should personally become
                    acquainted with everything which had been done and was being done at Rhodes, and
                    that they should carry back to Rome facts ascertained by themselves, not popular
                    rumours. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After many refusals, they induced the
                    envoys to endure a short delay of their voyage for the sake of the safety of an
                    allied city. After their arrival at Rhodes, the same leaders also dragged them
                    by entreaty before an assembly. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The arrival of
                    the envoys increased rather than diminished the fear of the city; <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> for Popilius rehearsed every hostile word or act
                    during this war either on the part of individuals or of the commonwealth, and
                    being a man of harsh temperament, <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> he
                    increased the savage effect of his remarks by his grim face and prosecutor's
                    tone, so that, since he had no reason for a personal quarrel with Rhodes, the
                    people guessed from the bitterness of one Roman senator what the attitude of the
                    whole senate was toward them. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The speech of Gaius Decimius was milder, for
                    he laid the blame for many of the offences mentioned by Popilius not at the door
                    of the people as a whole, but at that of a few agitators; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> these, he said, whose tongues were for sale, had written
                    the decrees full of fawning upon the king and had sent those embassies
                    concerning which the Rhodians had always felt as much shame as regret. All these
                    acts, said Decimius, would, if the people's reason was sound, recoil upon the
                    heads of the guilty. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.277"/>
                <p> There was great approval felt for his speech, but no <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> more because he relieved
                    the commons of blame than because he assigned responsibility to the guilty.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> And so when the leaders of the Rhodians
                    answered the Romans, their speeches were by no means as pleasing when the
                    speaker tried at all costs to extenuate the charges made by Popilius, as when he
                    agreed with Decimius in urging that the responsible persons should expiate their
                    wrong. A decree was therefore passed at once that anyone convicted of saying or
                    doing anything against the Romans in behalf of Perseus should be put to death.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Some had left the city on the arrival of
                    the Romans, others committed suicide. After a delay of not more than five days
                    at Rhodes, the ambassadors left for Alexandria. <milestone n="15" unit="section"
                    /> The Rhodians proceeded no less zealously to prosecute trials according to the
                    decree passed in the presence of the Romans. This unflagging zeal in carrying
                    the matter out was produced as much by the mildness of Decimius as by the
                    harshness of Popilius. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While this was going on, Antiochus had left
                    Alexandria after an unsuccessful trial of the fortifications and had taken
                    control of the rest of Egypt. He left at Memphis the elder Ptolemy <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.,</hi> Ptolemy VI Philometor; the younger was
                        Euergetes II. </note> whose claim to the throne he was pretending to support
                    with his army, in order that he might attack the winner presently, and led his
                    army off into Syria. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Ptolemy was well aware of
                    this ulterior motive too, and thought that, as long as his younger brother was
                    cowed by fear of a siege, he might be restored to Alexandria <pb n="p.279"/>
                    with the aid of his sister and without opposition on <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> the part of his brother's
                    friends. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He therefore kept sending, first to
                    his sister, then to his brother and his friends, until he made an amicable
                    settlement with them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Suspicion was directed
                    against Antiochus because, though he had turned over the rest of Egypt to
                    Ptolemy, he had left a strong garrison at Pelusium. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> It was evident that the key to Egypt was in Antiochus'
                    hands, so that he could reinvade it when he wished. The upshot of a civil war
                    between the brothers would be that the winner, worn out by the struggle, would
                    be no match for Antiochus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This wise reasoning
                    by the elder brother was gratefully accepted by the younger brother and his
                    associates; the sister gave much assistance not only by her advice, but by her
                    entreaties. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Accordingly, peace was made by
                    general agreement, and the elder Ptolemy returned to Alexandria, without
                    opposition even on the part of the mob, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Who had proclaimed the younger brother king.</note>
                    which had suffered throughout the war from a scarcity of all supplies not only
                    during the siege, but after the enemy had left the walls, because nothing came
                    in from Egypt. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It would have been in order for Antiochus to
                    rejoice at this conclusion had he led his army into Egypt for the purpose of
                    restoring Ptolemy —the specious plea that he had employed in statements to all
                    the states of Asia and Greece either when he received embassies or sent out
                    messages. But he was so incensed that he prepared for war against the two
                    brothers with much more urgency and bitterness than against the one. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> He immediately sent a fleet to Cyprus; and in early
                    spring <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Of <date when="-0168">168
                            B.C.</date> ; he had made preparations in 171, XLII. xxix. 5; the first
                        invasion was in 170, the reconciliation of the brothers presumably in <date
                            when="-0169">169 B.C.</date> Polybius, on whom Livy based this account,
                        records these events in XXVIII. 19-23; XXIX. 23 (8). 26-7 (7a, 11). </note>
                    he himself advanced <pb n="p.281"/> with his army into Hollow Syria on his way
                    to Egypt. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        168</note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Near Rhinocolura envoys from Ptolemy met him,
                    offering thanks for his assistance in recovering Ptolemy's ancestral throne and
                    requesting that he should not undo his act of kindness and rather say what he
                    wanted done than shift from ally to enemy and act by force of arms. Antiochus
                    replied that he would recall his fleet and lead back his army on no other terms
                    than the cession to him of all Cyprus, Pelusium, and the region which lies
                    around the Pelusian mouth of the Nile. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He
                    also named a day before which he must receive the report of the execution of his
                    terms. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the time allotted for the truce had
                    expired, Antiochus' officers sailed to Pelusium via the mouth of the Nile, while
                    he marched through the Arabian Desert and, after being received by the
                    inhabitants of Memphis and the rest <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> of the
                    Egyptians, partly through good-will and partly through fear, he came down to
                    Alexandria by short marches. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Antiochus crowned himself king of Egypt, and issued coins in that capacity,
                        see Naphtali Lewis, <hi rend="italics">Classical Philo-</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">logy</hi> 44 (1949), pp. 32-3. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When he had crossed the river at Eleusis, a
                    place four miles away from Alexandria, the Roman envoys met him. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> As they approached, he greeted them and offered his
                    hand to Popilius; whereat Popilius handed him the tablets containing the decree
                    of the senate in writing, and bade him read this first of all. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> On reading the decree, he said that he would call in his
                    friends and consider what he should do; Popilius, in accordance with the usual
                    harshness of his temper, <pb n="p.283"/> drew a circle around the king with a
                    rod that he <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        168</note> carried in his hand, and said, <quote> Before you step out of
                        this circle, give me an answer which I may take back to the senate. </quote>
                    After the king had hesitated a moment, struck dumb by so violent an order, he
                    replied, <quote>I shall do what the senate decrees.</quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Only then did Popilius extend his hand to the
                    king as to an ally and friend. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Later, when Antiochus had quitted Egypt by the
                    appointed day, and the envoys had also confirmed by their own weighty approval
                    the agreement of the brothers, who with great difficulty had settled on terms of
                    peace, the Romans sailed for Cyprus, whence they sent away the fleet of
                    Antiochus which had already defeated the Egyptian ships in battle. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> According to Polybius XXIX. 27. 10,
                        this victory of Antiochus' forces was on land. </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This embassy gained a great reputation among
                    the nations, because Egypt had clearly been taken away from Antiochus after he
                    had possession of it, and their ancestral kingdom had been restored to the House
                    of Ptolemy. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The term of one of the consuls of this year
                    was distinguished by a notable victory; the reputation of the other was
                    correspondingly undistinguished, because he did not have the wherewithal for
                    achievement. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At the very outset, when he
                    proclaimed a day for his legions to assemble, he entered the sacred enclosure
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Perhaps a special one laid out for
                        this ceremony.</note> without taking the auspices. When the augurs were
                    consulted on this matter, they declared that the day had been wrongfully set.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The consul set out for Gaul, and had a
                    fixed camp near Campi Macri <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Also
                        mentioned above, XLI. xviii. 5-6.</note> close to Mounts Sicimina and
                    Papinus. Later he spent the winter in the same region with <pb n="p.285"/> the
                    allies of the Latin Name; the Roman legions had <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> remained at Rome, because
                    the day for the assembly of the army was wrongfully appointed. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The praetors also went to their provinces,
                    except Gaius Papirius Carbo, to whom Sardinia had fallen. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> The senate decreed that he should conduct at Rome the court
                    for suits between citizens and aliens, for this also had been allotted to him.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Anicius, the commander in
                        Illyricum, had first been assigned as <hi rend="italics">praetor
                            peregrinus.</hi> The praetor for Sardinia was often assigned to special
                        tasks (cf. XXXIX. xxxviii. 3; XL. xxxvii. 4; xliii. 2), while his
                        predecessor, in this case P. Fonteius Capito (cf. XLIII. xv. 3), continued
                        in office; see also below, xvi. 4. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Popilius, too, and the embassy which had been
                    sent to Antiochus returned to Rome. They reported that the disputes between the
                    kings had been settled and the army led out of Egypt into Syria. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Afterwards the envoys of the kings themselves
                    arrived. Antiochus' envoys reported that to the king peace had seemed preferable
                    to any conquest, since it was the wish of the senate, and that Antiochus had
                    obeyed the orders of the Roman envoys as if they had been gods. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Then they presented congratulations on the victory, to
                    which the king would have contributed his aid, they said, if any demand had been
                    made upon him. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Ptolemy's envoys <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The embassy was from both Ptolemies, according to
                        Polybius XXX. 16. </note> offered thanks in the names of the king and
                    Cleopatra together; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> they owed, they said, more
                    to the Roman senate and people than to their own parents, more than to the
                    immortal gods, since they had been freed by the Romans from a most wretched
                    state of siege, and had recovered the ancestral kingdom which they had almost
                    lost. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.287"/>
                <p> The senate's reply to Antiochus was that he had <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> done what was right and
                    proper in obeying the envoys, and that the Roman senate and people were pleased.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To the king and queen of Egypt, Ptolemy
                    and Cleopatra, the reply was that the senate was very happy if by its agency
                    something good and beneficial had come to pass, and that the senate would use
                    its best efforts to convince them that the greatest bulwark of their reign was
                    founded on the good faith of the Roman people. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Instructions were given to Gaius Papirius the praetor that he should see that
                    the customary presents were sent to the envoys. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> Despatches from Macedonia were then introduced, calculated to redouble the
                    rejoicing over the victory; they reported that King Perseus was a prisoner of
                    the consul. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After the royal embassies were dismissed, a
                    dispute was heard between envoys from Pisa and from Luna. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The colony at Luna was established in <date
                            when="-0177">177 B.C.</date> , see XLI. xiii. 5. Luna at this time was
                        reckoned as belonging to Cisalpine Gaul, the boundary of Italy proper
                        running between it and Pisa; in earlier times it had been Etruscan. </note>
                    The Pisans complained that Roman colonists were driving them off their land,
                    whereas the men of Luna declared that the land in question had been assigned to
                    them by the board of three. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The senate sent
                    five men to investigate the facts about the boundary and make a decision,
                    namely, Quintus Fabius Buteo, Publius Cornelius Blasio, Titus Sempronius Musca,
                    Lucius Naevius Balbus, and Gaius Apuleius Saturninus. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> From the brothers Eumenes, Attalus, and
                    Athenaeus a joint embassy of congratulation on the victory arrived. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Perhaps the same as the embassy
                        mentioned below, xix.</note> When Masgaba, too, the son of King Masinissa,
                    landed from his ship at Puteoli, he was met by Lucius Manlius the quaestor who
                    had been sent with money to meet him, to escort him at <pb n="p.289"/> public
                    expense to Rome. On Masgaba's arrival, a <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> meeting of the senate was
                    at once held for him. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> There the young man
                    spoke so as to make matters pleasing by their nature even more pleasing by his
                    words. He recalled how much infantry and cavalry, how many elephants, and how
                    much grain his father had sent to Macedonia during those four years. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> He said that there were two matters which brought a
                    blush to his father's cheeks: first, that the senate had requested through
                    envoys what they needed for the war, and had not ordered it, and secondly, that
                    they had sent him money for the grain. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Masinissa remembered, said his son, that he held a kingdom won by the Roman
                    People, and that they had increased it and made it many times as great; he was
                    satisfied with the usufruct of the kingdom, and knew that the ownership and
                    title to it were vested in those who had given it. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> Therefore it was right that they should claim what they
                    wished from him, not request it, nor buy the products of his country that sprang
                    from a soil that was their own gift. Masinissa was and would be satisfied with
                    what the Roman People did not need. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> After
                    Masgaba had set out with this message, he said, horsemen had overtaken him to
                    report that Macedonia had been conquered and to bid him congratulate the senate
                    and point out to them that his father was so rejoiced over this event that he
                    wished to come to Rome and offer sacrifice and thanksgiving to Jupiter, Greatest
                    and Best, on the Capitol; he requested permission from the senate to do this, if
                    they had no objection. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The answer was given to the prince that his
                    father Masinissa was acting as was proper for a good and grateful man, in that
                    he attached to payment due <pb n="p.291"/> for kindness such credit and honour.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On the one hand <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> the Roman People had
                    profited by his brave and loyal aid in the Punic War, and on the other, he had
                    secured his kingdom through the good will of the Roman People; after this
                    balancing of favours, he had performed every possible act of friendship in wars
                    against three kings successively. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Joy over the
                    victory of the Roman People was not surprising in a king who had linked with the
                    fortunes of the Romans the whole hazard of his personal fortunes and those of
                    his realm. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As for thanks to the gods for the
                    victory, let him offer them in his own home; his son would serve as his
                    representative at Rome. The son had also offered sufficient congratulations on
                    his own and his father's behalf. That Masinissa himself should leave his kingdom
                    and go outside of Africa, apart from the fact that it was against his own
                    interests, was also contrary to the public welfare of the Roman People, the
                    senate believed. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When Masgaba requested that Hanno, son of
                    Hamilcar, be demanded as hostage in place of . .., the answer was given that the
                    senate considered it by no means just to exact hostages from the Carthaginians
                    according to the judgment of Masinissa. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    quaestor was ordered to buy gifts for the prince, in accordance with a
                    resolution of the senate, to the amount of one hundred pounds of silver, and to
                    escort him to Puteoli, to provide for all his expenses while he was in Italy,
                    and to hire two ships to convey <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> him and his
                    suite to Africa. Garments were presented to all his suite, both free and slave. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Not very much later dispatches were brought
                    from Masinissa's other son Misagenes, stating that he had been sent with his
                    cavalry to Africa by Lucius Paulus <pb n="p.293"/> after the defeat of Perseus,
                    that on his voyage his <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 168</note> fleet had been scattered in the Adriatic, and he had
                    arrived in ill heath with three ships at Brundisium. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Lucius Stertinius the quaestor was sent to him with the
                    same gifts which had been given at Rome to his brother, and was instructed to
                    see to it that a house for entertainment . . . <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> From Valerius Maximus V. 1. Id, the following matters
                        seem to have been recounted here: the quaestor was to provide for the care
                        of Misagenes, furnish expense-money for him and his suite, and provide ships
                        for the voyage to Africa; also a pound of silver and 500 sesterces apiece
                        were to be given to each cavalryman; Misagenes died. Presumably also the
                        report of the elections, and something about the activity of the censors,
                        prefatory to the following chapter, was included here. Previous activity of
                        the censors was reported in XLIII. xiv-xvi; XLIV. xvi. 8-10. Cf. also the
                        Summary of this book. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Freedmen had been distributed among the four
                    city tribes except for those who had a son over five years old (these they
                    ordered to be reckoned where they <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> had been
                    enrolled at the census immediately previous), and those who had an estate or
                    estates in the country valued at over thirty thousand sesterces . . . <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The lacuna may have contained mention
                        of the country tribes, in which the freedmen with large holdings were
                        allowed. </note> the privilege of enrolling was granted. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Although this arrangement had become established in this
                    way, Claudius said that it was impossible for a censor without a decree of the
                    people to deprive any individual of his ballot, let alone a whole class.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For if, said Claudius, the censor could
                    move a man from his tribe, which was exactly what ordering him to change his
                    tribe meant, he could remove him from all thirty-five tribes, that is, deprive
                    him of citizenship and status as a free man-not determine where he should be
                    enrolled but exclude him from enrolment. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Claudius appears to be indulging in hyperbole, since
                        the private rights of a free citizen were not in question. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This was argued between the two censors;
                    finally they resorted to the following solution: they drew lots publicly in the
                    Hall of <pb n="p.295"/> Liberty for one of the four city tribes, to which they
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note>
                    would consign all those who had been slaves. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The lot of the Esquiline tribe was cast; Tiberius Gracchus announced that they
                    had decided to enrol all freedmen in this tribe. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This matter was regarded by the senate as
                    greatly to the credit of the censors. Thanks were voted to Sempronius, for
                    having persisted in a praiseworthy undertaking, and to Claudius, for not
                    interfering. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> More men were removed from the
                    senate than by former censors, and more also ordered to sell their horses. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Previous instances of severity on the
                        part of these censors are recorded in XLIII. xv. 6; xvi. 1; XLIV. xvi. 8.
                    </note> All alike were by both censors removed from their tribe and made <hi
                        rend="italics">aerarii;</hi> nor was the disgrace of anyone who had been
                    blacklisted by the one relieved by the other. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    When the censors asked that their term of a year and a half be prolonged in
                    order that they might, as was customary, see to repairs to buildings and inspect
                    the public works for which they had contracted, the request was vetoed by the
                    tribune Gnaeus Tremellius, because he had not been chosen for the senate. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In this same year Gaius Cicereius dedicated a
                    temple to Moneta on the Alban Mount five years after he vowed it. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> His vow is recorded in XLII. vii. 1;
                        his triumph, on the Alban Mount, in XLII. xxi. 7. Dio Cassius XXXIX. 20,
                        records as a portent that <quote>a small temple of Juno, on a certain table,
                            facing the east, was turned to the north.</quote> Perhaps the curious
                        mention of a table ( <hi rend="italics">trapeza</hi> ) is an error due to
                        the association of Juno Moneta with monetary matters, of. the monetary
                        associations of <hi rend="italics">trapeze.</hi>
                    </note> In this year Lucius Postumius Albinus was consecrated <hi rend="italics"
                        >as flamen</hi> of Mars. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                        death of the previous <hi rend="italics">flamen</hi> is recorded in XLIV.
                        xviii. 7. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the new consuls Quintus Aelius and Marcus
                    Junius <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Both these consuls were
                        plebeians, as in <date when="-0172">172 B.C.</date> , XLII. x. 9. 172 was
                        the first year in which two plebeians were elected, according to the Fasti
                        Capitolini, C.I.L.2 I. i., p. 25. </note> put to the senate the question of
                    provinces, the Fathers voted that Spain should again <pb n="p.297"/> be made two
                    provinces, after having been one during <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> the Macedonian War;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> also that the same officers, Lucius Paulus
                    and Lucius Anicius, should command in Macedonia and Illyricum until on the
                    advice of senatorial envoys they had made a settlement for these states which
                    had been upset by war, and which were to be given a constitution other than
                    monarchical. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To the consuls Pisa and Gaul were
                    assigned with two legions apiece, each legion to be composed of five thousand
                    two hundred infantry and four hundred cavalry. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The number sounds like the allied cavalry; a reference
                        to Roman cavalry and allied infantry may have been lost. The usual number of
                        Roman cavalry is 300, see XXII. xxxvi. 3; but the number 400 also appears in
                        XXIII. xxxiv. 13 and XL. xxxvi. 8. </note> The assignments for the praetors
                    were: to Quintus Cassius, the City Praetorship; to Manius Juventius Thalna, the
                    jurisdiction over aliens; to Tiberius Claudius Nero, Sicily; to Gnaeus Fulvius,
                    Hither Spain; to Gaius Licinius Nerva, Farther Spain. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Aulus Manlius Torquatus was assigned Sardinia, but was
                    unable to go to his province, since he was held by vote of the senate to preside
                    over trials for capital crimes. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Again
                        the new praetor did not go to Sardinia, see above, p. 284, note 1. For
                        similar special inquiries into crime, cf. XL. xliii. 2; XXXIX. xxxviii. 3;
                        xli. 5. For Spain cf. p. 405, note 1. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The question of the prodigies which had been
                    reported was next put to the senate. The temple of the Household Gods on the
                    Velia had been struck by lightning, as well as two gates and a section of wall
                    in the town of Minervium. At Anagnia there had been a rain of earth and at-
                    Lanuvium a meteor had been seen in the sky; and at Calatia on state-owned land
                    Marcus Valerius, a Roman citizen, reported that blood had trickled from his
                    hearth for three days and two nights. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Especially for this last the Board of Ten was ordered to consult the books; they
                        <pb n="p.299"/> proclaimed to the people a single day of prayer and <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> offered a
                    sacrifice of fifty goats in the forum. Because of the other prodigies, another
                    day of prayer was observed at all the banquet-tables of the gods, sacrifice with
                    greater victims was offered, and the city purified. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Another matter concerning the paying of
                    respects to the immortal gods was the senate's decree that, whereas the enemy
                    had been conquered and the kings Perseus and Gentius along with Macedonia and
                    Illyricum were under the sway of the Roman People, therefore the praetors
                    Quintus Cassius and Manius <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> Juventius should
                    see to the presentation at all the banquet-tables of the gods of gifts as great
                    as those given in the consulship of Appius Claudius and Marcus Sempronius
                    because of the victory over King Antiochus. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> These are mentioned in XXXVI. ii. 2-5; the consuls
                        served in <date when="-0185">185 B.C.</date>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Ten commissioners for Macedonia and five for
                    Illyricum were then appointed, on whose advice Lucius Paulus and Lucius Anicius
                    might arrange the settlements. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> First those for
                    Macedonia were named: Aulus Postumius Luscus and Gaius Claudius, both
                    ex-censors, Quintus Fabius Labeo, Quintus Marcius Philippus, and Gaius Licinius
                    Crassus, who was Paulus' colleague in the consulship and at that time was in
                    charge of Gaul, his term of command having been extended. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> To these ex-consuls were added Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus,
                    Servius Cornelius Sulla, Lucius Junius, Titus Numisius Tarquiniensis, and Aulus
                    Terentius Varro. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For Illyricum the following
                    were named: Publius Aelius Ligus, an exconsul, Gaius Cicereius and Gnaeus
                    Baebius <pb n="p.301"/> Tamphilus (the latter had been praetor the previous
                    year, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note>
                    the former many years before <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Five
                        years before, see above, xv. 9.</note> ), Publius Terentius Tuscivicanus,
                    and Publius Manilius. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Next the consuls were instructed by the
                    Fathers that, since one of them should relieve Gaius Licinius, who had been
                    appointed commissioner, in Gaul, they ought as early as possible either to agree
                    on their provinces or to draw lots. They accordingly drew lots. Pisa fell to
                    Marcus Junius, Gaul to Quintus Aelius. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    senate voted that before Junius went to his field of activity, he should present
                    to the senate the embassies which had assembled in Rome from all quarters to
                    offer congratulations. Moreover, although men were being sent of sufficient
                    calibre to justify the hope that by their advice the generals would establish
                        <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> nothing unworthy of either the mercy or
                    the high position of the Roman People, yet discussions went on in the senate too
                    as to general considerations, so that the commissioners might carry from home to
                    the generals a full outline of policy. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> First of all it was voted that the Macedonians
                    and Illyrians should be given their independence, so that it should be clear to
                    all nations that the forces of the Roman People brought not slavery to free
                    peoples, but on the contrary, freedom to the enslaved. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The senate wished nations which were free to consider that
                    their freedom was assured and lasting under the protection of the Roman People,
                    and that those who lived under kings should feel for the time being that their
                    rulers were milder and more just under the eye of the Roman People, and, if at
                    any time their kings should make war on the Roman People, that the outcome of
                    the war would bring victory to the Romans, but freedom to <pb n="p.303"/>
                    themselves. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was also voted to discontinue
                    the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note>
                    leasing of the Macedonian mines, a source of immense revenue, and of rural
                    estates, <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> for these could not be farmed
                    without a contractor, and where there was a contractor, there either the
                    ownership by the state lapsed, or no freedom was left to the allied people.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The reasoning is perhaps that of
                        Cato, who favoured Macedonian <quote>freedom,</quote> see Spartianus, <hi
                            rend="italics">Hadrian</hi> 5; for the attitude toward the financiers,
                        cf. XXXII. xxvii. 4; XXXIX. xliv. 8-9; XLIII. xvi. Below, xxix. 11, the
                        specific arrangement for the mines is mentioned: gold and silver mining was
                        prohibited, but iron and copper might be worked. The estates were no doubt
                        those of the king. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was impossible, the senate thought, for
                    even the Macedonians to farm these resources; for where there was booty as a
                    prize for administrators, in that state there would never be a lack of reasons
                    for conspiracies and strife. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Finally, fearing
                    that if there were a common legislature for the nation, some relentless
                    demagogue would turn the freedom given in healthy moderation into the licence
                    which brings ruin, the senate voted to divide Macedonia into four sections, so
                    that each might have its own legislature. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It
                    was further resolved that Macedonia should pay to the Roman People half the
                    taxes which they had been accustomed to pay to their kings. Like instructions
                    were given for Illyricum. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The details were
                    left to the generals and the commissioners themselves, for which the present
                    discussion would lay a surer foundation of planning. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> From xii. 9 to this point, Livy seems to have followed
                        Roman annalists; he now draws from Polybius XXX. 1-5. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Among the many embassies from kings, nations,
                    and peoples Attalus, the brother of King Eumenes, especially drew to himself the
                    eyes and <pb n="p.305"/> minds of everyone. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> According to Polybius, the warmth of this reception
                        suggested to Attalus the possibility of supplanting his brother. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For he was received by those <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> who had
                    served with him in this war in much more cordial fashion than if King Eumenes
                    himself had come. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Two reasons honourable in
                    outward view brought him to Rome, first the congratulations suitable to the
                    recent victory in which he himself had aided, and second, complaint about the
                    uprising of the Galatians and the disaster suffered thereby, which threatened
                    destruction to the kingdom itself. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Underneath
                    he cherished a secret hope of honours and rewards from the senate which he could
                    hardly accept without disloyalty to his brother. For there were also certain
                    untrustworthy Roman advisers to stimulate his self-seeking with hope; <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> the view, they said, held in Rome about Attalus and
                    Eumenes was that the former was a sure friend to the Romans, while the latter
                    was a faithful ally neither to the Romans nor to Perseus; accordingly it could
                    hardly be determined whether the senate would be more disposed to grant his
                    requests for himself or those against his brother —to <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> such an extent did one and all make every concession to the
                    one, but withhold any from the other. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Attalus was, as the facts showed, one of those
                    men who would desire whatever hope might promise; but the wise advice of one
                    friend tightened the reins, as it were, on his spirit elated by success.
                    Stratius, a physician, was with him, sent to Rome by the uneasy Eumenes
                    precisely to keep an eye on the actions of his brother and to give loyal advice,
                    if he saw any failure in loyalty. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This
                    Stratius made his approach to ears already filled and a mind already <pb
                        n="p.307"/> tempted, and by offering well-timed remarks won an almost <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> lost
                    cause; his argument was that different kingdoms had thrived on different things;
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> the kingdom of Pergamum, being new and not
                    bolstered by any longstanding wealth, was founded on brotherly harmony, because
                    one brother wore the name of king and the distinguishing emblem on his head, but
                    all the brothers ruled. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As for Attalus, who
                    was second in age, who did not consider him as a king? And not only because one
                    could see that his present powers were so great, but because it was beyond doubt
                    that he would reign before many <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> days had
                    passed, for the weakness and age <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >Eumenes was in his late fifties at this time.</note> of Eumenes pointed in
                    that direction, since he was at that time without issue (for Eumenes had not at
                    that time acknowledged the son who reigned after him <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This successor, Attalus III, was born shortly before
                        Eumenes' death, and reigned for 21 years under a regency of his uncle
                        Attalus. (See XLII. xvi. 9 and the note, Vol. XII, p. 339, for the view that
                        Attalus III was actually the son of Attalus II). An illegitimate son of
                        Eumenes, Aristonicus, captured the throne after the death of Attalus III,
                        and fought Rome: cf. Summary LIX. </note> ). What use was there, said
                    Stratius,. in seeking by violence a prize which would automatically fall to him
                    shortly? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Furthermore, the kingdom had been
                    assailed by the fresh tempest of the Galatian uprising, which could hardly be
                    withstood by agreement and harmony in the royal family; but if civil strife were
                    added to the foreign war, no halt could be called. What he was considering was
                    simply preventing his brother from dying as king in order to rob himself of his
                    imminent expectation of the throne. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Even if
                    it were true that either action would bring fame, whether he preserved the
                    kingdom for his brother, or snatched it from him, nevertheless praise for
                    preserving the kingdom, coupled as it was with family loyalty, would still be
                    the better choice. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> But in as much as one <pb
                        n="p.309"/> alternative was in fact despicable and verging on the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> murder of
                    kin, what remained in doubt to keep judgment in suspense? Was he in doubt
                    whether to seek for part of the kingdom, or to seize it all? <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> If he took part, both parts would be weakened by disruption
                    of forces and without a doubt exposed to every kind of injury; if he took all,
                    would his elder brother become a private citizen, or an exile at his age and
                    with his weakness of body, or would Attalus in the end order his brother's
                    death? <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> To say nothing of the end of disloyal
                    brothers as told in legend, the fate of Perseus seemed to be a notable example,
                    for as he bowed himself down at the feet of a conquering enemy, he had laid
                    aside in the temple of Samothrace, as if the gods had been there exacting his
                    punishment, that crown which he had seized by means of a brother's murder.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The very men, said Stratius, who were
                    egging him on, no friends to him, but foes to Eumenes, would praise his loyalty
                    and steadfastness, if he kept faith with his brother to the end. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This reasoning prevailed on the mind of
                    Attalus. On being presented to the senate, therefore, he offered congratulations
                    on the victory; he explained his services during this war, and those of his
                    brother, such as they were, as well as the revolt of the Galatians <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> They were actually independent, but had
                        been warned by Rome to keep the peace, according to XXXVIII. xl. 1; Polybius
                        XXX. 3, also speaks of a <quote>revolt</quote> ( <hi rend="italics"
                            >aponoia</hi> ). </note> which had recently taken place with great
                    disturbance; he requested that the senate should send envoys to the Galatians,
                    to induce them to lay aside their arms. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Having
                    delivered these messages in the interest of his state, he asked for Aenus and
                    Maronea for himself. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Polybius says
                        this request was not granted, because Attalus had disappointed the Roman
                        hope that he would break with his brother. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Thus, after <pb n="p.311"/> disappointing the
                    hopes of those who had supposed that <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 167</note> he would accuse his brother and seek a
                    division of the kingdom, he left the senate-house. Seldom has anyone else, king
                    or citizen, been heard with as much good will and as much general approval;
                    Attalus was honoured with every mark of attention and gift while he was there,
                    and on his departure he was attended with equal ceremony. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Among the many embassies from Asia and Greece,
                    the envoys of the Rhodians especially drew the city's attention. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> For they first appeared in white clothes, as was
                    suitable for those offering congratulations —and had they worn soiled clothes,
                    they might have offered the appearance of men mourning for the fall of Perseus.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> However, after the senate was consulted by
                    Marcus Junius the consul, while the envoys stood in the assembly-ground, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Perhaps on the <hi rend="italics"
                            >Graecostasis,</hi> an open platform, from which foreign envoys watched
                        ceremonies; this was later located in the Forum. </note> whether lodgings,
                    entertainment, and reception before the senate should be provided, and the
                    Fathers had advised that none of the rights of hospitality should be granted in
                    their case, the consul came forth from the senate-house, and in reply to
                        <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> the Rhodians, who said they had come to
                    offer congratulations on the victory and to clear their city of the charges
                    against it, and asked that a session of the senate be held for them, the consul
                    announced that for allies and friends the Romans were accustomed to perform
                    various acts of courtesy and hospitality, one of which was to grant a hearing
                    before the <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> senate, but the Rhodians during
                    this war had not earned the right to be considered in the category of friends
                    and allies. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Formally, the Rhodians
                        were not allies, having preferred to retain complete independence of action,
                        cf. below xxv. 9. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On hearing this, the Rhodians threw themselves
                    on the ground and begged the consul and all who were present not to adopt the
                    principle that new and false charges <pb n="p.313"/> against the Rhodians should
                    outweigh the good <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        167</note> services of long standing of which they themselves were
                    witnesses. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Forthwith the Rhodians put on
                    mourning <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Polybius XXX. 4. 5 says this
                        occurred after the activity of Juventius mentioned just below. </note> and
                    went the rounds of the houses of the chief men begging with tears and entreaties
                    that they would hear the case before passing sentence. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Manius Juventius Thalna, the praetor with
                    jurisdiction over suits between citizens and aliens, was stirring up the people
                    against the Rhodians and had announced a motion to declare war against Rhodes
                        <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> and to choose from the magistrates of
                    this year one to be sent to this war with a fleet (Juventius hoped that he would
                    be the one designated). Such action was opposed by Marcus Antonius and Marcus
                    Pomponius, tribunes of the people. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But not
                    only had the praetor in the first place undertaken the matter in a novel and
                    dangerous fashion, because he <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> was proposing
                    entirely on his own initiative, without previously consulting the senate or
                    notifying the consuls, to put to the people the question, whether it was their
                    will and command that war should be declared against the Rhodians, whereas
                    previously the senate had always been consulted first about war, and then the
                    question brought before the people <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> on the
                    authority of the senate, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> There was
                        precedent, however, for action by the assembly over senatorial opposition,
                        see XXI. lxiii. 3; XXXVIII. xxxvi. 8, and the note. A constitutional
                        question is involved: war was regularly declared by the centuriate assembly,
                        the oldest and least democratic gathering; but could the praetor summon this
                        assembly, except for judicial purposes? The decision to relieve Messana
                        which opened the First Punic War is a near parallel, though one faction of
                        the senate led the appeal to the commons (Polybius I. 11. 1-3). </note> but
                    the tribunes also were in the same position, since the custom was that no one
                    should veto a law until opportunity was given to private citizens <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Not excluding magistrates; Livy takes
                        it for granted that they might address a meeting; for examples, see XXXIV.
                        i. 7; v. 1; XLIII. xvi. 8. </note> to argue for and against the law;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> in this way it had often turned out either
                    that those <pb n="p.315"/> who had not announced that they would exercise the
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> veto
                    did so when the faults of the law had been called to their attention by the
                    speeches of those who opposed the law, or that those who had come intending to
                    veto were overborne by the prestige of those who argued for the law. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> On this occasion the praetor and the tribunes vied
                    with each other in doing everything in the wrong order; the tribunes by their
                    premature veto . . . the haste of the praetor . . . <milestone n="8??"
                        unit="section"/> till the arrival of the general . . <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Polybius XXX. 4.6 says that Antonius, who had removed
                        the praetor Juventius from the Rostra, introduced the Rhodians to the
                        senate; Philophron spoke first, then Astymedes; Livy undertakes to reproduce
                        the speech of the latter, though it is not found in Polybius, who criticized
                        its tone adversely. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> ". .. is. Whether we have done wrong is so far
                    unproved, but we are already suffering all the penalties and disgrace. In former
                    times, after the defeat of Carthage, when Philip or Antiochus had been subdued,
                    on our arrival in Rome we came from public entertainment to the senate-house to
                    offer you our congratulations, gentlemen of the senate, and from the
                    senate-house we mounted to the Capitol, bearing gifts to your gods. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Today from a mean inn, having hardly found shelter
                    for pay and all but ordered like enemies to remain outside the city, we Rhodians
                    in this mourning garb enter the senate-house of Rome —we <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> to whom you lately presented the provinces of Lycia and
                    Caria, who received from you the most unstinted rewards and honours. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> "You are bidding the Macedonians and Illyrians
                    be independent, we hear, though they were slaves before they waged war against
                    you-nor are we jealous of anyone's good fortune, nay rather we recognize the
                    mercy of the Roman People; and will you transform us Rhodians from allies into
                    enemies — <pb n="p.317"/> us, who have been no worse than inactive in this war?
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Surely you are the same Romans who boast that
                    your wars are favoured of Fortune because they are just, nor do you exult as
                    much in the outcome, because you conquer, as in the beginning, because you never
                    undertake war without good cause. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The siege of
                    Messana in Sicily made the Carthaginians your enemies, the siege of Athens, the
                    attempted enslavement of Greece and the aid given Hannibal in money and troops
                    made Philip your foe. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In XXX. xxvi.
                        2-4, Livy reports grievances of Greece against Philip and a report of
                        Macedonian aid to Carthage ( <date when="-0203">203 B.C.</date> ); he also
                        reports the presence of a Macedonian force at Zama (XXX. xxxiii. 6), though
                        no mention is made of them during the battle; and later (XXX. xlii. 4-9) the
                        ransom of Macedonian prisoners, said to be mercenaries, is discussed. -See
                        also XXXI. i. 10. But Polybius says nothing about this aid from Macedonia;
                        Livy may, then, be quoting Roman rumour. Philip and Hannibal, while opposing
                        Rome, seem to have been suspicious of each other, and each anxious that the
                        other should not profit by the elimination of Rome. </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Antiochus was summoned at the initiative of
                    the Aetolians, your enemies; he crossed in person with his fleet to Greece; he
                    seized Demetrias, Chalcis, and the pass of Thermopylae, and sought to cast you
                    out of the tenure of your empire. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> With
                    Perseus, your reason for war was the assault upon your allies, or the murder of
                    princes and chiefs of nations or peoples. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> A statement of these charges is found in XLII. xiii and
                        xl. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Under what heading, pray, shall our downfall
                    be placed, if we are to perish? For the present I am not separating the case for
                    the city from Polyaratus and Dinon, our fellow-citizens, and from those whom we
                    brought to hand over to you. If all we Rhodians were equally guilty, what would
                    be the charge against us in this war? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It
                    would be that we took the side of Perseus and as we took a stand for you in the
                    wars with Antiochus and with Philip against those kings, so now we sided with
                    the king against you. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> How we are accustomed
                    to help our allies, and how vigorously we enter into a war, you may ask Gaius
                    Livius, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. XXXVI. ii. 14 and xlii
                        for Livius; XXXVII. ii. 1 and 10; xiv. 1-3, etc., to lviii. 3-5 for
                        Aemilius. </note> or <pb n="p.319"/> Lucius Aemilius Regillus, who commanded
                    your <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note>
                    fleets in Asia. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Never did your ships enter
                    battle without ours. We fought independently first at Samos, and again off
                    Pamphylia against the command of Hannibal; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    this victory gives us the more pride because, undismayed by the terrible
                    catastrophe by which we had lost in the defeat at Samos a large part of our
                    fleet and a splendid group of young men, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Livy tells of these battles in XXXVII. x-xi and XXXVII.
                        xxiii-xxiv respectively. </note> we dared to go out again to meet the king's
                    fleet as it approached from Syria. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> These
                    matters I have mentioned not for the sake of boasting, for indeed our present
                    fortune does not permit that, but to make it clear how the Rhodians are
                    accustomed to aid their allies. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "The rewards which we received from you after
                    the conquest of Philip and of Antiochus were most abundant. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> These are enumerated in XXXIII. xxx. 11
                        and XXXVIII. xxxix. 13 respectively. </note> If the good fortune which is
                    now yours by the grace of the gods and because of your valour had fallen to
                    Perseus, and we had come to Macedonia to seek a reward from the victorious king,
                    what pray would we say? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> That we had aided him
                    with money or with grain, with forces on land or on sea? What fortress had we
                    held? Where had we fought either under his commanders or by ourselves?
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> If he asked where there had been a soldier
                    of ours, or where a ship, within his lines, what in the world would be our
                    answer? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Perhaps we should be defending
                    ourselves before the conqueror, as now we are before you. For the result we
                    obtained by sending envoys to both parties concerning peace was that we <pb
                        n="p.321"/> won no favour from either side, but incurred even <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> accusation
                    and danger from one of them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Yet Perseus might
                    truly reproach us, as you cannot, gentlemen of the senate, because we sent to
                    you at the beginning of the war envoys to promise you whatever was needed for
                    the war; we would be ready, we said, as in the former wars, with ships, arms,
                    and young men for every demand. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The obstacle
                    to our furnishing these things was of your making, since you for whatever reason
                    spurned our aid at that time. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                        story of this offer, and of the dismissal of the Rhodians as soon as they
                        appeared at the Roman naval station, is told in XLII. xlv; lvi. 6; and
                        Polybius XXVII. 7(6). </note> Neither therefore have we in any way acted as
                    enemies, nor have we failed in the duty of good allies, but we were prevented
                    from performing that duty by you. 'What then? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Has nothing been said or done in your city, Rhodians, which you would wish
                    undone, at which the Roman People might justly take offence? ' From this point I
                    do not propose to defend what has happened —I am not so mad —but I propose to
                    separate the defence of the state from the guilt of private citizens. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> There is no state which will not have not only wicked
                    citizens at certain times but an inexperienced commonalty always.: <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Even in your city I hear that there have been those
                    who pursued ill-gotten gain by toadying to the mob, and that at certain times
                    the commons seceded from you and you lost control of the commonwealth. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Presumably the reference is to the
                        struggles of patricians and plebeians, cf. III. xli. 5-6 and many other
                        passages; for more recent instances, see above, p. 312, note 2. </note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If this could happen in a state-with -so well
                    disciplined a character, can any one marvel that there were some among us who in
                    grasping after the king's friendship led our commons astray with their <pb
                        n="p.323"/> counsel? <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                        implication that the aristocracy of Rhodes favoured Rome is another
                        indication of a situation found in many states. Cf. XLII. xxx. 1. </note>
                    However, these people wrought no <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 167</note> harm beyond slackness in our loyalty as
                    friends. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> I shall not pass over the most
                    serious charge against our city in this war: we sent envoys at the same time
                    both to you and to Perseus on the subject of peace; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> this unhappy plan, through a madman, as we heard later, who
                    was spokesman, became something extremely stupid, for he spoke, it is well
                    known, as the Roman envoy Gaius Popilius might have spoken, whom you sent to
                    turn back from war Kings Antiochus and Ptolemy. But nevertheless this error,
                    whether it should be called arrogance or folly, was no different before you from
                    what it was before Perseus. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The character of
                    states is like that of individual men; some nations are hot-tempered, some bold,
                    some diffident, some over-indulgent in wine, others in sex. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> The people of Athens, report has it, is quick and bold
                    beyond its strength in adventure, the Spartan hesitant and hardly undertaking
                    matters of which it is sure. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This
                        seems to be directly out of Thucydides I. 70-71, and must have been supplied
                        by Livy, for Athens and Sparta had not been conspicuous for these tendencies
                        in the second century. </note>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> I would not deny that all the region of Asia
                    breeds somewhat flighty temperaments, and that our rhetoric is rather inflated
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> But Cicero expressly acquits the
                        Rhodians of indulging in <quote>Asianic</quote> oratory, <hi rend="italics"
                            >Orator</hi> viii. 25. </note> because we might seem to be outstanding
                    among the states in our area-a position due precisely not to our own powers but
                    to your favours and your choice of us. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Enough
                    punishment was meted out to that embassy on the spot and to their faces, when
                    they were sent away with so grim an answer from you. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> But if at that time they paid too small a penalty of
                    disgrace, certainly the present embassy, so <pb n="p.325"/> pitiable and so
                    humble, would be atonement <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">A
                        sin-offering, as if to gods.</note> great <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> enough for an even more
                    arrogant embassy than that other one was. Arrogance, especially of speech, is
                    hated by the hot-tempered, but laughed at by the wise, especially if directed by
                    an inferior against his superior; no one has ever thought it worthy of the
                    death-penalty. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> There was danger, to be sure,
                    that the Rhodians should despise the Romans! Even the gods are assailed by some
                    with overbold language, but we have never heard that any one has on that
                        <milestone n="19??" unit="section"/> account been struck by a thunderbolt. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> What then remains, of which we must clear ourselves, if there was never
                        a hostile action on our part, and if the overweening words of an envoy
                        should produce a disgust of the ear, <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified"> Cf. the Guard to Creon in <hi rend="italics"
                                >Antigone</hi> 317: <quote>Are you stung in the ear, or in the
                                mind?</quote>
                        </note> not the ruin of a city? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> I hear
                        that in conversations among yourselves an appraisal of damages, so as to
                        speak, is being made for our unexpressed desire; <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified"> Appraisal of damages was an important part of Roman
                            legal procedure, both civil and criminal; establishment of fines by
                            statute was rare. The Rhodian is continuing the figure of the prejudged
                            case. The <quote>unexpressed desire</quote> was for Perseus' success, so
                            the Romans thought; the Rhodians' actual preference was probably for a
                            stalemate, since they thrived on the balance of power. </note>
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> some believe, gentlemen of the senate,
                        that we favoured the king and preferred that he should win, and that
                        therefore we should be punished by armed force; others of you feel that we
                        did, to be sure, have this desire, but that we should not on that account be
                        punished by armed force, for, they say, there is no provision in the law,
                        written or unwritten, of any state that he who desires the death of his
                        enemy, but does nothing to bring it about, shall incur capital punishment.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To these men who free us of the
                        penalty, but not of the guilt, we are indeed <pb n="p.327"/> grateful; but
                        these are the terms which we ourselves <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> set for ourselves:
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> if we all have willed that of which we
                        are accused —we do not separate the will from the deed —let us all suffer
                        the penalty; but if some of our leaders favoured you, and others the king, I
                        do not ask that because of us who sided with you the partizans of the king
                        should be untouched; I merely beg that we may not perish because of them.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> You are no more hostile to them than
                        is our state itself, and because they knew this, many of them have either
                        fled or committed suicide; others who have been found guilty by us will be
                        placed in your hands, gentlemen of the senate. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The rest of us at Rhodes have no more deserved
                        punishment during this war than we have deserved gratitude, either. Let the
                        store of our previous helpful acts make good the present omission of
                        service. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> You have waged wars against three
                        kings during these years; let not our slackness in one war be, to our hurt,
                        of more importance than the fact that we fought on your side in two wars.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Take account of Philip, Antiochus, and
                        Perseus as if of the vote of three judges; two acquit us, the third is
                        undecided; suppose that it is for our condemnation; even so, if the Kings
                        were judging us, we should indeed lose our case, but your judgment,
                        gentlemen of the senate, determines whether Rhodes shall exist on earth or
                        shall be destroyed root and branch. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For
                        you are not deliberating about war, gentlemen of the senate; you can declare
                        it, but you cannot wage it, for not a man of Rhodes will bear arms against
                        you. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> If you will not abate your wrath, we
                        shall ask of you time in which to report <pb n="p.329"/> home on this fatal
                        mission; every free person, every <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                            type="margin">B.C. 167</note> man and every woman of us in Rhodes will
                        embark on ships with all our money and, abandoning our homes and our altars,
                        will come to Rome; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> we will heap up in the
                        assembly-ground and in the entry of your senate-house all our gold and our
                        silver, whether owned by the state or its citizens, and will put our persons
                        and those of our wives and children in your power, that we may suffer here
                        whatever we must suffer; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy
                            perhaps had in mind the appeal of the whole people of Tusculum, VIII.
                            xxxvii. 9. </note> far from our sight be the plundering and burning of
                        our city. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Romans may judge that the
                        Rhodians are enemies, but they cannot make them so. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> For we have also in us the power of passing judgmenton
                        ourselves, and we shall never adjudge ourselves your enemies, nor commit any
                        act of hostility, though we suffer the utmost disaster. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Following a speech to this effect all the
                    envoys again cast themselves down in the posture of suppliants, waving their
                    olive-branches; after some time they were made to rise and left the
                    senate-house. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then the roll-call of opinions
                    began. The chief enemies of the Rhodians were those who had been conducting the
                    war in Macedonia as consuls, praetors, or staff-officers. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Great aid to the cause of Rhodes was given by Marcus
                    Porcius Cato, who, though of a harsh temperament, on this occasion played the
                    part of a tolerant and mild senator. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> I shall
                    not include here a pale wraith of this eloquent man by reporting what he said;
                    his own speech is <pb n="p.331"/> preserved in written form, as part of the
                    fifth book of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        167</note> his <quote>Beginnings.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Small parts of this speech are
                        reported by Gellius VI (VII) 3, especially 35. 37. 50, where arguments
                        appear which Livy puts into the mouth of the Rhodian. Cato was an
                        antiimperialist, at least as to expansion eastward, which involved contact
                        with what he regarded as the debilitating culture of Greece, so that his
                        attitude in this matter was sincere, not a pose. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The reply to the Rhodians was couched in such
                    form that they were neither declared enemies nor continued to be allies. </p>
                <p> Philocrates and Astymedes were the leaders of this embassy. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> It was decided that some of them with Philocrates should
                    report to Rhodes about the embassy, while some remained at Rome with Astymedes
                    to keep track of what was being done and inform their people. For the time being
                    orders were given that they should withdraw their governors from Lycia and Caria
                    by a certain date. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> These actions were reported
                    at Rhodes; of themselves they would have been grievous, but were turned into a
                    cause for rejoicing, because the Rhodians were relieved of fear of a greater
                    evil, since they had feared war. So they immediately voted a crown of twenty
                    thousand gold pieces. They sent Theodotus, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Frequently mentioned by Polybius as a pro-Roman, <hi
                            rend="italics">e.g.,</hi> XXVII. 14 (11), where the name is given as
                        Theaedetus. </note> the admiral of their fleet, on this embassy. They wanted
                    to ask the Romans for an alliance in such fashion that no decree of the people
                    concerning it should be passed or committed to dispatches, because if they did
                    not obtain their request, the disgrace of an open repulse would be greater.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The admiral of the fleet alone had the
                    right to negotiate for such a purpose without the passing of any enabling
                    resolution. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For the Rhodians had for all these years <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Polybius XXX. 5. 6 says 140 years; the
                        first embassy from Rhodes recorded by Livy in the extant text is over 100
                        years later, in <date when="-0201">201 B.C.</date> , XXXI. ii. 1. </note>
                    maintained their friendship in such a way as not to bind themselves to the
                    Romans by any treaty of alliance, <pb n="p.333"/> precisely for the purpose of
                    not cutting off hope on <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 167</note> the part of the kings that they would come to their aid, if
                    need arose, as well as their own hope of reaping a harvest from the good will
                    and good fortune of the kings. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At this time
                    they felt that they should by all means seek an alliance, not to protect
                    themselves against other peoples, for they feared no one but the Romans, but to
                    alleviate the Romans' suspicion of themselves. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At about the same time the Caunians revolted
                    from them, and Mylassa seized the towns of the Euromenses. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The spirit of Rhodes was not so broken that they did not
                    perceive that if Lycia and Caria were taken away by the Romans, and the rest of
                    their possessions either freed themselves by revolt or were seized by the
                    neighbours, they would be hemmed in by the shores of a small island of infertile
                    soil, which could by no means support the population of so large a city. Troops
                    were therefore promptly sent and the Caunians compelled to accept their rule,
                    even though forces of Cibyra were called in by the Caunians. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Mylassa too and Alabanda, which had also come to join
                    Mylassa in taking away the province of Euromus, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Alabanda and Mylassa lay to north and south,
                        respectively, of Euromus. Rhodes had been interested in Euromus for some
                        time, as shown by XXXII. xxxiii. 6, and probably by XXXIII. xxx. 3. If
                        Livy's order of events is right, this early interest would explain why
                        Rhodes kept Euromus, after the <quote>liberation</quote> of Caria by the
                        Romans; but Polybius puts the <quote>liberation</quote> after an interval
                        following the return of the embassy, and the fighting may have taken place
                        during this interval. Mylassa was left <quote>tax-exempt,</quote> presumably
                        autonomous, by the settlement with Antiochus, XXXVIII. </note> were defeated
                    in battle near Orthosia. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these events were occuring in Asia, and
                    the previously-mentioned events in <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> Macedonia
                    and at Rome, in Illyricum <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> meanwhile, after
                    taking King Gentius into custody, as previously related, <milestone n="4??"
                        unit="section"/> Lucius Anicius put Gabinius in charge of the garrison
                        <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.335"/> placed in Scodra, the capital, and Gaius. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Licinius in <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 167</note> charge of the strategic cities <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">They were on the coast.</note> of Rhizon
                    and Olcinium. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After putting these men in
                    charge of Illyricum, Anicius marched into Epirus with the rest of his army.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In that region, Phanote the first city
                    surrendered to him, all its population coming <milestone n="9??" unit="section"
                    /> out with fillets to meet him. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He placed a
                    garrison here and passed on to Molossis, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> A different district of Epirus, Phanote being in
                        Chaonia. </note> and on <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> recovery of all
                    of its cities except Passaron, Tecmon, Phylace, and Horreum, <milestone n="12??"
                        unit="section"/> he led his force first against Passaron. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Antinoüs and Theodotus were the leading-men of this city,
                    distinguished both by their <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> attachment to
                    Perseus and their hatred of the Romans, and likewise responsible for the
                        <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> defection of the whole people from the
                    Romans. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Polybius <milestone n="27"
                            unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> 15 (13) and XXX. 7 says that at the outset
                        of the war, the Epirote leaders, including Antinoüs and the Cephalus
                        mentioned below, wished to keep out of the war, though maintaining their
                        alliance with Rome; but Charops the younger, by traducing them to Rome,
                        compelled them to declare for Perseus in order to avoid arrest by the
                        Romans. </note> Because of their feeling of personal guilt, since there was
                    no hope of pardon for them, these men shut the gates, in order to be buried in
                    the general downfall of their city, and urged the people to prefer death to
                    slavery. No one dared open his mouth against such all-powerful men. At last a
                    certain Theodotus, a youth of equal rank, spoke out, his dread of the Romans
                    outweighing his timidity before the chief men of his city. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>What is this madness,</quote> said he, <quote> which is goading you, that
                        you make the state an accessory to the crime of two men? <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Certainly I have often heard tales of those who met
                        death for the fatherland; but these are the first ever known to believe that
                        the fatherland ought to die for them. Why do we not <pb n="p.337"/> open our
                        gates and accept the overlordship which <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> the world has
                        accepted? </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the crowd concurred with these remarks,
                    Antinoüs and Theodotus charged into the first outpost of the enemy and, exposing
                    themselves to wounds, were there killed; the city was surrendered to the Romans.
                    By similar obstinacy on the part of Cephalus, the leading citizen, Tecmon was
                    closed, but when he was killed, it was recovered by surrender. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Neither Phylace nor Horreum stood up against attack. When
                    order had been established in Epirus, and the troops distributed in winter
                    quarters among suitable cities, Anicius returned to Illyricum, summoned the
                    chief men from all his theatre of operations, and held a conference at Scodra,
                    where the five commissioners from Rome had arrived. There he announced as
                    officer in charge, on the advice of his council, that the Roman senate and
                    people gave the Illyrians their freedom; he would remove his garrisons from all
                    towns, citadels, and forts. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Not only freedom,
                    but tax-exemption as well would be granted, he said, to the people of Issa and
                    Taulantia, and to the Pirustae among the Dassaretii as well as to Rhizon and
                    Olcinium, because they had gone over to the Romans while Gentius was still
                    undefeated. The Daorsi would also be granted tax-exemption, because they had
                    abandoned Caravantius and gone over with their arms to the Romans. On the people
                    of Scodra, the Dassarenses, the Selepitani, and the rest of the Illyrians a tax
                    was laid of half what they had paid to the king. Next, Anicius divided Illyricum
                    into three parts. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He made the first of these
                    the region above Pista, the second all the Labeatae, and the third the
                    Agravonitae, Rhizon <pb n="p.339"/> and Olcinium and their neighbours. After
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note>
                    announcing this charter for Illyricum, Anicius returned from there into Epirus
                    to his winter-quarters at Passaron. </p>
                <p> XXVII. While these events were occurring in Illyricum, Paulus sent his son
                    Quintus Maximus, who had by this time returned from Rome, to sack Aeginium and
                    Agassae before the arrival of the ten commissioners. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> In the case of Agassae, the reason was that, although they
                    had surrendered their city to the consul Marcius with a voluntary request for
                    alliance with Rome, they had again gone over to Perseus. The fault of Aeginium
                    was recent; because they did not believe the rumour about the Roman victory,
                    they had cruelly treated as enemies certain soldiers who had entered their city.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This seems to be another version,
                        or another phase, of the episode recorded in XLIV. xlvi. 3; if, as seems
                        likely, Aeginium was in north-western Thessaly, its adherence to Perseus was
                        more of a fault; but Paulus seems to have been looking for reasons which
                        would justify the acquisition of plunder by the army. If, as Livy's
                        arrangement implies, but does not make certain, these events occurred a year
                        after the fall of Perseus, the justification for them is thin. Assuming this
                        time interval, however, we may suppose that the arrangements of the senate
                        (xvii. 1) were made with the benefit of advice from Paulus, and that Paulus'
                        sightseeing mentioned below was more in order than it would have been soon
                        after the battle of Pydna. </note> Paulus also sent Lucius Postumius to sack
                    the city of Aenia, because they had maintained resistance more stubbornly than
                    the neighbouring cities. </p>
                <p> It was about the season of autumn; Paulus decided to employ the beginning of
                    this season travelling about Greece and seeing the sights which are made so
                    famous by repute that they are greater by hearsay than by visual acquaintance.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Putting Gaius Sulpicius Gallus in charge
                    of the camp, he set out with no large escort, his son Scipio and Athenaeus, the
                    brother of King Eumenes, serving as his personal aides. He went through Thessaly
                    to Delphi, the <pb n="p.341"/> famous oracular shrine. There he offered
                    sacrifice <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        167</note> to Apollo, and when he saw the columns which had been begun at
                    the entrance, on which they were going to place statues of King Perseus, he
                    reserved them for his own statues as conqueror. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Polybius XXX. 10. 2 (14) reports the statues of Paulus
                        as actually erected. </note> At Lebadia also he visited the shrine of
                    Jupiter Trophonius; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                        identification of the oracular hero Trophonius with Zeus seems to be
                        unofficial, though Strabo IX. ii. 38 (p. 414) also makes it. A description
                        of the sanctuary, including the shrine of Hercynna, a nymph of a spring and
                        stream, is given by Pausanias IX. xxxix. </note> there he viewed the mouth
                    of the cave through which those who use the oracle go down to make their
                    inquiries of the gods, and offered sacrifice to Jupiter and Hercynna, whose
                    temple is there. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Paulus then went down to
                    Chalcis to see the spectacle of the Euripus and of that great island Euboea
                    which is joined by a bridge to the mainland. From Chalcis he crossed to Aulis,
                    three miles away, with its harbour famous as the anchorage once upon a time for
                    the thousand ships <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The ships
                        enumerated in Homer's Catalogue are 1186; but the round number appears in
                        Aeschylus, Vergil, and other poets before Marlowe. </note> of Agamemnon's
                    fleet, and its temple of Diana, where the renowned king of kings sought passage
                    to Troy for his ships by bringing his daughter as a victim to the altar.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Thence Paulus went to Oropus in Attica,
                    where an ancient prophet is worshipped as a god, and there is an old temple made
                    charming by springs and streams around it. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The <quote>ancient prophet</quote> was Amphiaraüs, of
                        the Seven against Thebes. His sanctuary was established, according to
                        archaeological evidence, near the end of the fifth century, and became a
                        modest spa, which was favoured by the Romans; in <date when="-0073">73
                            B.C.</date> , Amphiaraüs was officially recognized as a god by the
                        consuls, with Cicero's assistance, and his lands were therefore tax-exempt,
                        see Pausanias I. xxxiv and Fraser's note. </note> Thence he went to Athens,
                    which is also replete with ancient glory, but nevertheless has many notable
                    sights, the Acropolis, the harbours, the walls joining Piraeus to the city, the
                    shipyards, the monuments of great <pb n="p.343"/> generals, and the statues of
                    gods and men —statues <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 167</note> notable for every sort of material and artistry. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After offering sacrifice to Minerva, the
                    Guardian of the Citadel, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.,</hi> Athena Polias, or Poliouchos; Livy gives her
                        the same title in XXXI. xxx. 9. </note> in Athens, Paulus set out for
                    Corinth and reached it on the second day. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    city was then world-famous before its destruction; its citadel and the Isthmus
                    were also sights to see; the citadel rising to a huge height, enclosed by the
                    city wall and flowing with springs, while the Isthmus separated by its narrow
                    passage two neighbouring seas lying toward the sunrise and sunset. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Thence Paulus went to Sicyon and Argos, both famous
                    cities; from there he visited Epidaurus, by no means as wealthy a town, but
                    noted for the famous temple of Aesculapius which, at a distance of five miles
                    from the city, is now rich in the traces of gifts of which it has been robbed,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Perhaps by Sulla (Pausanias IX.
                        vii. 5), who took the temple-treasures for his soldiers, and reimbursed the
                        god with lands in Boeotia. </note> but then was rich in the gifts themselves
                    which the sick had consecrated to the god as payment for health-giving remedies.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Next he visited Lacedaemon, notable not
                    for the splendour of its buildings, but for its discipline and institutions;
                    from there he went up to Olympia via Megalopolis. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> At Olympia he saw many sights which he considered worth
                    seeing; but he was stirred to the quick as he gazed on what seemed Jupiter's
                    very self. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Therefore he ordered a sacrifice
                    prepared larger than usual, just as if he had been going to sacrifice on the
                    Capitol. </p>
                <p> In this way he travelled through Greece, raising no question as to how either
                    any individual or any state had felt about the war with Perseus, so as not to
                        <pb n="p.345"/> trouble the minds of the allies by any fear. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> When <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 167</note> he was returning to Demetrias, he met a crowd
                    of Aetolians in mourning; on his asking in surprise what was the matter, it was
                    reported to him that five hundred and fifty leading men had been killed by
                    Lyciscus and Tisippus, while the senate was surrounded by Roman soldiers sent by
                    Aulus Baebius, the commander of the garrison; others had been driven into exile,
                    and the property of those killed and of the exiles had been seized. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Ordering the accused men to meet him at Amphipolis,
                    he joined Gnaeus Octavius in Demetrias. When a report arrived that the ten
                    commissioners had by now crossed the sea, he gave up everything else and went to
                    them at Apollonia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There Perseus came to meet
                    him from Amphipolis —a. day's journey —free of any guard. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Paulus greeted him in kindly fashion but after he arrived
                    in camp at Amphipolis, he is said to have rebuked Gaius Sulpicius severely,
                    first because he had allowed Perseus to roam so far from him through the
                    province, and secondly because he had allowed the soldiers the great liberty of
                    stripping the city walls of tiles, in order to roof over their winter-quarters;
                    Paulus ordered the tiles taken back and the uncovered areas repaired to their
                    previous condition. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Perseus and his elder son
                    Philip he turned over to Aulus Postumius and put under guard; Perseus' daughter
                    and his younger son he summoned to Amphipolis from Samothrace and maintained
                    completely in the state of free persons. </p>
                <pb n="p.347"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the day arrived on which he had <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> ordered
                    ten leading men from each city <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Typical Roman procedure; so ten leading men are summoned from some Latin
                        colonies in XXIX. xv. 5; the Twelve Tables were also established by a board
                        of ten. </note> to be at Amphipolis, and all official despatches which had
                    been filed anywhere and the royal money to be brought in, Paulus with the ten
                    commissioners took his official seat surrounded by the whole crowd of
                    Macedonians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Although the latter were used to
                    a royal court, yet the ceremonial of a new master was frightening as it met
                    their eyes —the consul's bench, his entrance after the way had been cleared, the
                    herald, and the orderly, all things novel to their eyes and ears, which might
                    have inspired terror in allies, to say nothing of conquered enemies. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> After the herald had commanded silence Paulus
                    announced in Latin the decisions of the senate, as well as his own, made by the
                    advice of his council. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This announcement was
                    translated into Greek and repeated by Gnaeus Octavius the praetor —for he too
                    was present. </p>
                <p> The terms were: first of all the Macedonians were given their freedom; they were
                    to keep their own cities and lands, to use their own laws, and to elect annual
                    magistrates; they were to pay to the Roman People half the tax which they had
                    paid to their kings. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Amounting to 100
                        talents, according to Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> xxviii. 3. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Next, Macedonia was to be divided into four
                    regions; one, the first section, would comprise the land between the Strymon and
                    Nessus Rivers; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> to this region were to be added
                    across the Nessus to the eastward the villages, forts, and towns which Perseus
                    had held except Aenus, Maronea, and Abdera; on this side of the Strymon, too,
                    toward the west there was included all the country of the Bisaltae, including
                    Heraclea, called Sintice. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The second region
                    was to be the region bounded on the east by the Strymon River, except <pb
                        n="p.349"/> for Heraclea Sintice, and the Bisaltae, while the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> western
                    boundary would be the Axius River; this would also include the Paeonians who
                    were settled near the Axius River in an easterly direction. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The third region was established as that bounded on the
                    east by the Axius, and on the west by the Peneüs River; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> What river is meant cannot be definitely determined;
                        the famous Peneüs of Thessaly is too far south to be even the southern
                        boundary, except at the sea-coast; but since Mount Bora is north-west rather
                        than north of this region, Livy or his informant may have a distorted
                        impression of the limits. </note> to the north Mount Bora forms a barrier;
                    to this region was added that part of Paeonia which stretches along the west
                    bank of the Axius River; Edessa and Beroea fell in the same part. The fourth
                    region was across Mount Bora, part marching with Illyricum, the rest with
                    Epirus. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The capitals of the regions, where
                    their assemblies were to meet, were established: for the first region,
                    Amphipolis, for the second, Thessalonica, for the third, Pella, and for the
                    fourth, Pelagonia. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This is usually
                        the name of a region, not a city; perhaps Heraclea Lyncestis is meant; it
                        would be appropriately central. </note> In those places Paulus ordered an
                    assembly <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Perhaps modelled after that
                        of the Achaean League; if not formally restricted to men with a property
                        qualification, it would become so, except for the populace of the capital
                        itself. </note> of each region to be appointed, money to be gathered, and
                    magistrates elected. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Paulus then announced that it had been
                    decided that no one should be allowed the right of marriage or of trading in
                    land or buildings outside the bounds of his own region. Furthermore, the mines
                    of gold and silver were not to be worked, but those of iron and copper were
                    permitted. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The tax on those who worked the
                    mines was set at half what they had paid to the king. The use of imported salt
                    was banned. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Perhaps as a further ban
                        on frequent communication between the regions. </note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When the Dardanians asked for the return of
                    Paeonia, on the ground that it had been theirs and adjoined <pb n="p.351"/>
                    their boundaries, Paulus proclaimed that freedom was <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> being given to all those
                    who had been subjects of Perseus. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> After
                    refusing them Paeonia, he granted them the right to import salt; he ordered the
                    third region to carry salt to Stobi in Paeonia, and he set a price on it. He
                    forbade the Macedonians to cut ship-timbers, or to permit others to do so.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The regions which bordered on barbarians
                    —and this was true of all except the third —were allowed to have armed guards
                    along their frontiers. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The announcement of these arrangements on the
                    first day of the gathering aroused mixed emotions. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The unexpected grant of freedom cheered men, as well as the
                    lightening of the annual taxation; but to those who were cut off from trading
                    between regions, their country seemed as mangled as an animal disjointed into
                    parts, each of which needed the other; so unaware were the Macedonians
                    themselves of the size of Macedonia, of how it lent itself to division, and of
                    how self-sufficient each part was. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The assets of the first region are the
                    Bisaltae, men of great courage (they live beyond the Nessus and around the
                    Strymon), soil suitable for many different crops, mines, and the strategic
                    position of Amphipolis, the interposition of which bars off every approach to
                    Macedonia from the sunrise side. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The second
                    region has those highly flourishing cities Thessalonica and Cassandrea, and in
                    addition, Pallene, a fertile and fruitful land; facilities for seafaring are
                    also furnished it by the harbours at Torone, Mount Athos, Aenea, and Acanthus,
                    some of which conveniently face Thessaly and the island of <pb n="p.353"/>
                    Euboea, and others the Hellespont. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The third
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note>
                    region has the famous cities of Edessa, Beroea, and Pella, and the warlike race
                    of the Vettii, as well as a large population of Gauls and Illyrians, who are
                    industrious farmers. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The fourth region is
                    inhabited by the Eordaei, Lyncestae, and Pelagonians; added to these are
                    Atintania, Tymphaeis, and Elimiotis. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This part
                    of the world is as a whole cold, difficult to cultivate, and harsh; it has
                    inhabitants of temperament like their land. These are also made fiercer by their
                    barbarian neighbours, who now give them training in warfare, now intermingle
                    their practices during peace. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The partition of
                    Macedonia therefore showed, by separating the assets of the regions, how great
                    the country is as a whole. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the proclamation of the charter for
                    Macedonia, Paulus declared that he would also lay down a law-code, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Since the Macedonians were to
                            <quote>use their own laws</quote> (above, xxix. 4), this must refer to a
                        code for the four federal governments, either new or a revision of previous
                        laws to meet the new arrangements and incorporate the Roman stipulations;
                        cf. below, xxxii. 7. </note> and then proceeded to summon the Aetolians.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In this investigation, the question was
                    more which side had favoured the king and which the Romans, than which had done
                    wrong or had been wronged; the assassins were acquitted of guilt; the exile of
                    the expelled was confirmed quite as definitely as the death of the slain; only
                    Aulus Baebius was condemned for furnishing Roman soldiers to help carry out the
                    slaughter. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This outcome of the case of the Aetolians
                    raised to an unbearable pitch of pride the spirits of those in all the states
                    and peoples of Greece who sided with the Romans, and crushed helplessly under
                    their feet any who were in some respect tainted by suspicion of having favoured
                    the king. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There were three sorts of <pb
                        n="p.355"/> leaders in the states, two groups who by fawning <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> upon the
                    Roman power and the friendship of kings respectively gained personal wealth for
                    themselves by tyrannizing over their cities; the middle group alone, opposing
                    both the others, strove to guard independence and constitutionality. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Polybius XXX. 6 names three groups, but
                        only of those accused of being anti-Roman; his first group, corresponding to
                        Livy's third, or middle-of-the-road group, wanted the status quo
                        undisturbed; the second wanted a decisive contest between Rome and Perseus,
                        with victory for Perseus; the third group shared the sentiments of the
                        second, and in addition were able to draw their states into open alliance
                        with Perseus. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Their reward was greater affection from their
                    own people, and less favour in foreign quarters. Carried along on the tide of
                    Roman success, the members of the pro- Roman party were then alone occupying all
                    magistracies and serving as envoys. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These
                    gathered in great numbers both from the Peloponnesus and Boeotia and the other
                    leagues of Greece, and filled the ears of the ten commissioners, saying that not
                    only those who out <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> of vanity openly boasted
                    themselves guests and friends of Perseus, but many more who kept under cover,
                    had sided with the king, and under the guise of preserving independence they had
                    turned the whole organization of the league meetings against the Roman interest;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> these peoples, said their representatives,
                    would not maintain loyalty unless the spirit of the opposition was crushed and
                    the prestige sustained and strengthened of those who had no object in view but
                    the power of Rome. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Names were furnished by these men, and their
                    opponents from Aetolia, Acarnania, Epirus, and Boeotia were summoned by
                    dispatches from the general to follow him to Rome to stand trial. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> According to Polybius XXX. 13 (10). 11,
                        Paulus did not take the accusations at face-value. </note> Two <pb n="p.357"
                    /> of the board of commissioners, Gaius Claudius and <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> Gnaeus Domitius, set out
                    for Achaia in order to summon men by proclamation on the spot. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> This they did for two reasons, first because they thought
                    the Achaeans had more confidence and more pride to make them refuse obedience
                    and perhaps also Callicrates and the other informers and purveyors of charges
                    might be endangered; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> the second reason for
                    the personal summons was that from the other leagues they had letters of the
                    leaders that had been seized in the royal archives, but no letters from the
                    Achaeans had been found and the charge against them was blind. </p>
                <p> When the Aetolians had been dismissed, the Acarnanian League was called up. No
                    changes were made concerning them, except that Leucas was removed from the
                    Acarnanian federation. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This was a
                        serious matter, however; the town had sometimes served as the meeting-place
                        of the league assembly. The Romans were taking control of the coast. </note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> In the course of more sweeping inquiries as
                    to support of the king, either individual or by political <milestone n="13??"
                        unit="section"/> units, the investigation was extended to Asia, and Labeo
                    was sent to destroy Antissa on the island of Lesbos and to move its inhabitants
                    to Methymna, because when Antenor, the king's admiral, had been roaming about
                    Lesbos with his scout-ships, the people of Antissa had received him into their
                    harbour and aided him with provisions. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Two
                    men of distinction were beheaded by the consul, Andronicus, son of Andronicus,
                    an Aetolian, because following his father <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/>
                    he had borne arms against the Roman People, and Neon of Thebes, who had induced
                    his people to make an alliance with Perseus. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the interruption due to these
                    investigations of other <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> peoples, the
                    assembly of the Macedonians was again convened. Concerning the <pb n="p.359"/>
                    constitution of Macedonia it was announced that <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note>
                    <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> senators, whom they call <hi rend="italics"
                        >synhedri,</hi> were to be chosen, by whose advice affairs of state <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">In each of the four districts.</note>
                    were to be conducted. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The names were read of
                    the Macedonian leaders who, it had been decided, were to precede the consul on
                    the way to Italy with their sons of over fifteen years of age. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> This ordinance, cruel at first glance, soon was seen by the
                    commons of Macedonia to have been enacted in the interests of their freedom.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For the names were those of the king's
                    friends and the wearers of the purple, of commanders of armies, of officers in
                    command of ships and garrisons-men accustomed to being humble slaves of the
                    king, but haughty tyrants toward others. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Some
                    were exceedingly rich, others equalled in expenditure those whose fortunes they
                    could not match; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> all of them used the diet and
                    garments of the court, none had the temperament of a citizen, or would endure
                    the rule of law and the give-and-take of free men. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> All, therefore, who had held some office under the king,
                    even those who had served as ambassadors, were ordered to leave Macedonia and
                    travel to Italy; death was the penalty announced for disobedience to this order.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Paulus laid down laws for Macedonia with
                    such care as to seem to be giving them not to conquered enemies, but to
                    well-deserving allies —laws <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> which not even
                    experience over along period, the one best amender of legislation, could prove
                    faulty in actual use. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Justinus
                            <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> 2. 7, says that these laws <quote>are
                            still in use</quote> , <hi rend="italics">i.e.,</hi> in the time of
                        Trogus (first century after Christ), or possibly in that of Justinus himself
                        (second century). </note>
                </p>
                <p> After the serious business, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy does
                        not mention the destruction of the fortifications of Demetrias, one of the
                        three <quote>fetters of Greece</quote> , recorded by Diodorus XXXI. 13.
                    </note> Paulus celebrated with great pomp at Amphipolis a festival which had
                    been long under preparation, and to announce which he had sent men to the cities
                    and the kings of Asia, while he himself had given notice to the leading men <pb
                        n="p.361"/> during his tour of the Greek cities. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> For a crowd of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 167</note> all sorts of professionals in the art of
                    entertainment gathered from all over the world, as well as athletes and famous
                    horses; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> moreover there were delegations with
                    sacrifices, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> What the Greeks called
                            <hi rend="italics">theoriai-official</hi> representatives of their
                        states, who participated by offering sacrifices. </note> and whatever more
                    is usually done at the great games of Greece for the sake of gods or men, was so
                    carried out as to arouse admiration not only for lavishness but for skill in
                    giving shows, at which Romans were then tyros. Banquets for the delegations were
                    also prepared with equal sumptuousness and pains. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> From mouth to mouth went the saying of Paulus himself, that
                    the man who knew how to conquer in war could also arrange a banquet and organize
                    games. </p>
                <p> XXXIII. After the festival had been held and the bronze shields loaded into
                    ships, the rest of the arms of all kinds were piled up into a great heap, and
                    the general, after prayer to Mars, Minerva, Mother Lua, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Consort or companion of Saturn, she was a destructive
                        power to be placated, cf. VIII. i. 6 and the note, and perhaps Servius on
                            <hi rend="italics">Aeneid</hi> III. 139 ( <hi rend="italics">Luae</hi>
                        emended from <hi rend="italics">Lunae</hi> ). </note> and the other gods to
                    whom it is right and lawful to dedicate the spoils of the enemy, with his own
                    hands put the torch to the pile; then each of the military tribunes as they
                    stood round about tossed in fire. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In that
                    great gathering of Europe and Asia, when such a crowd had assembled partly to
                    offer congratulations and partly for the display, and in the presence of such
                    forces naval and military, a remarkable fact was that supplies were so abundant
                    and grain so cheap that both to individuals and to cities and peoples abundant
                    gifts of such supplies were made by the general, not only for immediate use, but
                    to be taken home with them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The eyes of <pb
                        n="p.363"/> the crowd which came were no more drawn to the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> stage
                    spectacle, the contests of men, or the racing of the horses, than to the
                    collected loot of Macedonia, set out on exhibition, statues, paintings, rare
                        <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> stuffs, and vessels made of gold,
                    silver, bronze and ivory, manufactured with great pains in the palace at Pella,
                    so as to serve not only for immediate show, as did the objects with which the
                    palace at Alexandria was crammed, but for continuous use. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> A similar triumphal display is recorded in XXVI. xxi.
                        7-8 (from Syracuse); and the Romans' interest in looted art is expressed in
                        XXXII. xvi. 17 (Chalcis) and XXXVIII. ix. 13 (Ambracia). </note> This booty
                    was loaded on the fleet and given to Gnaeus Octavius to transport to Rome. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After a courteous farewell to the delegates,
                    Paulus crossed the Strymon and pitched camp a mile from Amphipolis; thence he
                    set out for Pella and arrived on the fifth day. Passing by the city to what is
                    called the Pellaeum, he halted for two days, and sent his son Quintus Maximus
                    and Publius Nasica with a portion of the troops to ravage Illyrians who had
                    helped Perseus in the war, ordering the expedition to meet him at Oricum; the
                    consul himself made for Epirus and reached Passaron on the fifteenth day. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Not far from here was the camp of Anicius.
                    Paulus sent him despatches, so that there should be no disturbance over what was
                    about to take place, saying that the senate had granted to Paulus' army the
                    booty from those cities of Epirus which had deserted to Perseus. The consul sent
                    centurions to the several cities, who were to say that they had come to remove
                    the garrisons so that the people of Epirus might be free like the Macedonians;
                    ten leading men from each city were summoned to the consul. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> These men were instructed <pb n="p.365"/> to have the gold
                    and silver collected at the civic <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 167</note> centre. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then
                    cohorts were sent to all the cities, those bound for the more distant leaving
                    before those for the nearer, so that they would arrive at all the towns on the
                    same day. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The tribunes and centurions had been
                    instructed as to their mission. Early in the day all the gold and silver was
                    collected; at the fourth hour the soldiers were given the signal to plunder the
                    towns. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> So great was the booty that a
                    distribution was made of four hundred denarii apiece to the cavalry, and two
                    hundred apiece to the infantry, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> xxix. 3, says that only 11
                        drachmas per soldier were realized, that is, about 13 denarii; this would
                        explain the dissatisfaction of the soldiers mentioned below, but implies a
                        serious and improbable miscalculation on the part of Paulus. In xxx. 1,
                        Plutarch apologizes for Paulus in respect to this action, which is charged
                        to the senate. </note> and one-hundred and fifty thousand persons were
                    removed. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The walls of the plundered cities
                    were destroyed; the number of communities was about seventy. All the booty was
                    sold, and from the proceeds the amounts given above were paid to the army. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Paulus went down to the sea at Oricum, having
                    by no means met the expectations of the soldiers, as he had supposed he would;
                    the men were complaining that they had no share in the booty from the king, as
                    if they had fought no campaign in Macedonia. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    On finding at Oricum the troops he had sent with Scipio Nasica and his son
                    Maximus, Paulus embarked his army on ships and crossed to Italy. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> A few days later Anicius, after waiting for the ships
                    which the army of Macedonia had used, crossed to Italy, first holding an
                    assembly of the remaining Epirotes and Acarnanians, and ordering the leaders,
                    judgment about whom he had reserved for the senate, to follow him to Italy. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.367"/>
                <p> While these events were occurring in Macedonia <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> and Epirus, the
                    commissioners who had been sent with Attalus to put an end to the war between
                    the Galatians and King Eumenes, arrived in Asia. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> A truce had been declared for the winter; the Galatians on
                    their side had returned to their homes, and the king had gone into
                    winter-quarters at Pergamum and was ill with a serious disease. Early spring
                    called the Galatians into the field, and they had by this time reached Synnada;
                    Eumenes had mustered an army from all sides at Sardis. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> At that city the Romans learned that Solovettius the
                    Galatian leader was at Synnada, and decided to go there to confer with him;
                    Attalus set out with them, but it was decided that he should not enter the camp
                    of the Galatians, lest tempers be lost during an altercation. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Publius Licinius, an ex-consul, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Head of this embassy (Polybius XXX. 3) and consul 4
                        years before, XLII. xxix. 1. Polybius implies that the embassy was not
                        really meant to restrain the Galatians, as shown by the actual results.
                    </note> talked with the prince of the Galatians and reported that he had been
                    emboldened by the appeal to him, so that it was occasion for wonder that the
                    words of Roman <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> envoys had had such weight
                    with those prosperous kings Antiochus and Ptolemy that they at once made peace,
                    whereas with the Galatians Roman words were without effect. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Rome first the captive kings, Perseus and
                    Gentius, were placed in custody with their children, next the horde of other
                    prisoners, and after them the Macedonians who had been ordered to come to Rome,
                    and the leaders of Greece, for these men <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> too
                    had not only been summoned when at home, <pb n="p.369"/> but if any of them were
                    reported as being at the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 167</note> courts of the kings, they had also been sought out by
                    letter. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Polybius XXX. 9, gives an
                        illustration of this: Polyaratus the Rhodran was at the court of Ptolemy;
                        Popilius ordered him to be sent to Rome. Ptolemy sent him instead to Rhodes,
                        but Polyaratus jumped ship at Phaselis, in eastern Lycia, and again at
                        Caunus; then he took refuge at Cibyra, but was finally rounded up and taken
                        to Rome. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After a few days, Paulus himself sailed up the
                    Tiber to the city in a royal galley of immense size, which was driven by sixteen
                    banks of oars, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Perhaps the one left
                        to Philip by the treaty of <date when="-0196">196 B.C.</date> : XXXIII. xxx.
                        5. </note> and decorated with the spoils of Macedonia, not only splendid
                    armour, but also royal fabrics. The banks were lined with the crowd which had
                    poured out to welcome him. A few days later Anicius and Octavius arrived aboard
                    their fleet. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A triumph was decreed to all
                    three commanders by the senate, and Quintus Cassius the praetor was assigned the
                    task of arranging with the tribunes of the commons that they should propose to
                    the commons, on motion of the senate, a resolution that the commanders should
                    keep their authority of office on the day on which they rode into the city in
                    triumph. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A similar provision for
                        Marcellus' ovation over Syracuse is recorded in XXVI. xxi. 5. For the voting
                        of a triumph over the refusal of the senate, see III. lxiii. 8-11 and the
                        note. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Moderate circumstances are unassailed by envy;
                    that passion always aims at the heights. There was no debate over the triumphs
                    for Anicius and Octavius; but defamation attacked Paulus, to whom the others
                    themselves would have blushed to compare themselves. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> He had held the soldiers to old-fashioned discipline; he
                    had given them less of the booty than they had hoped for from such lavish royal
                    resources, though had he given rein to their greed, they would have left nothing
                    to be deposited in the public treasury. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    whole army of Macedonia, angered at their general, were prepared to be slack in
                    attending the assembly for passing the law. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    But Servius Sulpicius Galba, who had been military tribune of the <pb n="p.371"
                    /> second legion in Macedonia, and was personally <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> hostile to the general,
                    had egged on the men to appear for voting in full numbers, by buttonholing the
                    men himself and urging them through the soldiers of his legion. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Let them, said Sulpicius, avenge themselves on their
                    domineering and stingy leader by voting down the proposal concerning his
                    triumph; the city commons would follow the opinion of the soldiers. Paulus had
                    been unable to give them money; but the rank and file were able to award
                    honours. Let him not look for a harvest of gratitude where he had not earned it. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such was the urging of Sulpicius. When
                    Tiberius Sempronius, tribune of the commons, proposed this resolution on the
                    Capitol, and opportunity was given to citizens to speak concerning the law,
                    hardly anyone came forward to urge passage, since the case seemed quite clear.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Suddenly Servius Galba came forward and
                    asked of the tribunes, inasmuch as it was now the eighth hour of the day, and
                    time would not serve for him to show cause why they should not allow Lucius
                    Aemilius to celebrate a triumph, that they should adjourn to the following day,
                    and bring the matter up early, because he needed a full day to present his
                    arguments. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When the tribunes ordered him to
                    say what he wished on that day, he prolonged the meeting till nightfall with his
                    speaking, recalling and reminding them of the harsh enforcement of military
                    duties; more toil and more danger had been imposed, he said, than the situation
                    demanded; on the other hand, rewards and honours had been without exception
                    restricted; and military service, if success attended this sort of leadership,
                    would be more dreadful and full of hardships in <pb n="p.373"/> wartime, and
                    after victory would moreover be left without <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> funds or honours.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The fate of the Macedonians was
                    preferable, said Galba, to that of the Roman soldiers. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> If they turned out in large numbers on the next day to
                    reject the law, men with authority would be made aware that not everything was
                    under the control of the leader, but something also under that of the soldiers. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Roused by these utterances, the soldiers next
                    day filled the Capitol with such a crowd that no one else could approach to cast
                    his vote. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the first tribes <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Plutarch <hi rend="italics"
                            >Aemilius</hi> xxxi. 1 says that the vote of the first tribe gave the
                        signal for the protest of the senators. </note> called within the enclosure
                    voted against the law, the leaders of the state hastened to gather on the
                    Capitol, crying out that it was an unworthy action to rob Lucius Paulus of his
                    triumph when he had won so great a war; the generals were being helplessly
                    subjected to the insubordination and greed of their men. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Even now wrong action was all too often taken for the sake
                    of currying favour; what would happen if soldiers were made the masters of their
                    generals? Each man hurled reproaches on his own score against Galba. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When this uproar had at last been calmed,
                    Marcus Servilius, who had been consul and master of the horse, requested of the
                    tribunes that they should conduct this balloting anew, and give him an
                    opportunity to speak to the people. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After the
                    tribunes had retired to consider the proposal, overborne by the influence of the
                    leading men, they began to repeat the proceedings, and announced that they would
                    call the same tribes again, once Marcus Servilius and other citizens who wished
                    to speak, had had their say. </p>
                <pb n="p.375"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then Servilius said: "If it were impossible,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note>
                    fellow-citizens, to determine from anything else how great a general Lucius
                    Aemilius has shown himself to be this one criterion would have sufficed -that
                    although he had in camp such mutinous and unreliable soldiers, as well as a
                    personal enemy of such high rank, so rash, and so eloquent a rabble-rouser, yet
                    Paulus had no breach of discipline in his army. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> The same strictness of command which now they hate at that time restrained
                    them. Consequently, being kept under old-fashioned discipline, they neither said
                    nor did anything mutinous. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> "As for Servius Galba, if he wished by
                    accusing Lucius Paulus to put his apprenticeship behind him and offer proof of
                    his skill as an orator, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Galba became
                        a noted orator, cf. Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Brutus</hi> xxi. 82 and xxii.
                        86. </note> he should not have interfered with the triumph, which the senate
                    had adjudged to be proper, to say nothing of other considerations. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Rather on the day after the triumph was celebrated,
                    when he would see Paulus a private citizen, he should bring accusation and
                    question him according to law, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This
                        latter refers to an arraignment of the accused, at which the
                            <quote>question</quote> was whether he pleaded guilty or not guilty.
                    </note> or a little later, when Galba entered upon his first public office, he
                    should summon his enemy to trial and accuse him before the people. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Thus there would accrue to Lucius Paulus not only the
                    triumph which is the due reward for his success in gloriously conducting the
                    war, but also punishment, if he had done anything unworthy of his laurels, both
                    new and old. </p>
                <pb n="p.377"/>
                <p> "But, if you please, Galba wished to tarnish the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> praises of the man to whom
                    he could ascribe no crime, no guilt. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Yesterday
                    he asked for a full day in which to accuse Lucius Paulus; actually he squandered
                    in speaking four hours, all that was left of the day. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> What defendant was ever so guilty that the faults in his
                    life could not be expounded in all those hours? What did Galba say in this time
                    which Lucius Paulus would want to deny, if he were on trial? Let someone, pray,
                    call two meetings for a moment, one of the army of Macedonia, the other
                    unprejudiced and of judgment less impaired by partisanship or hate, a meeting of
                    the whole Roman people. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> "Let the defendant be brought first before the
                    meeting in mufti —the civilians. What would you say before the citizen-body of
                    Rome, Servius Galba? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For all your speech of
                    yesterday would be cut short: 'You were posted on guard too strictly and
                    watchfully; the sentries were inspected too severely and too frequently; you got
                    more work done than formerly, because the general himself was going the rounds
                    to see that it was done; on the same day you made a march and went from the
                    march out to battle; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Actually the
                        soldiers had called for battle, and Paulus had refused it, XLIV. xxxvi. 3.
                    </note> even when you had won the battle he did not let you rest —he led you at
                    once in pursuit of the enemy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Although he
                    might have made you rich by dividing the spoil, he is planning to carry the
                    royal treasure in his triumph and deposit it in the treasury.' <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> These statements, though they have a certain sting to
                    provoke the temper of the soldiers, who think that Paulus has catered too little
                    to their lack of discipline and their greed, would just as surely have had no
                        <pb n="p.379"/> power to move the Roman people; for even though <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> the people
                    should not recall the old stories which they heard from their fathers of
                    disasters suffered <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> because generals courted
                    popularity, and of victories won by strictness of command, yet the people surely
                    remember the late Punic War, and what a difference there was between Marcus
                    Minucius the master of horse, and Quintus Fabius Maximus the dictator. And so it
                    would have been clear that the accuser could not open his mouth, and that a
                    defence of Paulus was superfluous. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> "Let us pass over to the other meeting;
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> and I think I will not address you as
                    'Citizens,' but as 'Soldiers,' in case this title may at least bring a blush to
                    your cheeks, and instill some scruple against maltreating your general. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Indeed the state of my own feelings is
                    different, when I picture myself speaking before the army, than it was
                    previously, when my speech was directed toward the people of the city.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For what do you mean, soldiers? Is there
                    anyone in Rome except Perseus who does not want the triumph over Macedonia to be
                    celebrated? And are you not ready to tear such an objector to pieces with the
                    same hands with which you conquered the Macedonians? He who prevents you from
                    entering the city in triumph would have prevented you from winning the victory,
                    had he been able. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> You are wrong, soldiers, if
                    you suppose that a triumph is an honour only to the general, and not also to the
                    soldiers and to the Roman People as a whole. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    It is not the glory of Paulus alone which is at stake in this matter. </p>
                <pb n="p.381"/>
                <p> "Furthermore, many who did not secure a triumph <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> from the senate celebrated
                    their triumph on the Alban Mount. No one can deprive Lucius Paulus of the glory
                    of bringing the Macedonian war to an end any more than he can deprive Gaius
                    Lutatius of credit for the First Punic War, or Publius Cornelius of that for the
                    Second, or the others who have more recently celebrated triumphs. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> A triumph will make Lucius Paulus neither greater nor
                    less as a general; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> rather it is the reputation
                    of the soldiers and that of the Roman People as a whole which is at stake in
                    this matter, in the first place that Rome may not gain a reputation for a
                    jealous and ungrateful spirit toward her most distinguished citizens, and seem
                    in this respect to be imitating the people of Athens who in their envy buffet
                    their leading men. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Enough of a crime was
                    committed by your ancestors against Camillus —though they wronged him before his
                    recovery of the city from the Gauls; enough was done by yourselves against
                    Publius Africanus. Let us blush that the home and abode of the conqueror of
                    Africa was at Liternum, and that it is at Liternum that his tomb is displayed.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. XXXVIII. liii. 8 and lvi. 3,
                        where Livy says he is following Valerius Antias. </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Let Lucius Paulus rival these men in glory,
                    but let him not be their equal in suffering injustice at your hands. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> "Let therefore this disgrace be in the first
                    place blotted out —a disgrace odious before other peoples, and harmful to
                    ourselves. For who would want to emulate either Africanus or Paulus in a city so
                    ungrateful and so hostile to excellence? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If
                    there were no question of disgrace, and only glory were at stake, what possible
                    triumph does not embody the glory of the Roman name which we all share?
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Are the many triumphs which have been
                    celebrated over the Gauls, <pb n="p.383"/> over the Spaniards, over the
                    Carthaginians spoken of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 167</note> as pertaining merely to the generals themselves, or to the
                    Roman People? Just as triumphs are celebrated, not merely over Pyrrhus or
                    Hannibal, but over the people of Epirus or Carthage, so not Manius Curius or
                    Publius Cornelius alone, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> There is a
                        reference to the victory of Curius in Summary XIV; Scipio's triumph is
                        mentioned in XXX. xlv. </note> but the Romans celebrated the triumph.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Soldiers indeed are directly interested
                    in the matter, for they too are crowned with laurel, while each man is adorned
                    with the decorations he has been given; they parade through the city invoking
                    the spirit of Triumph by name and singing their own praises and those of their
                    general. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> If on some occasion the soldiers are
                    not brought back from the field for the triumph, they grumble; and yet even on
                    such an occasion they believe that they are included in the triumph, though
                    absent, because the victory has been won by their hands. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> If someone should ask you, soldiers, for what purpose you
                    were transported to Italy, and were not dismissed at once when your mission had
                    been completed, if he should ask why you had come to Rome in complete military
                    units, why you were lingering here and were not dispersing, each to his own
                    home, what would you answer but that you wished to be seen celebrating your
                    triumph? Certainly you yourselves ought to have wanted to make a public
                    appearance as conquerors. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Triumphs have been celebrated in recent years
                    over Philip, the father of this king, and over Antiochus; both were still on the
                    throne when the triumph was celebrated. Shall no triumph be celebrated over
                    Perseus, who was taken prisoner and brought with his children to Rome?
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Nay, if while the other commanders were
                    mounting the Capitol in <pb n="p.385"/> the chariot, arrayed in their gold and
                    purple, from <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        167</note> below them Lucius Paulus, a lone citizen in the crowd of
                    civilians, should ask them, ' Lucius Anicius, Gnaeus Octavius, do you consider
                    yourselves more worthy of a triumph, or me? ' they would, I believe, yield him
                    their place in the chariot and for very shame hand their regalia over to him.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Do you prefer, fellow-citizens, to have
                    Gentius rather than Perseus led in a triumph, and the celebration to be made for
                    an appendage to the war rather than for the war itself? <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The legions from Illyricum will also enter the city crowned
                    with laurel, and so will the sailors; shall the legions of Macedonia witness the
                    triumphs of others after their own has been cancelled? What then shall become of
                    so kingly a booty, of the spoils of so rich a victory? <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> What, pray, shall be the hiding-place for all those
                    thousand sets of arms stripped from the bodies of the enemy? Shall they be sent
                    back to Macedonia? What of the golden statues, the marbles, the ivories, the
                    paintings, the rare stuffs, all the embossed silver, all the gold, all the royal
                    money? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Shall they be carried to the treasury
                    by night as if stolen? And what is more —that greatest of shows, royal prisoner
                    of highest birth and greatest riches —where shall he be displayed to the people
                    who have gained the victory? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Many of us can
                    recall what crowds were drawn by the sight of King Syphax as prisoner, an
                    appendage to the war with Carthage. Shall our prisoner King Perseus, shall the
                    king's sons, Philip and Alexander, names of such potency, —shall they be removed
                    from the sight of the commonwealth? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Lucius
                    Paulus himself, twice consul, conqueror of Greece —all eyes are eager to behold
                    him entering the city in his chariot; to this end we made him consul, <pb
                        n="p.387"/> that he might bring to an end the war which to <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> nothing
                    less than our great shame had dragged on through four years. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> When he was allotted this field of operations, when he left
                    home, we marked him for victory and triumph with minds that read the future; and
                    shall we deny him a triumph when he has won his victory? <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Nay more —shall we rob not only Paulus, but even the gods,
                    of the honour that belongs to them? For it is to the gods too, not only to men,
                    that we owe a triumph. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Elsewhere
                        (XXVI. xxi. 3; XXXI. xlviii. 12) Livy makes use of the argument that
                        thanksgivings must be followed by a triumph. </note> Your ancestors made the
                    gods their starting-point in every important enterprise, and likewise resorted
                    to them at the conclusion. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When consul or
                    praetor, his lictors in their military dress, sets out for his field of action
                    and to war, he proclaims his vows upon the Capitol; when war has ended in
                    victory, he returns in triumph to the same gods on the same Capitol, and brings
                    them the well-earned gifts, as he promised them in his vows. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> No small part of a triumphal procession is formed by the
                    sacrificial animals going ahead, which make it clear that the general is
                    returning with thanksgiving to the gods for success on behalf of the
                    commonwealth. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Away with all those sacrificial
                    victims which he has assigned to be led in the triumphal procession, and offer
                    them up, some here, some there! I ask you! What of the banquet of the senate,
                    which is not held on private property, nor on the unconsecrated land of the
                    state, but on the Capitol-is this ceremony held for the pleasure of men, or in
                    honour of the gods? </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.389"/>
                <p>
                    <quote> Will you play havoc with all these rites at the <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> instigation of Servius
                        Galba? Will the gates be closed to the triumph of Lucius Paulus? Will King
                        Perseus of Macedonia, together with his sons, the throng of other prisoners,
                        and the spoils of Macedonia, be left behind in the Flaminian Circus?
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Will Lucius Paulus go home from the
                        gate as a private citizen, as if he were returning from his country house?
                        You, centurion, and you, private, harken to what the senate decrees about
                        General Paulus rather than what Servius Galba babbles, and harken too to my
                        speech rather than his. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> He has learned
                        nothing except talk, and that of a slanderous and malicious sort; I have on
                        twenty-three occasions challenged and fought an enemy; I brought back the
                        spoils of every man with whom I duelled; I possess a body adorned with
                        honourable scars, every one of them received in front. </quote>
                </p>
                <p> He then stripped, it is said, and told in which war he had received each wound.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> While displaying these, he by chance
                    uncovered what should have remained concealed, and the swelling of his groin
                    raised a laugh among those nearby. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>This too,</quote> he then said, "at which you are laughing I got by
                    sitting my horse through whole days and nights; and I feel no more shame or
                    regret for this than for these wounds of mine, since it never hindered me from
                    successfully conducting affairs of state at home or in the field. As a veteran
                    soldier before young soldiers, I have displayed this body of mine which has
                    often been marred by the sword; let Galba uncover his sleek and untouched
                    person. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.391"/> Tribunes, call back the tribes, if you please, to the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> voting; I
                    [will join] you, soldiers ... <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> xxxi. 6, supplies the conclusion,
                        the bracketed words being suggested by this: <quote> I shall come down and
                            accompany (you) all and shall discover the base and ungrateful who
                            prefer to be led in war by demagogues rather than generals. </quote>
                        Also missing is the date of the triumph, Nov. 27-29, C.I.L.2 I. i. p. 48,
                        xxvii, and the description of most of the triumphal procession, cf. Diodorus
                        XXXI. xiii. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The total of all the captured gold and silver
                    which was carried in the procession was one hundred and twenty million
                    sesterces, according to the account of Valerius Antias; no doubt a somewhat
                    larger total than this is made up from the number of wagons and the weights of
                    gold and silver in various forms which are mentioned by this same author. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics"
                            >Aemilius</hi> xxxii, mentions 750 vessels, each containing three
                        talents of coined silver. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As much again was either expended in the late
                    war, or scattered during the flight, when Perseus was making for Samothrace,
                    according to the historians; and this fact is the more marvellous, because this
                    huge sum of money was accumulated within thirty years after Philip's war with
                    the Romans, partly from the output of the mines, and partly from other revenues.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Philip therefore began his war against
                    Rome when he was rather ill-supplied with funds, but Perseus, when he was very
                    rich. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Paulus himself came last in his chariot,
                    showing a magnificent presence not only because of the general dignity of his
                    bearing, but because of his advanced age as well. After the chariot came his two
                    sons, Quintus Maximus and Publius Scipio, among other distinguished men; then
                    came the cavalry by troops, and the units of infantry, rank by rank. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Each infantryman received one hundred denarii, each
                    centurion, twice the amount, and each cavalryman, <pb n="p.393"/> three times as
                    much. It is thought that double the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 167</note> amount would have been given to the infantry,
                    and proportionately to the rest, if they had supported Paulus' triumph in the
                    voting, or had cheerfully applauded the announcement of the gift as actually
                    given. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But Perseus was not the only testimony at this
                    time to the state of human fortunes, as he was led in chains before the chariot
                    of his conqueror through the city of his enemies; the conqueror Paulus, in the
                    splendour of his gold and purple, was no less a witness. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> For of the two sons whom he kept at home as the only heirs
                    of his name, his family rites, and his household, after he had given two other
                    sons to be adopted, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> See above, XLIV.
                        xxxv. 14 and the note; Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> xxxv.
                    </note> the younger boy, aged about twelve, died five days before the triumph,
                    and the elder, fourteen years old, died three days after the festivity.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These were the minor boys who should have
                    ridden with their father in the chariot, secretly planning like triumphs for
                    themselves. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When a few days later an assembly
                    of the commons was called by Marcus Antonius the tribune, and Paulus discoursed,
                    as was customary for commanders, on his exploits, his speech was noteworthy and
                    well-suited to a leading Roman: </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Although you, my fellow-citizens, are not
                    unaware, I believe, of the good fortune with which I have conducted the affairs
                    of the state, and of the two thunderbolts which have recently struck my house
                    —for you were eyewitnesses first of my triumph, and then of the funerals of my
                    sons —yet <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> I beg you to permit me in a few
                    words to compare, in the proper <pb n="p.395"/> spirit, my personal fortune with
                    the good fortune of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        167</note> the state. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> When I left Italy, I set sail from Brundisium at sunrise; at the ninth
                        hour of the day I reached Corcyra with all my ships. Five days later at
                        Delphi I offered sacrifice to Apollo on my own behalf, and on that of your
                        armies and fleets. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> From Delphi I arrived
                        five days later in camp. I took command of the army, removed certain great
                        obstacles to victory, and advanced. Because the camp of the enemy was
                        impregnable, and the king could not be compelled to fight, I slipped between
                        his garrisons through the pass at Petra, <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified"> For this pass, cf. XLIV. xxxii. 9; xxxv, end, and
                            the note. Diodorus XXXI. xviii practically reproduces Livy's sentence
                            above. </note> and at Pydna I conquered the king in battle. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> I brought Macedonia under the control of the
                        Roman People, and in fifteen days I finished a war which three consuls
                        before me had waged over a period of four years, each in such a way as
                        always to leave a worse situation for his successor. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> A harvest, as it were, of further successes followed;
                        all the cities of Macedonia surrendered, the royal treasures were secured,
                        the king was taken prisoner along with his children in the temple of
                        Samothrace, almost as if the gods themselves delivered him into our hands.
                        Even to me this good fortune seemed excessive, and therefore I viewed it
                        askance. I began to fear the dangers. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> of
                        the sea during the carrying of the great royal treasure to Italy, and the
                        transfer of the victorious army. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After
                        everything had been brought to Italy in a successful voyage, and I had
                        nothing left to pray for, my hope was that, since fortune is wont to plunge
                        downward from its high point, the brunt of this <pb n="p.397"/> change
                        should fall not upon the state, but upon my <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> household. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> And so I hope that the fortune of Rome has
                        completed its course in so extraordinary a disaster as mine, since my
                        triumph, as if in mockery of human vicissitudes, was interposed between the
                        two funerals of my sons. Both Perseus and I are now on view as especially
                        conspicuous samples of man's lot. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Yet he,
                        who as a prisoner saw his children led as prisoners before him, yet has
                        those children unharmed; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> whereas I who
                        celebrated the triumph over him mounted my chariot after the funeral of one
                        son, and when I returned from the Capitol found the other almost on the
                        point of death, nor is there one left of so splendid a generation of sons to
                        carry on the name of Lucius Aemilius Paulus. For two sons were given in
                        adoption, as if from a great stock of children, and they belong to the
                        Cornelian and Fabian clans. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Not a Paulus
                        is left in my house, save one old man. But I am consoled in this disaster to
                        my house by your happiness and the good fortune of the state. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These words, spoken with such magnificent
                    spirit, caused more turmoil of soul to the hearers than if his speech had been a
                    pitiable lamentation for his bereavement. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On the first of December, Gnaeus Octavius held
                    a naval triumph over King Perseus. This triumph was unadorned with prisoners or
                    spoils. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Octavius presented to each of the
                    sailors seventy-five denarii, to the pilots of the ships twice as much, and to
                    the captains, four times the amount. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The senate then met. The Fathers voted that
                    Quintus Cassius should conduct King Perseus with his son Alexander to Alba <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Alba Fucens, mentioned as a place of
                        custody in XXX. xvii. 2 and Summary LXI. </note> for safe-keeping; he was to
                    permit the king to keep intact the staff, money, silver, <pb n="p.399"/> and
                    furnishings which he had. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Bithys, the son of
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note>
                    Cotys, King of Thrace, was sent with the hostages to Carseoli for safe-keeping.
                    It was voted to place in the prison the other prisoners who were led in the
                    triumph. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics"
                            >Aemilius</hi> xxxvii relates that Perseus died no long while after by
                        self-starvation; though a story was told that his guards caused his death
                        from sleeplessness by over officious attentions. His son Alexander learned a
                        trade, and presumably lived out a normal life. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A few days after these transactions, envoys
                    came from Cotys, King of Thrace, bringing money to ransom his son and the other
                    hostages. When these envoys were brought before the senate, they used the fact
                    itself as the theme of their apology, saying that Cotys had not voluntarily
                    aided Perseus in the war, because he had been compelled to give hostages;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> the envoys pleaded that they should be
                    permitted to ransom them for whatever amount the Fathers themselves might
                    determine. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The answer authorized by the senate
                    was that the Roman People were mindful of the friendship which had existed
                    between them and Cotys, his ancestors, and the people of Thrace; <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> but the giving of hostages constituted an accusation,
                    not a defence against accusation, since the Thracian people had no reason to
                    fear Perseus even when he was at peace, to say nothing of his being involved in
                    a war against Rome. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> However, although Cotys
                    had preferred the favour of Perseus to the friendship of the Roman People, the
                    latter would reckon rather what was worthy of themselves than what action would
                    answer to his deserts, and would send him back his son and his hostages.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Benefits conferred by the Roman People,
                    said the senate, are without charge; the Romans prefer to leave the price on
                    deposit in the hearts of the recipients rather than to demand cash down. </p>
                <pb n="p.401"/>
                <p> Three envoys, Titus Quinctius Flamininus, Gaius <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> Licinius Nerva, and Marcus
                    Caninius Rebilus, were appointed to escort the hostages back to Thrace. Gifts of
                    two thousand <hi rend="italics">asses</hi> apiece were given to the Thracians.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Bithys was summoned, along with the other
                    hostages, from Carseoli, and was sent off to his father with the envoys. </p>
                <p> The king's ships captured from the Macedonians, of a size never previously seen,
                    were beached by the Campus Martius. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While recollections of the Macedonian triumph
                    remained not only in people's minds, but almost before their eyes, Lucius
                    Anicius celebrated his triumph over King Gentius and the Illyrians on the
                    festival of Quirinus. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">February
                        17.</note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Men saw in each detail a resemblance, but no
                    equality. The commander himself was the lesser, both in public esteem, as an
                    Anicius compared with an Aemilius, and in rank of office, a praetor rather than
                    a consul. Gentius could not be compared to Perseus, the Illyrians to the
                    Macedonians, nor the spoils of the one to those of the other, nor the moneys,
                    nor the gifts to the soldiers. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But though
                    accordingly the previous triumph outshone this one, yet it was also clear to
                    those who contemplated this one on its merits that it was by no means to be
                    scorned. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Within a few days Anicius had
                    overcome the Illyrian people, bold on both land and sea, and confident in their
                    terrain and their fortifications; he had captured the king and all the royal
                    family. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In his triumph he bore through the city many
                    military standards and other booty, as well as the royal furniture, twenty-seven
                    pounds of gold, nineteen pounds of silver, thirteen thousand denarii, and <pb
                        n="p.403"/> one hundred and twenty thousand Illyrian silver-pieces. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Probably the <hi rend="italics"
                            >victoriati,</hi> of 53 grains, which the Romans later imitated for use
                        about the Adriatic, cf. XLI. xiii. 7. </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> Before
                    the chariot were led King Gentius with his wife and children, Caravantius the
                    king's brother, and several prominent <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Illyrians. Anicius gave from the booty to each soldier forty-five denarii,
                    double the amount to each centurion, and three times as much to the cavalry; the
                    allies of the Latin Name received as much as the Romans, and the sailors as much
                    as the soldiers. The soldiery followed this triumph in better spirits, and the
                    leader was the subject of many <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> songs. Twenty
                    million sesterces was realized from this booty, according to Antias, besides the
                    gold and silver delivered to the treasury; since it was not clear to me from
                    what source this amount could be derived, I have quoted an historian instead of
                    stating a fact. </p>
                <p> King Gentius with his wife, his children, and his brother, was taken to
                    Spoletium for safe-keeping, in accordance with a decree of the <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> senate. The other prisoners were thrown into the prison at
                    Rome. When the people of Spoletium refused to take custody, the royal family was
                    transferred to <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Iguvium. There remained from
                    the Illyrian booty two hundred and twenty scout-ships; as prizes taken from King
                    Gentius they were presented to the people of Corcyra, Apollonia, and Dyrrhachium
                    by Quintus Cassius, in accordance with a decree of the senate. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In that year the consuls merely ravaged the
                    fields of the Ligurians, since the enemy never led out their forces. Without
                    accomplishing anything worthy of note, the consuls returned to Rome to attend to
                    the election of their successors, and on the first day of the elections,
                    declared Marcus Claudius Marcellus and Gaius Sulpicius Gallus elected as
                    consuls. On the next day there were elected as <pb n="p.405"/> praetors Lucius
                    Julius, Lucius Apuleius Saturninus, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 167</note> Aulus Licinius Nerva, Publius Rutilius Calvus,
                    Publius Quinctilius Varus, and Marcus Fonteius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> The provinces appointed for these praetors were the two city magistracies,
                    the two Spains, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A return to
                        peace-time practice; the Spains were combined during the war, so that a
                        praetor could be assigned as naval commander, or for other special purposes.
                        Cf. xvi. 4. </note> Sicily, and Sardinia. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There was an intercalation in this year; the
                    day after the Terminalia was the first day of the intercalary month. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> See XLIII. xi. 13 and the note on the
                        need at this time for frequent intercalation. This intercalary month began
                        on what would ordinarily have been the twenty-fourth of February. </note> An
                    augur died this year, Gaius Claudius; in his place, the augurs chose Titus
                    Quinctius Flamininus. The <hi rend="italics">flamen</hi> of Quirinus, Quintus
                    Fabius Pictor, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A clash between his
                        priesthood and his desire for a public career is related in XXXVII. li. 1-6;
                        his grandson or great grandson, Numerius Fabius Pictor, issued coins in
                        honour of his ancestor, showing an armed figure with the priest's headdress
                        in his hand, perhaps to indicate that Quintus was both soldier and priest
                        —unless the figure represents Quirinus, who had military functions even
                        before his identification with the deified Romulus during the late Republic.
                    </note> also died. </p>
                <p> In this year King Prusias came to Rome with his son <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Nicomedes. Entering the city with a large train, he
                    proceeded from the gate to the Forum and the judgment-seat of Quintus Cassius
                    the <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> praetor. A crowd gathered from all sides;
                    Prusias announced that he had come to bring greetings to the gods who inhabited
                    the city of Rome, and to the senate and the Roman People, and to congratulate
                    them on their victory over King Perseus and King Gentius, and on the extension
                    of their empire by placing the Macedonians and Illyrians under their <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> sway. When the praetor offered to call a session of
                    the senate for him on that very day, if he pleased, Prusias asked for a two-day
                    interval, during which he might visit the temples of the gods, the city, and his
                    friends and <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> guest-friends. There was assigned
                    to him as escort Lucius Cornelius Scipio the quaestor, who had also <pb
                        n="p.407"/> been sent to Capua to meet him; and a house was <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note> rented for
                    him, where he and his suite might be well entertained. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On the third day following, he approached the
                    senate; he offered congratulations on the victory; he recited his services in
                    the war; and he requested permission to fulfill a vow of ten full-grown victims
                    at Rome in the Capitol and one at Praeneste to Fortune. This vow, he said, was
                    for the victory of Rome; and he asked that the alliance with him should be
                    renewed, and that the land taken from King Antiochus, which had been assigned to
                    no one by the Roman People and was being held by Galatians, should be given to
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> him. Last of all, he placed his son
                    Nicomedes under the protection of the senate. </p>
                <p> He was aided by the good-will of all those who had been commanders in <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Macedonia. Consequently all but one of his requests
                    were granted; as to the land, the answer was that envoys would be sent to look
                    the matter over; if this land belonged to the Roman People and had been assigned
                    to no one, they would consider Prusias most worthy of receiving it as a
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> gift; if, on the other hand, it was shown
                    not to have belonged to Antiochus, and therefore not to have come into the
                    possession of the Roman People, or that it had been presented to the Galatians,
                    then Prusias must pardon the Roman People, if they were unwilling to wrong
                    anyone in the process of making him a <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    present. A gift, said the senate, could not be pleasing even to the recipient,
                    if he knew that the giver would take it away again whenever he <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> pleased. The senate accepted the commission to protect his
                    son Nicomedes. How great was the care with which <pb n="p.409"/> the Roman
                    People guarded the sons of kings was <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 167</note> shown, said the senate, by the case of
                    Ptolemy, King of <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Egypt. </p>
                <p> With this answer, Prusias was dismissed. Gifts were ordered given him of a value
                    of . . . <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The amount has been lost from
                        the MS.</note> sesterces, and silver vessels of fifty pounds' <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> weight. It was also voted to give to Prince
                    Nicomedes gifts to the same amount as had been given to Masgaba, the son of King
                    Masinissa. It was further voted that the victims and other requisites for
                    sacrifice should be furnished at public expense to the king, just as to Roman
                    magistrates, whether he wished to sacrifice at Rome or <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> Praeneste. Also twenty war-vessels from the fleet at
                    Brundisium were to be assigned to his <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> use;
                    until the king should reach the fleet presented to him, Lucius Cornelius Scipio
                    was to escort him uninterruptedly, and to provide for the expenses of the king
                    and his suite, until he boarded ship. </p>
                <p> They say that the king was wonderfully pleased with this expression of good-will
                    toward himself on the part of the Roman <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    People. He refused to have gifts bought for himself, but instructed his son to
                    accept the gift of the Roman People. Such is the account of Prusias given by
                    Roman <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> writers. Polybius reports <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">XXX. 18 (19. 16).</note> that this king
                    was unworthy of the dignity of so high a title; that he was accustomed to meet
                    envoys with his head shaved, while he wore a freedman's cap and called himself
                    the freedman of the Roman People, giving this as his reason for wearing the
                    emblem of this <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> class. Polybius further says
                    that when Prusias entered the senate-house at Rome, he fell down and kissed the
                    threshold of the <pb n="p.411"/> senatehouse, hailed the senate as his
                    saviour-gods, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This title (Soter) was
                        adopted by several Hellenistic rulers, notably Ptolemy the First. </note>
                    and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 167</note>
                    indulged in further speech which conveyed more disgrace to himself than honour
                    to his hearers. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> After remaining in the vicinity of Rome no
                    more than thirty days, he set out for his kingdom, and . . . <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A few lines are missing in the MS. at
                        the end of this book. The lost verb of this sentence is presumably
                            <quote>egged on,</quote> or the like. </note> the war under way between
                    Eumenes and the Galatians. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
