<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 45</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <!--<biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>-->
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="book">
                <head>Rome stabilizes the East</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The heralds of victory travelled to Rome
                        with the utmost possible speed, but on their arrival they found that the
                        rejoicings over it had forestalled them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Four days after the battle, while the Games were going on in the Campus
                        Martius, a whispered rumour suddenly spread amongst the whole concourse of
                        spectators to the effect that a battle had taken place in Macedonia
                        resulting in the utter defeat of the king. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Then the rumour grew louder until at last cheers and applause arose as
                        though definite tidings of victory had been brought to them. The magistrates
                        were taken by surprise and enquired who had started this sudden outburst of
                        joy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As no one could be found the
                        excitement produced by what they had taken for a certainty calmed down, but
                        still they were convinced that it was a happy omen, which was subsequently
                        verified by the arrival of the authentic messengers. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> They were delighted quite as much at their
                        prognostications proving true as at the victory itself. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> A second outburst amongst the crowd in the Circus is
                        recorded. On 17th September, the second day of the Roman Games, whilst the
                        consul was mounting the stand to start the chariots, a despatch-bearer who
                        said that he had come from Macedonia handed him a despatch wreathed in
                        laurel. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After the chariots were started he
                        mounted his own and, riding across the course to the raised benches where
                        the spectators were seated, held up the laurelled despatch for the people to
                        see. On catching sight of it, the populace, regardless of the races, ran
                        down into the middle of the Circus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                        consul called the senate together there and after obtaining their sanction,
                        read the despatch to the onlookers in their seats. He announced that his
                        colleague Lucius Aemilius had fought a decisive battle with Perseus, that
                        the Macedonian army had been routed and cut to pieces, that the king with
                            <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> a few of his followers was a
                        fugitive, and that all the cities of Macedonia had passed under the power of
                        Rome. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On hearing this, cheers and frantic
                        applause broke out; most of the men deserted the Games and went home to
                        carry the joyful news to their wives and children. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> This was thirteen days after the battle had been fought
                        in Macedonia. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The following day there was a meeting of
                        the senate in the senate-house, and a decree was made ordering public
                        thanksgivings. The senators also passed a resolution that, with the
                        exception of the regular soldiers and the seamen of the fleet the consul
                        should disband those who had taken the military oath to him. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The question of the disbandment of the soldiers
                        and seamen was postponed until the arrival of the deputation from L.
                        Aemilius, by whom the despatch-bearer had been sent on in advance.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On 25th September, about 8 A.M., they
                        entered the City. A vast crowd had gone out to meet them at various points
                        and accompany them back to the City. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Carrying the throng along with them they made their way to the Forum, and
                        from there to the senate-house. The senate happened to be in session, and
                        the consul brought them into the House. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        They were detained there for some time whilst they described the strength of
                        the king's troops, both horse and foot, the numbers of those killed and
                        those taken prisoners, the small cost at which such a slaughter of the enemy
                        had been made, and the panic in which the king had fled. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> They thought he would probably make for Samothrace, and
                        they informed the senate that the fleet was ready to take up the pursuit; he
                        could not escape either by land or sea. Shortly afterwards they were
                        conducted to the Assembly, where they made much the same statement, and the
                        rejoicings were renewed on the consul <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                        giving notice that all the sacred buildings were opened, and every one was
                        to go from the Assembly and offer, each for himself, his thanks to the gods.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> All the temples throughout the City
                        were filled with crowds of women as well as men. The senators were recalled
                        to the senate-house and made a decree that, in consideration of the glorious
                        victory won by L. Aemilius, thanksgivings should be offered <milestone
                            n="9??" unit="section"/> at all the shrines for five days, and the
                        victims sacrificed were to be full-grown animals. Orders were given that the
                        ships which were lying in the Tiber fully equipped for service, <milestone
                            n="10??" unit="section"/> to be sent to Macedonia should occasion arise,
                        were to be hauled up and placed in dock; the crews were to receive a year's
                        pay and be discharged, as also all who had taken the military oath to the
                        consul. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In addition to these the troops
                        in Corcyra, Brundisium and the coast of the Hadriatic, or in the district of
                        Larinum-an army had been distributed in all these places as a reserve for C.
                        Licinius to take to the support of his colleague, should it become
                        necessary-were ordered to be disbanded. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> A
                        five days' thanksgiving was proclaimed before the Assembly, to commence on
                        26th September. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The two commissioners who had been sent to
                        Illyria reported on their return that the Illyrian army had been destroyed
                        and Gentius taken prisoner, and that Illyria had made formal submission to
                        Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For these successes, gained under
                        the leadership and auspices of L. Anicius, the praetor, the senate ordered a
                        three days' thanksgiving. A second celebration of the Latin Festival was
                        proclaimed by the consul for 10th-12th November. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Some writers assert that the envoys from Rhodes who
                        were still in Rome were summoned before the senate after the announcement of
                        the victory, as if to expose them and their stupid arrogance to ridicule.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Agepolis, their leader, is reported to
                        have declared that they had been sent by the government of Rhodes to make
                        peace between Perseus and the Romans because that war was burdensome and
                        hurtful to the <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> whole of Greece and an
                        expensive and unprofitable one to the Romans themselves. Now that the war
                        had ended otherwise, the Fortune who presides over Rome had done well to
                        give them an opportunity of congratulating the Romans on their splendid
                        victory. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> So far the Rhodians. The senate's
                        reply was to the effect that it was neither to promote the interests of
                        Greece nor to save the Roman exchequer that the Rhodians had despatched that
                        embassy, but solely in the interest of Perseus. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Had they really felt as anxious about these two matters
                        as they pretended to be, the envoys ought to have been sent at the time when
                        Perseus led his army into Thrace and went on for two years attacking the
                        cities of Greece, some by actual investment, others by intimidation; there
                        was no mention of peace made by the Rhodians then. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> It was not till they learnt that the mountain defiles
                        had been crossed and the Romans had invaded Macedonia that they sent their
                        envoys, their only motive being to save Perseus from the dangers which were
                        hanging over him. With this reply the envoys were dismissed. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About this time M. Marcellus, who was on
                        his way home from Spain, captured the important city of Marcolica, and
                        brought into the treasury 10 pounds' weight of gold and a quantity of silver
                        amounting to one million sesterces. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        consul Paulus Aemilius was, as I have already said, still in camp at Sirae,
                        in the Odomantic country, when three persons of mean appearance brought him
                        a letter from Perseus. On seeing the missive he is said to have shed tears
                        over the fate that befalls men, for the man who a short time ago was not
                        contented with his kingdom of <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> Macedonia,
                        but made an attack on the Dardanians and the Illyrians, and had called out
                        the auxiliary levies of the Bastarnae-that man had now lost his army, was
                        driven out of his kingdom a homeless wanderer into a small island where, as
                        a suppliant, he was protected by the sanctity of the temple, not by any
                        strength which he possessed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When,
                        however, he read the salutation, "From King Perseus to the consul Paulus."
                        the man's utter failure to realise his condition destroyed all feeling of
                        compassion. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Consequently, though in the
                        body of the letter there were appeals for mercy which were anything but
                        kingly, the messengers were dismissed without any reply either by word of
                        mouth or in writing. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Perseus saw that he
                        must forget his royal title in his defeat, and a second letter was sent in
                        which he described himself by his personal name. In this he begged most
                        urgently that some persons might be sent to him with whom he could confer as
                        to his status and the circumstances in which he was placed. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The three who were sent to him were P. Lentulus, A.
                        Postumius Albinus and A. Antonius. Nothing resulted from this conference;
                        Perseus clung desperately to his royal title, and Paulus was determined that
                        he should place himself and all that he possessed at the mercy of Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meantime the fleet under Cn. Octavius had
                        put in at Samothrace. Octavius thought that the presence of the fleet would
                        intimidate Perseus, and he tried to induce him to surrender by appealing to
                        his hopes and fears. An incident brought about either by accident or design
                        assisted his efforts. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> A young man of
                        distinction, L. Atilius, noticed that the people of Samothrace were holding
                        an assembly, and he requested the magistrates to allow him to address a few
                        words to the people. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Permission being
                        granted, he began: "My friends and hosts of Samothrace, is it true or false
                        what we have heard, that this is a consecrated island and that its soil is
                        everywhere sacred and inviolable?" <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There
                        was a unanimous response in the affirmative, and he went on: "Why, then, is
                        it polluted and violated by a murderer stained with the blood of King
                        Eumenes? And whilst all approach to your sacred shrines is forbidden to
                        those who do not come with clean hands before commencing any holy rite, will
                        you allow them to be contaminated by the presence of a blood-stained
                        assassin?" <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was well known through all
                        the cities of Greece that the murder of Eumenes at Delphi had been attempted
                        and all but effected by Euander. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They were
                        aware that the temple and the whole of the island lay at the mercy of the
                        Romans, and they felt, too, that they deserved the reproach. Theondas, their
                        chief magistrate-they give him the title of "king"-was accordingly sent to
                        Perseus to inform him that Euander was accused of murder and that courts
                        were established after the manner of their ancestors to try those who were
                        alleged to have entered the sacred boundaries with unholy hands. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> If Euander felt sure that he would be proved
                        innocent of any capital crime let him appear to defend himself, but if he
                        did not dare to stand his trial, let him deliver the temple from a curse end
                        take measures for his personal safety. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Perseus called Euander aside and advised him on no account to undergo a
                        trial; he was no match for his accusers, either on the merits of the case or
                        in the influence which he possessed. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He
                        was haunted by the fear that if Euander were found guilty he would bring him
                        in as the instigator of that infamous crime. What was left for him to do but
                        to die bravely? Euander raised no objection openly, but after saying that he
                        would rather die by poison than by the sword, he made preparations for
                        secret flight. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On this coming to the
                        king's ears he was afraid that Euander, by escaping punishment, might bring
                        down the wrath of the Samothracians upon himself under the belief that he
                        had connived at his escape. He therefore gave orders for Euander to be put
                        to death. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> After the reckless perpetration
                        of this murder he suddenly reflected that he had beyond any doubt brought
                        upon himself the blood-guiltiness which had previously rested on Euander.
                        Eumenes had been wounded by Euander in Delphi, and now he himself had put
                        Euander to death in Samothrace. Thus he alone was responsible for the
                        profanation of the two holiest temples in the world by human blood.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He averted this terrible charge by
                        bribing Theondas and inducing him to announce to the people that Euander had
                        taken his own life. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> However, the commission of such a crime
                        against his one remaining friend, who had been tested through so many
                        misfortunes and who had been betrayed because he would not betray his
                        master, alienated all men's sympathies from him. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Each thinking only of himself went over to the Romans,
                        and as he was left all but alone he was compelled to form plans for flight.
                        There was a Cretan named Oroandas who was familiar with the coast of Thrace
                        through his trading journeys. Perseus called upon him to take him on board
                        with him to Cotys. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There was a bay formed
                        by one of the headlands of Samothrace, named from the adjacent temple of
                        Demeter the Demetrium, and there the boat was lying. Just after sunset
                        everything required for use, and as much of the money as could be carried
                        without detection, was put on board. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        king with three who shared his flight went out at midnight through a door at
                        the back of the house into the garden which was close to his room, and after
                        climbing the wall with considerable difficulty succeeded in reaching the
                        shore. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Oroandas had only waited till the
                        money was on board, and as soon as it grew dark weighed anchor and put out
                        to sea for Crete. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As no ship was to be
                        found in the harbour Perseus wandered about for some time on the shore. At
                        last, dreading the approach of day, he did not dare to return to his
                        quarters but hid himself in a dark corner on one side of the temple.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The children of the Macedonian
                        nobility who were chosen to wait on the king used to be known as "the royal
                        pages." <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These boys had followed the king
                        in his flight, and even now refused to desert him until a proclamation was
                        published by order of Cnaeus Octavius, stating that the royal pages and any
                        other Macedonians who were in Samothrace would, if they went to the Romans,
                        preserve their personal safety and liberty, and all their property, both
                        what they had with them and what they had left in Macedonia. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> After this pronouncement all went over and
                        reported themselves to C. Postumius, one of the military tribunes. Ion, the
                        Thessalian, also gave up the king's little children to Octavius, and now no
                        one was left with the king except his eldest son Philip. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Then Perseus, inveighing against Fortune and the gods
                        in whose temple he was for refusing all aid to their suppliants, surrendered
                        himself and his son into the hands of Octavius. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Orders were given for him to be put on board the
                        commander's ship, together with what remained of the money. The fleet at
                        once sailed back to Amphipolis. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> From
                        there Octavius sent the king to the consul's camp, having previously advised
                        him that the king was being brought to his camp as a prisoner. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Paulus regarded the capture of the king as
                        a second victory, as it really was, and on receiving the news offered
                        sacrifices. He then called his council together and read the praetor's
                        despatch to them. Q. Aelius Tubero was sent to meet the king, the rest were
                        ordered to remain together at the headquarters tent. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Never has so great a crowd been brought together at any
                        other sight. In the time of our fathers Syphax was brought as a captive
                        monarch into the Roman camp. But he is not to be compared with Perseus in
                        respect either of his own renown or that of his nation, and besides, he had
                        only played a subordinate part in the Punic War, as Gentius had done in the
                        Macedonian. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Whereas Perseus was the head
                        and supreme director of the war; and not only were all eyes drawn to him
                        through his own reputation and that of his father and grandfather and others
                        to whom he was allied by blood relationship, but he was heir to the glory of
                        Philip and Alexander the Great, who raised the Macedonian Empire to a
                        supreme position in the world. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Perseus
                        entered the camp in mourning garb without a single attendant to make him
                        more pitiable by sharing his misfortunes. His only companion was his son.
                        Owing to the crowd who surrounded him he was unable to make any progress
                        until the consul sent his lictors to clear a passage for him to the
                        headquarters tent. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After asking the rest
                        to keep their seats the consul went forward a few steps and held out his
                        hand to the king as he entered, and when he was going to prostrate himself
                        he raised him to his feet and would not allow him to embrace his knees as a
                        suppliant. Once inside the tent, he bade him take his seat facing the
                        members of the council. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The first question put to him was what
                        wrongs had he suffered which compelled him to commence war against Rome in
                        such an aggressive temper and so imperil his own existence and that of his
                        kingdom? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Whilst all were waiting for his
                        answer, he kept his eyes fixed on the ground and wept for some time in
                        silence. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then the consul continued: "Had
                        you received the crown in your youth I should be the less surprised at your
                        not knowing what weight Rome possesses either as a friend or an enemy.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But now, after having been associated
                        with your father in his war against us and in the peace which followed, and
                        which you well remember we kept with perfect good faith towards him, what
                        could have been your object in choosing war rather than peace with those
                        whose strength you have felt in war and whose fidelity you have experienced
                        in peace?" He made no reply to either the question or the charge. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Then the consul said: "Well, however this may
                        have been brought about, whether through the blindness of human nature or
                        through chance, or through the decree of Fate, keep a stout heart. The
                        clemency of the people of Rome, which has been shown in the misfortunes of
                        many kings and nations, affords you not only a hope, but a tolerably certain
                        guarantee of your personal safety." <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He
                        said this in Greek to Perseus, and then turning to the council he said in
                        Latin, "You see a striking example of the mutability of human affairs.
                        Especially to you younger men am I now speaking-it does not become us,
                        therefore, in the hour of prosperity to form any aggressive designs against
                        anyone, or to trust the fortune of the moment, for it is uncertain what the
                        evening will bring. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He only will prove
                        himself a man whose spirit is not elated by the breath of prosperity nor
                        broken by the blasts of adversity." When the council had broken up, the
                        custody of the king was entrusted to Q. Aelius. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> On that day he was invited to dine with the council,
                        and every mark of honour was shown to him which could be shown to any one in
                        his position. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this the army went into winter
                        quarters. Amphipolis took in the greater portion. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The rest were disposed in the neighbouring cities. Such
                        was the end of the war which had for four successive years been waged
                        between the Romans and Perseus, and the end, too, of a kingdom long renowned
                        through the whole of Asia and most of Europe. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> From Caranus, the first king, twenty monarchs are
                        enumerated down to Perseus. He received the crown in the consulship of L.
                        Fulvius and L. Manlius, and was recognised as king by the senate when M.
                        Junius and A. Manlius were the consuls. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        His reign lasted eleven years. The nation of the Macedonians was almost
                        unknown to fame down to the time of Philip, the son of Amyntas. From that
                        time it began to extend under his rule, but it still confined itself within
                        the limits of Europe, embracing the whole of Greece and portions of Thrace
                        and Illyria. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then it overflowed into Asia
                        and during the thirteen years of Alexander's reign he first brought under
                        his power the whole of the Persian dominions, the extent of which was almost
                        illimitable, and then he traversed Arabia and India <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> up to where the Red Sea washes the remotest frontiers
                        of the world. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In those days the empire of
                        Macedonia was the greatest in the world, but after Alexander's death it was
                        broken up into numerous kingdoms, each man grasping at power for himself
                        until its strength was exhausted by internal conflicts, and it sank from the
                        highest pinnacle of prosperity to its final disappearance. It stood for
                        about 150 years. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the news of the victory of Rome had
                        spread into Asia, Antenor, who was lying with a fleet of swift ships at
                        Phanae, left that place for Cassandrea. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> C.
                        Popilius was at Delos to escort the supply ships destined for Macedonia, and
                        when he learnt that the war in Macedonia was at an end and that the enemy
                        vessels had left their station he sent home the ships of the allies which
                        were under his command and set sail for Egypt to <milestone n="3??"
                            unit="section"/> carry out the mission with which he was charged. He was
                        anxious to meet Antiochus, if possible, before he approached the walls of
                        Alexandria. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Coasting along the shores of
                        Asia the commissioners arrived at Loryma, a harbour little more than twenty
                        miles from Rhodes and facing the city. Here some of the leading Rhodians had
                        come to meet them-for by this time the news of the victory had been carried
                        to Rhodes-and begged them to break their journey at Rhodes. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> They said that it deeply concerned the good name and
                        safety of their city that the commissioners should find out for themselves
                        what had been going on and what was going on at the time, and should carry
                        back to Rome what they had personally ascertained and not simply empty
                        rumours. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For a long time they refused, but
                        at last consented to a brief interruption of their voyage for the sake of an
                        allied city. After they had entered Rhodes, these same men persuaded them to
                        appear before their assembly. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                        appearance of the commissioners increased rather than allayed the fears of
                        the citizens. Popilius brought up all the hostile speeches and acts of which
                        they had been guilty during the war, whether individually or collectively.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Being a man of fierce temper, he made
                        the matters he spoke about appear still more heinous by his angry expression
                        and the sternness of his voice. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> So though
                        the citizens had given him no personal offence, they could gather from the
                        embittered tone of one Roman senator what the feelings of the senate as a
                        whole were towards them. The address of C. Decimius was much more moderate.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> With regard to most of the things
                        that Popilius had mentioned, he said that the blame did not rest with the
                        people, but with a few agitators who had stirred up the mob, and, winning
                        their votes by bribery, had passed decrees filled with flattery of the king,
                        and had been the means of those embassies being sent to him which had caused
                        the Rhodians as much shame as regret. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> All
                        this, if the people were sound at heart, would recoil on the heads of the
                        guilty parties. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> His words were loudly
                        applauded, for he not only exculpated the great body of the citizens, but he
                        fastened the guilt on those who were really responsible for the mischief.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> When, therefore, their leaders spoke
                        in reply, those of them who tried to explain away the charges which Popilius
                        had made were not listened to with anything like the approval which greeted
                        those who agreed with Decimius that the authors of the evil should be made
                        to atone for the evil they had done. A decree was at once passed that those
                        who were convicted of having spoken or acted in favour of Perseus against
                        the Romans should be sentenced to death. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        Some had left the city before the Romans came, others took their own lives.
                        The commissioners did not stay beyond five days in Rhodes, and then went on
                        to Alexandria. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Their departure did not
                        make the Rhodians any the more slack in commencing the trials under the
                        decree passed when the commissioners were present; the mildness of Decimius
                        did quite as much to strengthen their resolution to see the thing through as
                        the severity of Popilius. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> (Livy takes up the history from Book
                        24.19) Antiochus was now master of the rest of Egypt, but after his check
                        before Alexandria he retired from its walls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> The elder Ptolemy, whose restoration to his throne Antiochus pretended
                        was his sole object in invading Egypt was left at Memphis, and Antiochus
                        withdrew his army into Syria, prepared to attack whichever brother should
                        prove victorious. Ptolemy was quite aware of his intention, and hoped that
                        by playing upon his brother's fears and holding out the prospect of a siege
                        he might possibly, with the active assistance of his sister and the
                        acquiescence of his brother's friends, be admitted into Alexandria.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He began a correspondence with his
                        sister and his brother's friends, and continued to write to them until he
                        had come to terms with them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> What made him
                        suspicious of Antiochus was that after handing over the rest of Egypt he had
                        left a strong garrison in Pelusium. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was
                        obvious that Antiochus was holding the key of Egypt in order to make a fresh
                        invasion whenever he chose, and for Ptolemy to engage in intestine strife
                        with his brother would prove to be his ruin, since, even if victorious, he
                        would be no match for Antiochus after an exhausting war. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> These wise reflections met with the approval of his
                        brother and his friends, and his sister helped him very largely by her
                        advice and her appeals to the brother. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> So
                        peace was made, and he was admitted into Alexandria with everybody's
                        consent; even the populace manifested no opposition, though they had
                        suffered severely both during the investment and after the retirement of the
                        enemy, as no supplies were being brought in from the rest of Egypt. This
                        ought to have given the liveliest satisfaction to Antiochus, had his motive
                        for bringing his army into Egypt really been the restoration of Ptolemy.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For this was the pretext he alleged in
                        all his communications to the cities of Greece and Asia, and in his replies
                        to their deputations. But he was so intensely annoyed at what had happened
                        that he began to make preparations for war in a much more aggressive and
                        ruthless temper against the two brothers than he had previously shown
                        against the one. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He at once sent his fleet
                        to Cyprus, and in the first days of spring set his army in motion for Egypt
                        and advanced into Coelo-Syria. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When near
                        Rhinocolura he was met by envoys from Ptolemy, who thanked him for the
                        recovery of his ancestral crown and begged him to protect the boon he had
                        conferred and to say clearly what he wanted rather than attack him as an
                        enemy by force of arms after being his friend. Antiochus replied that he
                        would not recall his fleet or withdraw his army on any other conditions than
                        the cession of Cyprus and of Pelusium and the surrounding country at the
                        mouth of the Nile. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He further fixed a day
                        by which he was to receive a reply stating the acceptance of the conditions.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the time for the suspension of
                        hostilities had elapsed he marched through the desert of Arabia, while his
                        fleet was sailing up the mouth of the Nile to Pelusium. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> After receiving the submission of the inhabitants of
                        Memphis and of the rest of the Egyptian people, some submitting voluntarily,
                        others under threats, he marched by easy stages towards Alexandria.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After crossing the river at Eleusis,
                        about four miles from Alexandria, he was met by the Roman commissioners, to
                        whom he gave a friendly greeting and held out his hand to Popilius.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Popilius, however, placed in his hand
                        the tablets on which was written the decree of the senate and told him first
                        of all to read that. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After reading it
                        through he said he would call his friends into council and consider what he
                        ought to do. Popilius, stern and imperious as ever, drew a circle round the
                        king with the stick he was carrying and said, "Before you step out of that
                        circle give me a reply to lay before the senate." For a few moments he
                        hesitated, astounded at such a peremptory order, and at last replied, "I
                        will do what the senate thinks right." <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Not
                        till then did Popilius extend his hand to the king as to a friend and ally.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Antiochus evacuated Egypt at the
                        appointed date, and the commissioners exerted their authority to establish a
                        lasting concord between the brothers, as they had as yet hardly made peace
                        with each other. They then sailed to Cyprus and sent home the fleet of
                        Antiochus which had defeated the Egyptian ships in a naval engagement.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The work of the commissioners won
                        great renown amongst the nations, for it was undoubtedly owing to this that
                        Egypt had been rescued out of the hands of Antiochus and the crown restored
                        to the Ptolemaic dynasty. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Whilst one of
                        the consuls for the year had signalised his consulship by a famous victory,
                        the other remained in comparative obscurity because he had no opportunity of
                        distinguishing himself. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At the outset, in
                        fixing the day for the muster of his legions, he did so in a place where the
                        auspices had not been taken. The matter was referred to the augurs, who
                        announced that the proceeding was invalid. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                        /> After his departure into Gaul he selected a spot near the Macrian Plain
                        at the foot of Mount Sicimina and Papinus for his standing camp and then
                        went into winter quarters in the same neighbourhood with the troops of the
                        Latin allies; the Roman legions owing to the informality in appointing the
                        day for their assembling, remained in Rome. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> The praetors, with the exception of C. Papirius Corbo, went to their
                        respective provinces. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Sardinia had been
                        allotted to him, but the senate decided that he should exercise the alien
                        jurisdiction in Rome, for this, too, the ballot had assigned to him. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The commissioners who had been sent to
                        Antiochus returned to Rome, and Popilius informed the senate that the
                        differences between the kings had been adjusted and the army had returned to
                        Syria. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Afterwards envoys from the monarchs
                        themselves arrived. Those from Antiochus assured the senate that their king
                        regarded the peace which the senate had imposed as preferable to any
                        victory, and had obeyed the instructions of the Roman commissioners just as
                        though they had been the commands of the gods. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> They then offered their congratulations on the victory,
                        which they said the king would have done his utmost to further had any
                            <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> orders been given him to that
                        effect. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The envoys from Ptolemy returned
                        thanks in the name of the king and Cleopatra; they were more indebted to the
                        senate and people of Rome than to their parents or to the immortal gods, for
                        it was through them that they had been delivered from the miseries of a
                        siege and had recovered the throne when it was all but lost. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> The senate replied that Antiochus had done what
                        was right and proper in obeying the commissioners, and this was a source of
                        gratification to the senate and citizens of Rome; <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> as regards the Egyptian monarchs, Ptolemy and
                        Cleopatra, whatever benefit and advantage had been gained through their
                        action was a cause of rejoicing to the senate, and they would make it their
                        business to see that the two <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> monarchs
                        should always look upon the people of Rome as the most secure and
                        trustworthy protectors of their kingdom. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        C. Papirius was charged with the task of sending the customary presents to
                        the envoys. </p>
                    <p> Their departure was followed by the arrival of deputations from Pisae and
                        Luna, who had a dispute. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Pisans
                        complained that they had been expelled from their territory by the Roman
                        colonists; those from Luna asseverated that the land in question had been
                        assigned to them by the commissioners who settled the colony. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> The senate sent five commissioners to
                        investigate the facts and fix the boundaries-namely, Q. Fabius Buteo, P.
                        Cornelius Blasio, T. Sempronius Musca, L. Naevius Balbus and C. Apuleius
                        Saturninus. A joint deputation from Eumenes and the brothers Attalus and
                        Athenaeus also came to offer their congratulations on the victory.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Masgaba, the son of Masinissa, had
                        landed at Puteoli, and the quaestor L. Manlius was sent with a sum of money
                        to meet him and conduct him to Rome at the expense of the State. Immediately
                        on his arrival in Rome the senate granted him an audience. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> The young prince spoke in such a way as to make the
                        matter of his speech still more welcome by the way he put it. He stated the
                        force of cavalry and infantry, the number of elephants, the quantity of corn
                        which his father had sent to Macedonia during the last four years.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Two things made him blush; one was
                        that the senate through their ambassadors had requested him instead of
                        commanding him to furnish what was necessary for the war, the other was that
                        they had sent money to pay for the corn. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        Masinissa, he said, had not forgotten that it was to the Romans that he owed
                        his kingdom and the subsequent extension of it; he was quite contented with
                        enjoying the usufruct of it and was fully aware that the proprietary
                        remained with those who gave it to him. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        He thought it only right that they should take and not ask or pay for the
                        produce of the soil which they had given. What was over and above the
                        requirements of the people of Rome would be amply sufficient for him.
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> He then informed the senate that
                        after leaving his father with these instructions he was overtaken by mounted
                        messengers who informed him of the final defeat of Macedonia and brought an
                        order for him to offer his father's congratulations to the senate, and to
                        say that he was so rejoiced at this that he wished to go to Rome and offer
                        sacrifices and thanksgivings in the Capitol if the senate would give him
                        permission. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In reply the prince was told that
                        Masinissa had acted as became an honourable and grateful man in enhancing
                        the value and dignity of benefits which were justly due to him. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The people of Rome had received from him loyal
                        and powerful assistance in the Punic War, and it was through their good
                        offices that he had gained his crown. In this equal interchange of benefits
                        he had subsequently rendered every possible assistance in the successive
                        wars against three kings. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was not
                        surprising that the victory of Rome should give the king pleasure, seeing
                        how he had associated his own fortunes and those of his kingdom with the
                        cause of Rome. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Let him offer his
                        thanksgivings for the victory to the gods at home; his son would do this for
                        him in Rome. He had done quite enough in offering congratulations in his own
                        and his father's name. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The senate did not
                        think it would be to the interest of Rome for him to leave his kingdom and
                        come away from Africa, especially as he would gain no advantage by it.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The quaestor received instructions to
                        spend 100 pounds of silver in presents for the prince, to escort him to
                        Puteoli and defray all his expenses as long as he was in Italy, and also to
                        hire two vessels in which he and his suite were to be conveyed to Africa.
                        Presents of apparel were made to all his attendants, including the slaves.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Not long after a communication was
                        received from Misagenes, the <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> second son
                        of Masinissa, stating that after Perseus' defeat he had been sent by L.
                        Paulus with his cavalry back to Africa, that the fleet had been scattered
                        during the voyage in the Hadriatic, and that he had been carried down to
                        Brundisium and was ill. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> L. Stertinius was
                        sent to Brundisium with presents of equal value to those given to his
                        brother in Rome, and was instructed to place a house at his disposal. </p>
                    <p>. . . .</p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The freedmen had been distributed amongst
                        the four City tribes, those being excepted who had a son of their own more
                        than five years old, those they ordered <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                        to be registered where they had been assessed at the last census, and also
                        all who possessed a farm or farms more than 30,000 sesterces in value, these
                        were given the right of being registered in the local tribes. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Notwithstanding these reservations Claudius
                        insisted that without an order of the people the suffrage could not be taken
                        away from an individual freedman, much less from the order as a whole.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For though the censor could remove him
                        from his tribe, which simply meant ordering him to change his tribe, he had
                        no power to remove him from all the thirty-five tribes; that meant depriving
                        him of his citizenship and personal freedom, not deciding where he was to be
                        registered, but excluding him from the list of citizens altogether.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This was the question at issue between
                        them. At last they made a compromise. Out of the four City tribes they
                        decided to choose one by lot, publicly in the Hall of Liberty, into which
                        all who had ever been slaves should be incorporated. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The lot fell upon the Esquiline tribe, and Tiberius
                        Gracchus announced that it was decided that all the freedmen should be
                        enrolled in that tribe. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This action of the
                        censors was greatly appreciated by the senate, and a vote of thanks was
                        accorded to Sempronius for his perseverance in carrying so wise a measure
                        and to Claudius for not opposing it. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> More
                        names were struck off the senatorial roll than had been the case under
                        former censors, and also off the register of the equites. Both censors
                        concurred in removing them from their tribes, and no one who was branded by
                        the one had the stigma effaced by the other. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> They requested that their term of office-eighteen months-might be
                        extended to allow of the repair of buildings and the completion of the works
                        for which they had placed contracts, but a tribune of the plebs, Cneius
                        Tremellius, interposed his veto because he had <supplied reason="omitted">not</supplied> been chosen for the senate.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> During this year C. Cicereius
                        dedicated the temple of Monata on the Alban Mount, five years after he had
                        vowed it, and L. Postumius Albinus was inaugurated as a Flamen of Mars. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the new consuls, Q. Aelius and M.
                        Junius, brought up in the senate the allocations of the provinces, the House
                        decided that Spain should again form two provinces-during the Macedonian war
                            <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> it had only formed one-and that L.
                        Paulus and L. Anicius should continue to hold Macedonia and Illyria until,
                        in concert with the commissioners, they had settled the confusion caused by
                        the war and given the disturbed countries a constitution other than the
                        monarchical. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Pisae and Gaul were allotted
                        to the consuls, each to be held with two legions and 400 cavalry. The result
                        of the balloting among the praetors was that the civic jurisdiction fell to
                        Q. Cassius, the alien to M. Juventius Thalna, Sicily to Ti. Claudius Nero,
                        Hither Spain to Cneius Fulvius, and Further Spain to C. Licinius Nerva.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Sardinia had fallen to A. Manlius
                        Torquatus, but he was unable to go to his province as he was detained by the
                        enquiry into criminal cases which the senate had ordered. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The senate was next consulted as to various portents
                        which had been announced. The temple of the Penates in Velia had been struck
                        by lightning, as had also the two gates and a portion of the wall at
                        Minervium. At Anagnia there had been a shower of earth, and at Lanuvium a
                        blazing torch had been seen in the heavens. M. Valerius, who was farming
                        some of the State land at Calatia, reported that blood had trickled from his
                        hearth for three days and two nights. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Mainly on account of this latter portent the keepers were ordered to consult
                        the Sacred Books, and they announced special intercessions for one day and a
                        sacrifice of fifty goats in the Forum. In expiation of the other portents
                        there were special intercessions at all the shrines for a second day,
                        sacrifices of full-grown victims, and the lustration of the City. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Further, with the purpose of doing honour to the
                        immortal gods, the senate made the following decree: "Whereas our enemies
                        have been overcome, and Macedonia and Illyria have passed under the power of
                        the people of Rome, gifts should be presented at all the shrines <milestone
                            n="8??" unit="section"/> equal to those which had been offered after the
                        defeat of Antiochus in the consulship of Appius Claudius and M. Sempronius."
                        Q. Cassius and M. Juventius were to see that these offerings were made. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then the commissioners were appointed who
                        were to advise L. Paulus and L. Anicius as to the settlement of the
                        conquered provinces. The senate decreed ten for Macedonia and five for
                        Illyria. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Those for Macedonia were first
                        selected. They were A. Postumius Luscus, C. Claudius (both of them had been
                        censors), Q. Fabius Labeo, . . . C. Licinius Crassus, who had been Paulus'
                        colleague in the consulship and was at the time in command of Gaul, his
                        proconsulship having been extended. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These
                        were all ex-consuls, and there were added to their number Cn. Domitius
                        Ahenobarbus, Servius Cornelius Sulla, L. Junius, T. Numisius Tarquiniensis
                        and A. Terentius Varro. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The five who were
                        to act as commissioners for the settlement of Illyria were P. Aelius Ligus
                        (an ex-consul), C. Cicereius and Cnaeus Baebius Tamphilus-the latter had
                        been praetor the last year, Cicereius several years previously-P. Terentius
                        Tuscivicanus and P. Manlius. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consuls
                        were advised by the senate to arrange or ballot for their provinces as soon
                        as possible, as one of them would have to succeed C. Licinius in Gaul, in
                        consequence of his appointment as commissioner. They balloted, and Pisae
                        fell to M. Junius. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He decided before
                        leaving for his province to introduce to the senate the various deputations
                        who had come from all quarters to Rome to offer their congratulations. Q.
                        Aelius had Gaul allotted to him. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Although
                        the fifteen commissioners were men of such standing that it could reasonably
                        be hoped that the generals acting on their advice would form no decisions
                        unworthy of the clemency or the honour of Rome, the main principles of the
                        settlement were nevertheless discussed in the senate in order that the
                        commissioners might carry them in outline to the commanders. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> First of all it was resolved that the
                        Macedonians and Illyrians should be free peoples, so that it might be clear
                        to all the world that the arms of Rome did not carry slavery to the free,
                        but on the contrary freedom to the enslaved; <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> and also that amongst those nations which enjoyed liberty, the security
                        and permanence of their liberty rested under the protection of Rome, whilst
                        on the other hand those who lived under the rule of kings might be led to
                        believe that their kings were all the more just and merciful through the
                        respect they felt for Rome, and if ever their sovereigns began war, the
                        issue of the war would bring victory to Rome and liberty to the people.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was also resolved to abolish all
                        contracts for working the mines of Macedonia, which afforded a considerable
                        revenue, and also all leases of the royal domains; <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> these could not be carried on without the tax-farmer,
                        and wherever the tax-farmer flourished either the law lost its authority or
                        the subjects their liberty. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Nor were the
                        Macedonians able to work them themselves, for where those in charge found
                        plunder ready to their hand there were never lacking causes for quarrels and
                        riots. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The national council was
                        suppressed, lest some unprincipled flatterer of the mob should turn the safe
                        and reasonable liberty which had been granted into a dangerous and fatal
                        licence. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Macedonia was to be divided into
                        four cantons, each to have its own council, and the tribute to Rome was to
                        be half what they had been accustomed to pay to the king. The same
                        regulations were made in the case of Illyria. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The other measures were left to the generals and
                        commissioners, as they would be dealing with matters on the spot and would
                        be able to make more definite arrangements. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Amongst the numerous deputations from
                        kings and free States and communities Attalus, the brother of Eumenes,
                        attracted all men's eyes and thoughts. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He
                        was received by the men who had taken part with him in the war with as
                        hearty a welcome as though Eumenes himself had come. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Two objects had brought him to Rome, to all appearance
                        honourable ones; one was to offer congratulations on the victory which he
                        had himself helped to win, the other was to complain of an inroad of the
                        Gauls and a defeat which he had sustained and which seriously threatened his
                        kingdom. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But he was also cherishing secret
                        hopes of receiving from the senate benefits and rewards which could hardly
                        fall to his lot without injuring his relations with his brother. There were
                        certain men in Rome, evil counsellors, who encouraged his ambitions.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These men made him believe that the
                        prevailing opinion in Rome with regard to Attalus and Eumenes was that the
                        one was a sure friend to the Romans, the other was regarded as a man whom
                        neither the Romans nor Perseus could trust as an ally. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> It was difficult, therefore, to decide whether the
                        requests he made on his own behalf or those through which he might seek to
                        damage his brother would be the more likely to gain the consent of the
                        senate, so bent were they as a body on granting everything to Attalus and
                        denying everything to Eumenes. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Attalus, as
                        the event showed, was one of those men who try to gain all that their hopes
                        promise them; but in his case the wise admonitions of a friend put a curb,
                        so to speak, on a temper which was becoming wanton through popularity.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There was in his suite a physician
                        called Stratus; Eumenes, who felt uneasy, had sent him specially to Rome to
                        watch his brother's conduct, and if he saw him becoming disloyal to his
                        brother, to give him sound and faithful advice. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Stratus found that he had to deal with ears already
                        preoccupied and feelings already tampered with, but he seized favourable
                        moments for conversing with him, and in these interviews he restored a
                        position which had become almost hopeless. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                        /> He represented to him that different kingdoms had grown strong through
                        different causes; their kingdom was a new one, not based upon age-long
                        power; it stood through brotherly harmony; the royal title and the crown are
                        borne by one, but all his brothers reign with him. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Who would not regard Attalus, the next in age, as a
                        king, not only because he sees him in such a powerful position now, but also
                        because the day is near when he will ascend the throne owing to the age and
                        weakness of Eumenes, who has no legitimate son? (He had not yet acknowledged
                        the one who succeeded him.) What advantage would there be in trying to gain
                        by violent means what would shortly come to him of its own accord?
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> A fresh storm had burst on the realm
                        in an invasion of the Gauls which could with difficulty be withstood even by
                        the combined and harmonious efforts of the two monarchs. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> "If, however, in addition to a foreign foe there was
                        domestic strife, resistance would be impossible, and all that would be
                        gained would be that your brother would lose the crown before his death and
                        you would destroy all hopes of your succeeding him. Even assuming that to
                        save the kingdom for your brother and to wrest it from him were both things
                        you could boast about, still the preservation of the kingdom and the proof
                        it would afford of your brotherly affection would be the more commendable
                        and praiseworthy. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> But as a matter of fact
                        the one alternative is detestable and is next door to parricide; why then
                        should there be any doubt as to which course to take? Are you going to try
                        and secure a part of the kingdom or deprive your brother of the whole?
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> If the former, then, your power being
                        divided, you would be both weakened and exposed to every possible injury and
                        outrage. If the latter, are you prepared to send your elder brother into
                        private life or into banishment, old and infirm as he is, and at last to a
                        lonely exile's death? <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> For, without
                        recalling the legendary stories of unnatural brothers, what a signal warning
                        is given in the fate of Perseus, who laid at the feet of his conqueror the
                        diadem stained with his brother's blood which he had seized in the temple at
                        Samothrace, as though the gods who witnessed the murder were now exacting
                        the penalty. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The very men who are goading
                        you on, not because they are friendly to you, but because they are enemies
                        to Eumenes, will themselves applaud your affection and constancy if you
                        maintain your loyalty to your brother to the end." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These arguments prevailed with Attalus.
                        Accordingly, when introduced to the senate he offered his congratulations on
                        the victory, and alluded to the services, such as they were, which he and
                        his brothers had rendered. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He then
                        described the serious unrest among the Gauls which had brought about a
                        revolt and begged the senate to send envoys to them with sufficient
                        influence and authority to induce them to lay down their arms. Having
                        carried out his instructions so far as they affected the welfare of the
                        kingdom, he asked that Aenus and Maronea might be assigned to him.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> So, to the disappointment of those who
                        supposed that after bringing charges against his brother he would ask for
                        the kingdom to be divided between them, he left the senate-house. Seldom at
                        any time has either king or private citizen been listened to with such
                        universal pleasure and approval; all honours and gifts were showered upon
                        him during his stay, and his departure was witnessed by large crowds.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Amongst the numerous delegations from
                        Greece the one from Rhodes excited the greatest interest. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> They appeared in white garments as befitted their
                        mission of congratulation, and indeed if they had shown themselves in
                        mourning it might have looked as though they were lamenting the fall of
                        Perseus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the consul, M. Junius,
                        consulted the senate as to whether they would grant them free quarters and
                        hospitality and an audience, the House decided that the obligations of
                        hospitality should not be discharged in their case. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The envoys meanwhile were standing in the Comitium, and
                        when the consul came out of the senate-house they told him that they had
                        come to offer their congratulations on the victory and to rebut the
                        accusations of treason, and they begged that the senate would grant them an
                        audience. The consul told them plainly that it was to friends and allies
                        that the Romans were wont to give a hospitable welcome and grant an audience
                        of the senate. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The conduct of the Rhodians
                        during the war had not been such that they deserved to be counted amongst
                        the friends and allies of Rome. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On hearing
                        this, they all prostrated themselves to the ground and implored the consul
                        and all who were present not to think it just and right that the new charges
                        which were falsely made against them should outweigh their services in the
                        past, services to which the Romans themselves could testify. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> They lost no time in putting on mourning
                        garments and visiting the residences of the principal men, whom they
                        implored not to condemn them without a hearing. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> M. Juventius Thalna, who was the praetor
                        in charge of the alien jurisdiction, was inciting the populace against the
                        Rhodians and had proposed a resolution that war should be <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> declared against Rhodes, and that one of the
                        magistrates for the year should be chosen to command the fleet, hoping that
                        he himself would be appointed. Two of the tribunes of the plebs, M. Antonius
                        and M. Pomponius, opposed this proceeding. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        The praetor himself had acted in defiance of precedent, for he was making
                        the proposal on his own initiative without consulting the senate or
                        informing the consuls of the question he was going to put, viz. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> whether it was the will and order of the people
                        of Rome that war should be declared against Rhodes. Hitherto the senate had
                        always been consulted on the question of war, and then, if the senate gave
                        their sanction, the question was submitted to the popular Assembly.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The tribunes of the plebs, too, were
                        in the wrong, because the traditional usage was that no one should veto a
                        measure until the citizens had had the opportunity of speaking for or
                        against it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Hence it had very frequently
                        happened that those who had asserted that they would not interpose their
                        veto did interpose after the opponents of the measure had made them aware of
                        its defects, whilst on the other hand those who had come prepared to veto a
                        measure were convinced by the arguments of its supporters and withdrew their
                        veto. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On this occasion the praetors and
                        the tribunes vied with each other as to who could act most precipitately;
                        the tribunes forestalled the praetor by interposing their veto <milestone
                            n="8??" unit="section"/> before the right time . . . </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> ". . . So far it is a question whether we
                        have or have not been guilty of any offence; all the penalty, the
                        humiliation we are suffering from already. In the past, when we visited Rome
                        after the Carthaginians were defeated, after Philip and Antiochus had been
                        overcome, we went from our quarters where we were the guests of the State to
                        offer our congratulations in the senate house, and from there we went up to
                        the Capitol with gifts for your gods. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Now
                        we have come away from a miserable inn where we could hardly get admittance,
                        ordered as we are to remain outside the City almost as though we were
                        enemies. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In this squalid plight we have
                        come into the Roman senate-house-we Rhodians to whom not long ago you
                        granted the provinces of Lycia and Caria, and upon whom you have bestowed
                        the greatest distinctions and rewards. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        According to what we hear, you are ordaining that the Macedonians and
                        Illyrians shall be free peoples, though before they went to war with you
                        they were in servitude-not that we envy any one's <milestone n="5??"
                            unit="section"/> good fortunes, on the contrary we recognise the
                        clemency of Rome-but the Rhodians simply remained quiet, and are you going
                        to convert friends into enemies by this proposed war? <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Surely you are the same Romans who make it your boast
                        that your wars are successful because they are just, and pride yourselves
                        not so much upon bringing them to a close as victors as upon never beginning
                        them without just cause. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The attack on
                        Messana in Sicily made the Carthaginians your enemy; his attack on Athens,
                        his attempt to enslave Greece, the assistance rendered to Hannibal in money
                        and troops made Philip your enemy. Antiochus, on the invitation of the
                        Aetolians, who were your enemies, sailed in person with his fleet from Asia
                        to Greece, seized Demetrias, Chalcis and the Pass of Thermopylae and tried
                        to dispossess you of your empire. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Your
                        grounds for the war with Perseus were the attacks on your allies, or the
                        murder of the princes and leading men in different communities and
                        nationalities. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> What pretext or
                        justification will there be for our ruin, if we are to perish? So far I do
                        not make any difference between the case of our city as a whole and that of
                        our fellow-citizens Polyaratus and Dino and the others whom we have brought
                        with us to deliver up to you. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Suppose all
                        we Rhodians were equally guilty, what charge would be brought against us
                        with regard to this war? You say we took the side of Perseus, and just as in
                        the wars against Philip and Antiochus we stood by you against those
                        monarchs, so now we stood by the king against you. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Ask the commanders of your fleets in Asia, C. Livius,
                        L. Aemilius Regillus, how we were wont to help our allies and with what
                        energy we prosecuted the war. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Your ships
                        never fought without us to help you; we fought single-handed at Samos and a
                        second time off Pamphylia against Hannibal, who was in command. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> And this victory was all the more glorious for
                        us because after losing a large proportion of our ships and the flower of
                        our youth in the defeat at Samos, we were not daunted even by that disaster,
                        and we met the king's fleet on its way from Syria. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> I am not recounting these incidents in a spirit of
                        boasting-our present circumstances forbid that-but to remind you how the
                        Rhodians have been accustomed to help their allies. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "After the final defeat of Philip and of
                        Antiochus we received the most splendid rewards from you. If the good
                        fortune which, through the kindness of heaven and your own courage, is now
                        yours had fallen to the lot of Perseus and we had gone to Macedonia to meet
                        the victorious king and ask him for rewards, what could we possibly say for
                        ourselves? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> That he had received assistance
                        from us in money or corn? Or in naval and military contingents? Or that we
                        had held any fortified position for him? Or that we had fought any battles
                        for him either under his generals or on our own account? <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> If he were to ask where our soldiers were supplying his
                        garrison or our ships joining his fleet, we should, perhaps, make the same
                        defence before the victor that we are now making before you. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> This is what we have gained by sending envoys to
                        both parties to urge peace-we have won the gratitude of neither, and from
                        one side we have incurred suspicion and danger. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> And yet Perseus truly might bring a charge against us
                        which you, senators, cannot bring. At the outset of the war we sent a
                        deputation to promise assistance with whatever was needful for the war, and
                        to assure you that everything was in readiness, our naval forces, our
                        munitions of war, our fighting men, just as in the former wars. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> It was owing to you that we did not supply them;
                        whatever the reason was, you refused our assistance. So then not only did we
                        show no hostility to you, but we were not lacking in our duty as faithful
                        allies, though you prohibited us from discharging it. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> "Some one may say, 'What then? Has nothing
                        been done or said in your City which you disapproved of and which was such
                        as to give just offence to the people of Rome?' I am not here now to defend
                        what has been done-I am not so mad-but I shall draw a distinction between
                        the cause of the State as a whole and the guilty conduct of individual
                        citizens. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There is no State which does not
                        at some time possess bad citizens and at all times an ignorant populace.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> I have heard that even amongst you
                        there have been men who made their way by flattering the mob, and that there
                        have occasionally been secessions of the plebs when the government was no
                        longer in your hands. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If these things
                        could happen in so well-ordered a State as this, can any one feel surprised
                        that there have been amongst us a few men who in their desire to win the
                        friendship of the king have led our plebs astray by their evil counsels? All
                        the same, they did not effect anything more than make us slacken in our
                        duty. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> I will not pass over what is the
                        most serious charge brought against us with regard to this war. We sent
                        embassies to you and to Perseus simultaneously to urge peace. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> This unfortunate policy has been, as we have
                        heard, held up as abject folly by a furious orator, who it is admitted spoke
                        in such a tone that he might have been C. Popilius, your envoy, whom you
                        commissioned to dissuade Antiochus and Ptolemy from war. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Still, whether we are to call it arrogance or folly,
                        our policy towards you was the same as towards Perseus. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> "States, like individuals, have their
                        distinctive characters, some are hot-tempered, others bold and enterprising;
                        some are of a timid disposition, others more prone to sensual indulgence.
                        The people of Athens are generally reported to be quick and impulsive and
                        venture upon enterprises beyond their strength: <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> the Lacedaemonians are said to be slow in action and
                        only with difficulty are they brought to engage in undertakings in which
                        they feel perfectly safe. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> I quite admit
                        that Asia as a whole produces somewhat empty heads and that the language of
                        my countrymen is somewhat inflated because we fancy ourselves superior to
                        our neighbours. This in itself is due more to the honours which you have
                        judged us worthy to receive than to any strength which we ourselves
                        possessed. Surely that embassy was sufficiently chastised when it was
                        dismissed without any reply. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> If the
                        humiliation then inflicted was not enough, this embassy, at all events, with
                        its piteous and suppliant appeal will be an adequate atonement for an even
                        more peremptory set of negotiators than that one was. Arrogance, especially
                        in language, is bitterly resented by hot-tempered people and laughed at by
                        sensible people, particularly when shown by inferiors towards a superior,
                        but no one has ever regarded it as a capital offence. <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> Possibly some one imagined that the Rhodians felt a
                        contempt for the Romans. Some men even abuse the gods in presumptuous
                        language, but we do not hear of any <milestone n="19??" unit="section"/> one
                        being struck by lightning for it. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "If no hostile act can be imputed to us,
                        if the pompous language of our envoy, offensive as it was to listen to, did
                        not merit the destruction of our city, what is there left from which we have
                        to clear ourselves? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> I hear, senators, that
                        you are discussing the amount of the fine which is to be imposed upon us for
                        our unspoken wishes. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It is alleged that
                        our sympathies were with the king and that we should have preferred to see
                        him victorious, so, some of you think we ought to be punished by war, others
                        hold that while that was our wish we ought not on that account to be
                        punished. In no State has it been laid down either by traditional usage or
                        by positive enactment that whoever wishes the destruction of an enemy, but
                        does nothing to bring it about, shall still suffer capital punishment.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To those of you who are for freeing us
                        from the penalty though not from the charge we are grateful; we assert this
                        principle for ourselves-if, as is alleged, this was the universal wish, we
                        do not distinguish between will and deed, we are all involved. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> If some of our leaders were on your side and
                        others on the side of the king, I do not ask that the supporters of the king
                        should enjoy immunity on account of us who were on your side; what I do ask
                        is that we should not perish on account of them. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> You are not more angry with them than our State itself
                        is, and, knowing this, most of them have either fled or taken their own
                        lives; others whom we have found guilty will be in your hands, senators.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Though the conduct of the rest of us
                        during the war has merited no gratitude, it certainly has not merited
                        punishment. Let the accumulation of our former services outweigh this
                        failure in our duty. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> During these late
                        years you have been engaged in war with three kings; let not the fact that
                        we gave no assistance in one war count more against us than the fact that we
                        fought for you in two wars counts for us. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Let Philip, Antiochus and Perseus stand for three separate verdicts; two
                        acquit us, one is so doubtful as to be adverse. If they were our judges we
                        should be pronounced guilty; you, senators, are now acting as judges as to
                        whether Rhodes is to remain in the world or be utterly blotted out.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The question before you is not one of
                        war; you can commence one, but you cannot continue it, since not a single
                        Rhodian is going to bear arms against you. If you persist in nursing your
                        wrath against us we shall ask for time to carry the tidings of this fatal
                        embassy home. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> All of us every free
                        person, every man and woman in Rhodes, will go on board our ships with all
                        the money we possess, and bidding farewell to our national and our household
                        gods, we shall come to Rome. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> All the gold
                        and silver belonging to the State, all that individual citizens possess,
                        will be placed in a heap on the Comitium, on the threshold of your
                        senate-house, and we shall deliver up ourselves, our wives and children to
                        you, prepared to suffer whatever may be in store for us. Far removed from
                        our eyes, let our city be plundered and burnt. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> The Romans have it in their power to judge the Rhodians
                        to be public enemies, we too can pass some judgment on ourselves; <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> we shall never judge ourselves to be your
                        enemies, nor will we commit a single hostile act, even if we have to suffer
                        everything that you can inflict upon us." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such was the speech. At its close they all
                        again prostrated themselves, waving their suppliant olive branches to and
                        fro. At last they rose and left the senate-house. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Then the senators were asked to state their view. The
                        bitterest opponents of the Rhodians were those who as consuls or praetors or
                        staff officers had taken part in the war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        The one who did most to help them was M. Porcius Cato, who though naturally
                        stern and inflexible acted on this occasion the part of a lenient and
                        conciliatory senator. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> I will not insert a
                        specimen of his fluency and eloquence by transcribing his speech, it is
                        extant in the Fifth Book of his Origines. The reply made to the Rhodians was
                        to the effect that they would neither be declared enemies nor allowed to
                        remain as allies. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The leaders of the
                        deputation were Philocrates and Astymedes. Some of the delegates decided to
                        accompany Philocrates back to Rhodes with the report of the proceedings,
                        others elected to remain in Rome with Astymedes so that they could find out
                        what was going on and inform their countrymen. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> For the time being they were only required to withdraw
                        their governors from Lycia and Caria. This would in itself have created a
                        painful impression, but as they were relieved from the apprehension of a
                        worse evil, that of war, the announcement was received with joy. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> They at once decreed a crown of 20,000 gold
                        pieces in value and sent it to Theaetetus, the commandant of the fleet, for
                        him to carry it to Rome. They wished him to press for an alliance with Rome,
                        but in such a way that the terms would not be submitted to the people, nor
                        reduced to writing, because in case he was unsuccessful the failure would be
                        all the more humiliating. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was the sole
                        prerogative of the commandant of the fleet to act in these matters without
                        any formal decree being made. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For all
                        those years they had maintained friendly relations with Rome without binding
                        themselves by an express treaty of alliance, their only reason being that
                        they did not wish to preclude the kings from all hopes of their assistance
                        should it ever be needed, nor themselves from the advantage to be derived
                        from the bounty and good fortune of those monarchs. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Under present circumstances it seemed especially
                        desirable that an alliance should be formed, not to give them additional
                        security against other nations-for they feared none but the Romans-but to
                        make them less suspected by the Romans themselves. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Just at this time the Caunians revolted from them and
                        the Mylasensians seized the towns of the Euromensians. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> The Rhodian government was not so broken in spirit as
                        not to become aware that if Lycia and Caria had been taken from them by Rome
                        the other subject countries would either win their freedom by revolt or be
                        seized by their neighbours, and they themselves would be shut up in a small
                        and unfertile island which was quite incapable of supporting the population
                        of so large a city. A body of troops was accordingly despatched to the
                        disaffected districts and reduced the Caunians to submission, though they
                        had summoned help from the Cibyratae. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        They also defeated in an action near Orthosia the Mylasensians and
                        Alabandians who had joined forces to wrest from them the province of
                        Euromos. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these various events were taking
                        place in Caria, Macedonia and Rome, L. Anicius was campaigning in Illyria.
                        After receiving the submission of King Gentius, as stated above, he placed a
                        garrison in Scodra, the capital, with Gabinius in command, and others
                            <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> in Rhizon and Olcinium, cities well
                        adapted for the purpose, under C. Licinius. He then advanced with the rest
                        of his army into Epirus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The first city to
                        surrender to him here was Phanota, where the whole population streamed out
                        to meet him with fillets of supplication round their brows. He garrisoned
                        the place and marched into Molossia. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> All
                        the towns with four exceptions made their surrender. Those who stood out
                        were Passaron, Tecmon, Phylace and Horreum. The first to be attacked was
                        Passaron. Antinous and Theodotus were the leaders in this city. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> They had distinguished themselves by their
                        support of Perseus and their hatred of the Romans; it was through them that
                        the whole nation had revolted from Rome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Knowing that the guilt rested on them personally and hopeless of obtaining
                        pardon, they shut the gates that they might be buried in the general ruin of
                        their country, and appealed to the inhabitants to prefer death to servitude.
                        No one ventured to open his lips against such powerful men. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> At last a certain Theodotus, a young man of noble
                        birth, whose dread of the Romans proved stronger than his fear of his
                        chiefs, exclaimed, "What madness possesses you that you should make the
                        whole body of citizens accessories to the guilt of two men? <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> I have often heard tell of men who have met death on
                        behalf of their country; these are the first who have been found to think it
                        right that their country should perish for their sake. Why do we not open
                        our gates and accept the sovereignty which the whole world has accepted?"
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As he said this the whole multitude
                        followed him, Antinous and Theodotus rushed against the nearest outpost of
                        the enemy and died of the wounds they had invited, the city surrendered to
                        the Romans. At Tecmon the chief magistrate was equally defiant and closed
                        the gates. He was put to death and the place surrendered. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Neither Phylace nor Horreum stood a siege. </p>
                    <p> When Epirus was finally pacified and the army distributed amongst the cities
                        suitable for their winter quarters Anicius returned to Scodra, where the
                        five commissioners had arrived from Rome. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        Here he summoned the chief magistrates from all parts of the province to a
                        conference. Ascending the tribunal, he made the following announcement as
                        agreed upon with the commissioners: "It is the order of the senate and
                        people of Rome that the Illyrians shall be a free nation. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> I shall withdraw my garrisons from all your towns,
                        citadels and forts. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Issenses, the
                        Taulantii, the Pirustae of Dassaretia, the cities of Rhizon and Olcinium,
                        shall be not only free politically, but exempt from all tribute, because
                        they revolted to the Romans whilst Gentius was still in power. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> Similar exemption is also granted to the
                        Daorsei, because they deserted Caravantius and went over fully armed to the
                        Romans. The people of Scodra, Dassara, and Selepeta will have half the
                        tribute imposed upon them that they paid to the king." He then announced a
                        threefold division of Illyria. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> One has
                        been mentioned already; the second comprised the whole country up to Lake
                        Libeatus; the third included the Agravonites, the Rhizonites, the Olciniates
                        and the settlers on their borders. After laying down this constitution for
                        Illyria he returned to Passaron in Epirus for the winter. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these proceedings in Illyria,
                        Paulus, prior to the arrival of the ten commissioners, sent his son Q.
                        Maximus, who had now returned from Rome, to sack the cities of Aeginium and
                        Agassae, the latter because after surrendering to the consul Marcius and
                        voluntarily asking for an alliance it had again revolted to Perseus.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The offence of the people of Aeginium
                        was of a novel character. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They did not
                        attach any credence to the report of the Roman victory, and killed some of
                        the soldiers who had entered the town. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> L.
                        Postumius was also sent to sack the city of Aeniae because the inhabitants
                        had shown greater obstinacy than the surrounding cities. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Autumn was approaching and the consul decided to
                        utilise this season for making a tour through Greece and visiting objects to
                        which the fame that reaches our ears lends a grandeur which the eye fails to
                        discern. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He placed C. Sulpicius Galbus in
                        charge of the camp and set out with a small escort, his son Scipio and
                        Athenaeus, Eumenes' brother, riding on either side of him. Passing through
                        Thessaly he made his way to Delphi, the world-famed oracle. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Here he offered sacrifices to Apollo and some
                        unfinished columns in the vestibule on which it had been intended to place
                        statues of Perseus he set apart for statues of himself in commemoration of
                        his victory. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He also visited the temple of
                        Jupiter Trophonius at Lebadia and saw the mouth of the cavern into which
                        those who consult the oracle descended. There is a temple here dedicated to
                        Jupiter and Hercynna, and he offered sacrifices to these deities. He then
                        went on to Chalcis to see the Euripus and the bridge which connects the
                        large island of Euboea with the mainland. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        From there he crossed to Aulis, a distance of three miles, and viewed the
                        harbour, famous as the anchorage of Agamemnon's thousand ships, and also the
                        temple of Diana, at whose altar the renowned "king of kings" sacrificed his
                        daughter that his fleet might have a favourable voyage to Troy. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> He then went on to Oropus, where an ancient bard
                        is worshipped as a god and his venerable temple is delightfully situated
                        amidst fountains and brooks. From there he proceeded to Athens. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> This city is full of the traditions of its
                        ancient glory, but it nevertheless possesses many things worth seeing-the
                        citadel, the harbour, the walls connecting the city with the Piraeus and the
                        dockyards; memorials of great commanders, statues of gods and men,
                        splendidly wrought in every kind of material and every form of art. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After sacrificing to Minerva, the tutelary
                        deity in the Acropolis, he left for Corinth, which he reached on the
                        following day. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At that time, before its
                        destruction, it was a glorious city. The citadel and the Isthmus presented a
                        striking spectacle-the citadel inside the walls rising to a great height,
                        with streams flowing everywhere, and the Isthmus separating by a narrow belt
                        of land two seas, one to the east and the other to the west. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Sicyon and Argos were the next places visited,
                        both of them famous cities; and next to them Epidaurus, not so wealthy as
                        those, but celebrated for the splendid temple of Aesculapius, five miles
                        distant from the city, filled at the present day with the relics and
                        vestiges of the offerings which then enriched it, offerings made to the god
                        by the sick as a grateful reward for their recovery. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> From there he went on to Lacedaemon, a city memorable,
                        not for the magnificence of its buildings, but for its discipline and its
                        institutions. Passing through Megalopolis he went up to Olympia. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Here among the different objects which attracted
                        his attention, he was deeply impressed as he gazed on Jupiter, standing as
                        it were before him, and he gave orders for a sacrifice to be prepared on an
                        ampler scale than usual, just as if he were going to sacrifice in the
                        Capitol. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In this progress through Greece he was
                        careful to avoid doing anything that might alarm those who were friends of
                        Rome, and therefore he made no enquiry into the sentiments entertained by
                        communities as a whole or by individual citizens during the war with
                        Perseus. On his return to Demetrias he was met by a crowd of Aetolians
                        dressed in mourning. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On his asking with
                        some surprise what the matter was, they told him that five hundred and fifty
                        of their principal citizens had been put to death by Lyciscus and Tisippus,
                        after they had placed round the senate-house a cordon of Roman soldiers sent
                        by A. Baebius, the commandant of the garrison. Others they had sent into
                        exile, and they were keeping the property of those who had been killed as
                        well as of those who had been banished. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He
                        sent orders for those who were accused to await him at Amphipolis. He met
                        Cnaeus Octavius at Demetrias, and while he was there a report reached him
                        that the ten commissioners had landed in Greece, and laying aside all other
                        business he proceeded to Apollonia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Through the slackness of his guard Perseus had been able to get away from
                        Amphipolis and met Aemilius at Apollonia-it is only a day's journey.
                        Aemilius is said to have spoken to him in a kindly tone, but when he arrived
                        in the camp at Amphipolis he severely censured C. Sulpicius, in the first
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> place because he had allowed
                        Perseus to wander so far away in the province and secondly because he had
                        shown such indulgence to his soldiers that he allowed them to remove the
                        tiles from the city walls in order to roof their winter huts. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> He ordered the tiles to be taken back and the
                        uncovered places to be restored to their former condition. Perseus and his
                        elder son Philip were handed over to A. Postumius to be kept under guard;
                        Aemilius treated the daughter and the younger son, who had been brought from
                        Samothrace, with every mark of respect and kindness. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Aemilius gave notice for the councils of
                        ten from all the cities to assemble at Amphipolis and to bring with them all
                        archives and documents wherever they were deposited, and all the money due
                        to the royal treasury. When the day arrived he advanced to the tribunal,
                        where he took his seat with the ten commissioners, surrounded by a vast
                        concourse of Macedonians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Though they were
                        accustomed to the display of royal power, this novel assertion of authority
                        filled them with fear; the tribunal, the clearing of the approach to it
                        through the mass of people, the herald, the apparitor, all these were
                        strange to their eyes and ears and might even have appalled allies of Rome,
                        to say nothing of a vanquished enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        After the herald had called for silence Paulus, speaking in Latin, explained
                        the arrangements decided upon by the senate and by himself in concert with
                        the ten commissioners; Cnaeus Octavius, who was also present, translated the
                        address into Greek. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> First of all it was
                        laid down that the Macedonians were to be a free people, possessing their
                        cities and fields as before, enjoying their own laws and customs and
                        electing their annual magistrates. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They
                        were to pay to Rome half the tribute which they had been paying to the king.
                        Secondly, Macedonia was to be broken up into four separate cantons.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The first would embrace the district
                        between the Strymon and the Nessus, and in addition, beyond the Nessus to
                        the east, the forts, towns and villages which Perseus had held, with the
                        exception of Aenus, Maronea and Abdera, and beyond the Strymon to the west
                        the whole of Bisaltica together with Heraclea, which district the natives
                        call Sintice. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The second canton would be
                        bounded on the east by the Strymon, exclusive of Sintice, Heraclea and
                        Bisaltica; and on the west by the Axius, including the Paeonians, who dwelt
                        to the east of the Axius. The third division would be the district enclosed
                        between the Axius on the east and the Peneus on the west; the Bora range
                        shuts it in on the north. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This canton was
                        increased by the addition of the part of Paeonia which extends westwards
                        beyond the Axius; Edessa and Beroea were assigned to this division. The
                        fourth canton lay on the other side of the Bora range, bordering Illyria on
                        the one side and Epirus on the other. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Aemilius then designated the capital
                        cities where the councils were to be held in the different cantons;
                        Amphipolis was fixed for the first, Thessalonica for the second, Pella for
                        the third, and Pelagonia for the fourth. There the councils for each canton
                        were to be summoned, the tribute deposited, and the annual magistrates
                        elected. His next announcement was that all intermarriage between the
                        inhabitants of the different cantons was forbidden, as also the possession
                        of land or houses in more than one canton. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                        /> The gold and silver mines were not allowed to be worked, but permission
                        was given in the case of the iron and copper mines. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Those working the mines would have to pay one half of
                        the royalty which they had paid to the king. The use of imported salt was
                        also forbidden. The Dardanians were laying claim to Paeonia on the ground
                        that it once belonged to them, and they had a common frontier; <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> the consul told them in reply that he was
                        granting political liberty to all who had been under the rule of Perseus.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> As he had refused them Paeonia he
                        granted them the right to purchase salt and ordered the third canton to
                        carry its salt to Stobi, fixing, at the same time, the price at which it was
                        to be sold. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He forbade the Macedonians
                        either to cut timber for ship-building themselves or to allow others to do
                        so. He gave permission to those cantons whose frontiers were contiguous to
                        those of the barbarians to maintain armed forces on their borders. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This pronouncement made on the first day
                        of the conference called forth mixed feelings in the audience. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The unhoped-for boon of political liberty and the
                        lightening of the annual tribute were a great relief to them, but the
                        prohibition of mutual intercourse between the different cantons seemed to
                        them like the rending asunder of their country, like an animal deprived of
                        its limbs, where each limb is necessary to all the rest so ignorant were
                        they of the size of Macedonia, how easily it lent itself to division and how
                        self-contained each part was in itself. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        The first section includes the Bisaltae, a nation of warriors living on the
                        other side of the Nessus and around the Strymon and contains many special
                        kinds of fruit and minerals and the city of Amphipolis, which is so
                        conveniently situated, commanding as it does all approaches from the east.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then again, the second division
                        comprises the populous cities of Thessalonica and Cassandrea and also the
                        rich corn-growing district of Pallene. Facilities for sea-borne traffic are
                        afforded by numerous harbours: some at Torone under Mount Athos, and at
                        Aenea and Acanthus, others facing Thessaly and Euboea, and others again
                        easily accessible from the Hellespont. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                        third canton includes the famous cities of Edessa, Beroea and Pella, the
                        warlike tribe of the Vettii and also a large population of Gauls and
                        Illyrians who are devoted to husbandry. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The fourth canton is peopled by the Eordaei the Lyncestae and the Pelagones,
                        and there are also the three cities of Atintania, Tymphaei, and Elimiotis.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The whole of this strip of country is
                        cold and unkindly and difficult of cultivation, and the character of the
                        peasants corresponds to that of their country. Their barbarian neighbours
                        make them still more ferocious by sometimes familiarising them with war, and
                        in times of peace introducing their own rites and customs. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> In this division of Macedonia, therefore, each separate
                        portion had its own distinctive advantages </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the constitution of Macedonia had
                        been thus announced, and the consul had declared his intention of providing
                        a code of laws, the Aetolians were summoned to appear. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The enquiry was directed more to find out who had been
                        in favour of the Romans and who in favour of the king than to discover which
                        party had inflicted and which had suffered wrongs. The murderers were
                        acquitted, the exiles and the slain were alike considered to have deserved
                        their fate; the only one found guilty was A. Baebius because he had allowed
                        his soldiers to be the instruments of the massacre. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> This result of the case of the Aetolians had the effect
                        of inflating the adherents of the Roman party in all the communities and
                        peoples of Greece to an insupportable pitch of insolence, and whenever there
                        was any suspicion of having favoured the king their opponents were trampled
                        in the dust. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The leaders in the various
                        cities fell into three classes; two of these consisted of men who, whilst
                        insinuating themselves into the confidence of the Romans on the one hand or
                        the king <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> on the other, aggrandised
                        themselves at the expense of their fellow-citizens, the third class sought
                        to defend their liberties and their laws by opposing both the others. The
                        greater the affection which their compatriots felt for them at home, the
                        less were they appreciated abroad. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Elated
                        by the success of the Romans, the supporters of that party were in sole
                        possession of the magistracies and the sole representatives of their States.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Numbers of these men came from the
                        Peloponnesus, from Boeotia, and the other national councils in Greece to be
                        present at the congress, and they filled the ears of the commissioners with
                        their charges. They averred that the supporters of Perseus included not only
                        those who in a spirit of idle vanity openly boasted that they were his
                        friends and intimates, but a <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> far more
                        numerous body who had secretly espoused his cause, and under the pretext of
                        defending their liberties had everywhere induced the councils to act in
                        direct hostility to Rome. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The loyalty of
                        the different States could only be maintained by crushing these parties and
                        strengthening the authority of those whose sole aim was to support the power
                        of Rome. A list of names was furnished by these men, and letters from the
                        commander were despatched to Acarnania, Aetolia, Epirus and Boeotia,
                        ordering those named to follow him to Rome to make their defence. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Two of the commissioners, C. Claudius and Cnaeus
                        Domitius, went in person to Achaia to publish this order. There were two
                        reasons for this. One was their belief that the self-confidence and high
                        spirit of the Achaeans would prevent their obeying the order, and possibly
                        Callicrates and the other informers might even be in danger of their lives.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The other was that while letters from
                        the leaders in other States had been discovered in the royal archives, none
                        had been found from the Achaeans, and the charges against them lacked proof.
                        After the Aetolians had withdrawn, the Acarnanian deputation was called in.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> In their case no change was made
                        beyond the removal of Leucas as a member of their league. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Then the commissioners extended the scope of this
                        enquiry as far as Asia. Labeo was sent to destroy the city of Antissa in the
                        island of Lesbos, and transfer the inhabitants to Methymna, the reason for
                        this step being that they had admitted the king's naval commander, Antenor,
                        into their harbour and helped him with supplies while he was cruising off
                        Lesbos. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Two of their leaders were
                        beheaded: <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Andronicus, the son of
                        Andronicus, an Aetolian, because he had followed his father and borne arms
                        against Rome, and Neo, a Theban, who had been the prime agent in their
                        forming an alliance with Perseus </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The congress of the Macedonians which had
                        been interrupted by these proceedings was again convened. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> First of all the status of Macedonia was defined.
                        Senators, who were known as "synedri," were to be elected to form a council
                        for the administration of government. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then
                        a list was read out of the names of those Macedonian leaders who it was
                        decided were to go in advance to Italy with all their children over fifteen
                        years of age. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At first glance this seemed
                        a cruel measure, but it soon became apparent to the Macedonians that it was
                        done to protect their liberties. The names on the list were those of the
                        friends and court nobles of the king, the generals of his armies, the
                        commanders of his ships and garrisons accustomed to servile submission
                        towards him and dictatorial insolence towards others. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Some were exceedingly wealthy others whose fortunes did
                        not equal theirs lived quite as extravagantly; their table and dress were on
                        a regal scale they had no idea of citizenship, and were incapable of
                        submission to law or to a liberty equal for all. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Every one, therefore, who had been employed in the
                        king's service, even those who had been sent as envoys, were ordered to
                        leave Macedonia and proceed to Italy, and whoever refused obedience was
                        threatened with death. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The laws which
                        Aemilius gave to the Macedonians had been so carefully and considerately
                        drawn up that he might be thought to be giving them not to vanquished
                        enemies but to allies who had rendered good service, and not even after a
                        long practical experience-the only safe guide in legislative reform-have
                        they been found to need amendment. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After
                        attending to these more serious matters he celebrated the Games, for which
                        preparations had been going on for a long time, with great splendour. Notice
                        of them had been sent to the cities of Asia and to the kings, and during his
                        tour in Greece Aemilius had informed the leading men about them. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> There was a gathering of artistes proficient in
                        every kind of scenic display, a vast assemblage of athletes from all parts
                        of the world, and horses that had won many races. There were also civic
                        deputations with their animals for sacrifice; everything, in fact, which
                        usually formed a part of these exhibitions in honour both of gods and men.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The performances were so good that
                        not only the magnificence of the spectacle but the skill shown in its
                        display were universally admired; the Romans were not in those days adepts
                        at these exhibitions. The same care was taken over the rich banquets which
                        were prepared for the civic deputations. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        A remark of the consul's was often quoted, that, the man who knew how to win
                        a war had also to furnish entertainment and prepare Games for the conquered.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When all the performances were ended and
                        the bronze targes had been put on board the ships, the rest of the spoils
                        were collected into enormous heaps. Then the commander offered up prayers to
                        Mars and Minerva and Lua Mater and the other deities to whom the spoils
                        taken from the enemy must be solemnly dedicated. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He then applied a torch to the heap and the military
                        tribunes standing round each cast a brand on the pile. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> It is a noteworthy fact that in this great meeting of
                        Europe and Asia, where a multitude had been drawn together from every part
                        of the world, some to offer congratulations, some to see the spectacle,
                        where <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> such great naval and military
                        forces were assembled, there was nevertheless such abundance of everything
                        and provisions were so cheap that the general out of this abundance made
                        gifts to individuals, to cities, and even to whole nations, sufficient not
                        only for their use at the time, but enough for them to take home with them.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The spectators were not more
                        interested in the scenic representations and the athletic contests and
                        chariot races than they were in the display of the spoils from Macedonia.
                        These were all laid out to view-statues, pictures, woven fabrics, articles
                        in gold, silver, bronze and ivory wrought with consummate care, all of which
                        had been found in the palace, where they had not been intended, like
                            <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> those which filled the palace at
                        Alexandria, for a moment's ornament but for constant and lasting use. They
                        were all placed on board the fleet under the charge of Cnaeus Octavius to be
                        transported to Rome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After taking a
                        friendly leave of the various deputations Paulus crossed the Strymon and
                        fixed his camp a mile distant from Amphipolis. A five days' further march
                        brought him to Pella. Marching past the city he arrived at a place called
                        Spilaeum, where he stayed two days. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> During
                        his stay he sent P. Nasica and his son Q. Maximus to ravage that part of
                        Illyria from which assistance had been sent to Perseus and afterwards to
                        meet him at Oricum. He himself took the road to Epirus and after a fifteen
                        days' march reached Passaron. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Anicius' camp was not far away, and the
                        consul sent a letter telling him not to be disturbed at what was going on,
                        for the senate had made a grant to his army of the plunder from those cities
                        in Epirus which had gone over to Perseus. Centurions were sent to each of
                        the cities to say that they had come to bring away the garrisons in order
                        that the Epirots should be free as the Macedonians were free. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The town councillors in each community were sent
                        for and warned to have the gold and silver brought out into some public
                        place, and cohorts were ordered to visit all the cities. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Those who were to go to the more distant places started
                        before those who were to go to the nearer ones, and they all reached their
                        destination on the same day. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The military
                        tribunes had received instructions as to what they were to do. All the
                        silver and gold had been collected together in the morning, and at ten
                        o'clock the signal was given to the soldiers to sack the cities. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> So great was the amount of booty secured that 400
                        denarii were distributed to each cavalryman and 200 to each foot soldier,
                        and 150,000 human beings were carried off. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Then the walls of the plundered cities, some seventy in number, were
                        destroyed, the booty sold and the proceeds furnished the above-mentioned sum
                        for the troops. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Paulus went down to the
                        seaport of Oricum, but his soldiers were far from satisfied; they resented
                        being excluded from all share in the plunder of the palace, as though they
                        had not taken any part in the Macedonian war. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> At Oricum he found the troops which had been sent off
                        with Scipio Nasica and Q. Maximus, and after seeing his army on board sailed
                        back to Italy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A few days later Anicius,
                        who had been meeting the representatives of the rest of the Epirots, ordered
                        those of their leaders whose case he had reserved for the senate to follow
                        him to Italy. He then waited for the ships which had been used to transport
                        the army from Macedonia, and on their arrival he too returned to Italy. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> During these occurrences in Macedonia and
                        Epirus the mission which had been sent in company with Attalus to put a stop
                        to the war between the Gauls and Eumenes landed in Asia. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> A truce had been arranged for the winter; the Gauls had
                        gone home and the king had retired into winter quarters at Pergamum, where
                        he had been seriously ill. The beginning of spring had drawn the Gauls from
                        their homes and they had gone as far as Synnada, while Eumenes had assembled
                        at Sardis an army drawn from every quarter of his kingdom. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> When the Romans who were there had ascertained that the
                        Gauls were at Synnada they decided to proceed thither and interview
                        Solovetius, the Gaulish leader; Attalus accompanied them, but they decided
                        that he should not enter the Gaulish camp lest there should be an angry
                        debate. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> P. Licinius had a conversation
                        with their leader, and brought back word that all attempts to persuade him
                        only made him more defiant; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> he expressed
                        his astonishment that whilst the representations of the Roman commissioners
                        succeeded in allaying the strife between such powerful monarchs as Antiochus
                        and Ptolemy, they had no weight whatever with the Gauls. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The captive monarchs Perseus and Gentius,
                        with their children, were the first to be brought to Rome as prisoners; a
                        host of prisoners followed them. These were succeeded by the Macedonians and
                        the leading men of Greece who had received orders to go to Rome. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> In the case of these latter the summons embraced
                        not only those at home, but also any who were reported to be with Antiochus
                        or Ptolemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A few days later Paulus
                        himself sailed up the Tiber to the City in the king's ship, a vessel of
                        enormous size propelled by sixteen banks of oars and adorned with the spoils
                        of Macedonia in the shape of glittering armour and embroidered fabrics which
                        belonged to the king. The river banks were crowded with multitudes who had
                        streamed out to greet his arrival. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Anicius
                        and Octavius, with their fleet, arrived shortly afterwards. A triumph for
                        all three was decreed by the senate, and the praetor Q. Cassius was
                        instructed to arrange with the tribunes of the plebs that they should
                        propose a resolution to the Assembly that on the day when they entered the
                        City in triumph they should retain their full military powers. Men of
                        mediocre ability escape envy, it generally aims its shafts at the highest.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> No hesitation was felt about allowing
                        Anicius and Octavius a triumph; Paulus, with whom they would have blushed to
                        compare themselves, was the mark for calumny. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> He had maintained the ancient discipline amongst his
                        men; he had given the soldiers much less booty than they had hoped
                        considering Perseus' immense wealth; had he satisfied their demands they
                        would have left nothing for the treasury. The whole of the army in Macedonia
                        were incensed against their commander, and intended to give very little
                        support to the resolution. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Servius
                        Sulpicius Galba, who had served in Macedonia as military tribune in
                            <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> the second legion and who had a
                        private grievance against his commander, had gone about personally amongst
                        the men and through the soldiers of his own legion had solicited and spurred
                        on the rest to come in force and vote against the resolution, they would
                        then have their revenge upon their despotic and niggardly general.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> "The City plebs would follow the lead
                        of the soldiers. He forsooth had not the power to give the soldiers money!
                        The soldiers, however, had the power to confer honour. He must not hope to
                        reap the fruit of a gratitude which he had not earned." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In this angry mood they assembled in the
                        Capitol. When Tiberius Sempronius put the resolution and the citizens were
                        at liberty to speak, not a single person came forward to support it, as
                        though it was taken for granted that it would be carried. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Suddenly Servius Galba came forward and said that it
                        was now four o'clock in the afternoon and there was not sufficient time for
                        him to give his reasons why they should refuse the order for P. Aemilius to
                        enjoy a triumph; he requested the tribunes of the plebs to adjourn the
                        Assembly to the following day and commence the discussion in the morning, as
                        he would need an entire day to state his case. The tribunes told him to say
                        what he wanted to say there and then. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> His
                        speech lasted till nightfall. He reminded his audience how all military
                        tasks had been ruthlessly imposed, how there had been more labour, more
                        danger incurred than circumstances required; but on the other hand, when it
                        came to rewards and distinctions everything was cut down; <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> if such generals were to have their way warfare would
                        become more rough and repulsive to those engaged in it, and even when
                        victory came it would bring neither profit nor honour. The Macedonians were
                        better off than the Roman soldiers were. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        If they came in force the next day to vote against the resolution the men in
                        power would understand that the general has not everything in his own hands,
                        the soldiers too have something in their hands. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Excited by this language, the soldiers crowded into the
                        Capitol in such numbers that there was no room for any one else to give his
                        vote. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the tribes who were first
                        called upon were beginning to vote against the proposal, the chiefs of the
                        City hurried to the Capitol and exclaimed loudly against such an unworthy
                        proceeding. Lucius Paulus, they said, the victor in so great a war, was
                        being robbed of his triumph, the commanders were being placed at the mercy
                        of a licentious and grasping soldiery. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Political corruption had already been the cause of too many crimes; what
                        would happen if the soldiers were made the lords and masters of their
                        commanders? Each did his utmost to shower reproaches on Galba. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> The tumult was at last allayed, and M. Servilius
                        who had been consul and Master of the Horse begged the tribunes to commence
                        the proceedings afresh and give him an opportunity of addressing the people.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The tribunes retired to deliberate,
                        and out of deference to the authority of the leaders of the State, prepared
                        to go through the business from the beginning, and announced their intention
                        of calling upon the tribes who had already voted to vote again after M.
                        Servilius and any other citizens had stated their views. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then Servilius began: "How great a
                        commander L. Aemilius has shown himself may be estimated, if by nothing
                        else, at all events by this simple fact, that though he had in his camp such
                        mutinous and fickle soldiers, and a man so notorious for his impulsiveness
                        and power of rousing a multitude bent on mischief by his eloquence, yet he
                        never had a mutiny in his camp. The same stern exercise of authority, which
                        they now detest, kept them as a united body. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> Held fast by the ancient discipline, they neither uttered a seditious
                        word nor acted in a seditious way. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As to
                        Servilius Galba, if he wished to make his first essay, and give us a
                        specimen of his eloquence by accusing L. Paulus, he ought not to have stood
                        in the way of his triumph, if for no other reason at least for this, that
                        the senate had judged it just and right. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        He ought to have waited till the morrow of his triumph, when he would see
                        him as a private citizen and would be able to indict him before a
                        magistrate, or at a later time, as soon as he himself had taken up the
                        duties of a magistrate, he could impeach his enemy and prosecute him before
                        the Assembly. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In that way Lucius Paulus
                        would have been rewarded by a triumph for having done his duty in conducting
                        a war so gloriously, and would have been punished for anything he had done
                        unworthy of his former reputation and his newly-acquired glory. But see!
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He could not say anything against his
                        conduct as a citizen or his character as a man, so he tried to besmirch his
                        reputation. Yesterday afternoon he asked for a whole day in which to bring
                        his accusations against L. Paulus; he took up what was left of the day-four
                        hours-with his speech. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> What man has ever
                        been placed upon his trial, so steeped in guilt that the crimes of his life
                        could not be recounted in that number of hours? What, however, did he bring
                        up which L. Paulus, were he on his trial, would wish to deny? </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> "Let some one picture to himself for a
                        moment two assemblies, the one made up of the soldiers who served in
                        Macedonia, the other free from prejudice, with a judgment unwarped by either
                        partiality or aversion-the whole of the people of Rome sitting as judges.
                        Suppose the defendant were first brought before the assembly of civilians
                        clad in their peaceful togas. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> What would
                        you say, Servilius Galba, before the Quirites of Rome? You said yesterday:
                        'Your outpost duty was too arduous, too much of a strain; the inspection of
                        the night watches was too inconsiderate and incessant; you did heavier
                        fatigue duty than formerly, when the commander himself went round and
                        inspected. You had a march, and then went straight into battle on the same
                        day, and even after you had won the victory, you were not allowed any rest;
                        you were instantly sent in pursuit of the enemy. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> It was within his power to make you rich by
                        distributing the plunder; he is going to carry the royal wealth in his
                        triumphal procession and then put it into the treasury.' This sort of talk
                        has a certain sting in it to goad on men who think that sufficient deference
                        has not been shown to their licence and avarice. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> But it would have no influence with the people of Rome.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They might not remember the old-time
                        stories, and those which they have heard from their fathers, the defeats
                        incurred by commanders who wished to be popular, and the victories won by
                        stern and strict discipline; but they have not at all events forgotten the
                        last Punic war, the difference between M. Minucius, the Master of the Horse,
                        and Q. Fabius Maximus, the Dictator. So it is quite clear that the accuser
                        would not have had a word to say, and any defence by Paulus would have been
                        superfluous. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> "Now let us pass to the
                        other assembly. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> I think I shall call you
                        'soldiers,' and not 'Quirites,' if that title can at least call up a blush
                        and evoke in you a feeling of shame for the way you have insulted your
                        commander. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "While I fancy myself addressing the army,
                        I am in a very different state of mind from what I was in a few moments ago,
                        when my words were addressed to the citizens. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> What do you say, soldiers? Is there a single man in
                        Rome besides Perseus who would object to a triumph over the Macedonians, and
                        you do not tear him in pieces with the same arms with which you conquered
                        the Macedonians? The man who prevents you from entering the City in triumph
                        would have prevented you, had it been in his power, from winning the war.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> You are mistaken, soldiers, if you
                        think that a triumph is an honour to the general alone, and not to the
                        soldiers also, and to the whole people of Rome. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> It is not the glory of Paulus alone that is at stake
                        here-many who failed to obtain the senate's sanction have triumphed on the
                        Alban Mount; no one can snatch from Paulus the glory of bringing the
                        Macedonian war to a close any more than he could deprive C. Lutatius of his
                        glory in the first Punic war, or P. Cornelius of his glory in the second.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A triumph will not diminish or enhance
                        L. Paulus' greatness as a commander-it is the fair fame of the soldiers and
                        the people of Rome that is in question. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Take care that this action be not looked upon as an instance of jealousy and
                        ingratitude towards all our noblest citizens, copying the example of the
                        Athenians, who persecuted their foremost men because they were jealous of
                        their greatness. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Enough wrong was done by
                        your ancestors in the case of Camillus, whom they treated with injustice-it
                        was, however, before he rescued the City from the Gauls-enough, too, by
                        yourselves in the case of P. Africanus. We must blush with shame when we
                        remember that the domicile and home of the man who subjugated Africa was at
                        Liternum; that it is at Liternum we are shown his tomb. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> If the glory of L. Paulus is on a par with theirs, do
                        not let the injustice you are showing to him equal what was shown to them.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Let us begin then by effacing this
                        infamy so ugly in the eyes of other nations, so disastrous to our own
                        people; for who would wish to resemble either Africanus or Paulus in a
                        community which was ungrateful and hostile to its good citizens? <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> If there were no question of disgrace, if it
                        were only one of glory, what triumph, pray, does not bring with it a glory
                        in which every Roman has a share? <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> All
                        those triumphs over the Gauls, all those over the Spaniards; all those over
                        the Carthaginians, are they spoken of as the triumphs of the commanders
                        only, and not rather of the people of Rome as a whole? As it was not over
                        Pyrrhus or Hannibal personally but over the Epirots and the Carthaginians,
                        so it was not Manlius Curius or P. Cornelius alone who celebrated them but
                        the Romans. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Especially is this true of
                        the soldiers. With their laurel wreaths, each wearing his decorations, they
                        shout their 'Io Triumphe' and make their progress through the City, hymning
                        their commander's praises. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> If at any time
                        the soldiers have not been brought back from the province for their triumph
                        they murmur, yet even then they consider that they are taking their part in
                        it because it was by their hands that the victory was won. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> If any one were to ask you soldiers for what object you
                        were brought back to Italy and not disbanded as soon as the province was
                        brought into order; why you have come to Rome in your thousands and under
                        your standards; why you remain here and do not disperse each of you to your
                        homes; what answer would you give except that you want to appear in the
                        triumph? You, at all events, ought to wish to be seen as victors. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Triumphs have been celebrated over
                        Philip, this man's father, and over Antiochus; both were on the throne at
                        the time. Shall there be no triumph over Perseus carried off as a prisoner
                        and brought here with his children? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Now,
                        if while Anicius and Octavius were ascending the Capitol in their chariot,
                        clad in gold and purple, L. Paulus standing as an ordinary citizen in the
                        crowd were to ask them: 'Whom do you, L. Anicius and Cn. Octavius, think
                        more deserving of a triumph, me or yourselves?' I think they would for very
                        shame descend from their chariot and hand over their insignia of triumph to
                        him. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Would you rather, Quirites, see
                        Gentius led in triumph than Perseus? Would you rather see a triumph over an
                        episode of the war than over the war itself? The legions from Illyria will
                        enter the City in triumph wearing their laurel wreaths; so will the seamen
                        of the fleet. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Are the legions from
                        Macedonia going to watch the triumph of others after their own has been
                        denied? What will become of the royal booty, the spoils of such a rich
                        victory? Where will the many thousands of arms and armour stripped from the
                        bodies of the slain be stored? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Are they to
                        be sent back to Macedonia? Where are the statues of gold and marble and
                        ivory to go, the paintings, the embroidery, the mass of gold and silver
                        plate, the immense sum of money that belonged to the king? <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Will they be carried away to the treasury by night as
                        though they were the proceeds of a robbery? Yes, and the greatest spectacle
                        of all, a monarch once most famous and most wealthy, now a prisoner, where
                        is he to be shown to the victorious people? <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> Most of us remember the crowds that gathered to see the captive king
                        Syphax, who played a subordinate part in the Punic war; Perseus, a captive
                        monarch, and his sons Philip and Alexander-names borne by mighty
                        monarchs-are they to be kept out of the sight of the citizens? <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> All men's eyes are yearning to watch L. Paulus,
                        consul now for the second time, the conqueror of Greece, entering the city
                        in his chariot. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It was for this that we
                        made him consul that he might bring to an end a war which to our infinite
                        shame had been dragging on for four years. Are we going to deny a triumph to
                        the man to whom, when the ballot had allotted him the province, we destined
                        with prescient minds victory and a triumph, as we watched him leave the
                        City? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Are we going to defraud not him
                        alone but the gods as well? Your ancestors invoked them when they started
                        upon any great enterprise, and they invoked them also when they had carried
                        it through. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When a consul or a praetor
                        goes to his province with his lictors, wearing the paludamentum, he recites
                        prayers in the Capitol; when the war is over and he returns as victor in
                        triumph to the Capitol, he carries up the gifts which are their due to the
                        same deities to whom he offered the prayers. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Not the least important part of the procession is the
                        victims which precede the chariot, so that all may see that the commander is
                        coming back to offer thanks to the gods for the successes they have
                        vouchsafed to the commonwealth. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> All those
                        victims which he has destined for his triumphal procession you had better go
                        and sacrifice for yourselves, each where and when he chooses. Are those
                        solemn banquets to which the senators sit down, not in any private house nor
                        in any unconsecrated public building, but in the Capitol itself-are they, I
                        ask, intended to gratify men or to honour the gods, and are you going to
                        interfere with them at the bidding of Servius Galba? <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Will the City gates be closed against L. Paulus'
                        triumph? Is Perseus, the king of the Macedonians, with his children and all
                        the other prisoners, the spoils of Macedonia, to be left in the Circus
                        Flaminius? <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Is L. Paulus to go to his
                        house like an ordinary citizen returning home from the country, whilst you,
                        centurion and legionary, march wearing the decorations which Paulus has
                        bestowed upon you? </p>
                    <p> "Listen to the decree of the senate, rather than to the romancing of Servius
                        Galba. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Listen to this that I am saying,
                        rather than to him. He has learnt nothing but speech-making, and that only
                        to insult and calumniate. I have fought three-and-twenty times in answer to
                        challenges; from all whom I encountered I carried off the spoils. My body is
                        covered with honourable scars, every one received in front." It is said that
                        he then stripped himself and explained in what war each had been received.
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> While making this display he
                        uncovered what ought to be concealed, and a swelling in the groin evoked
                        laughter amongst those nearest to him. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> He
                        then continued: "This which you are laughing at I got from sitting on
                        horseback night and day, and I am no more ashamed of this than of my other
                        scars; it has never hindered me from serving the commonwealth faithfully,
                        either at home or on the field of battle. As an old soldier I have often
                        shown this body of mine, hacked with the sword, to the young ones.
                            <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Let Galba strip and show his smooth
                        skin with not a scar upon it. "Tribunes, call back, if you please, the
                        tribes to vote . . . ." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Valerius Antias states that all the gold
                        and silver coinage carried in the procession amounted to 120,000,000
                        sesterces, but from his own account of the number of wagons and the weight
                        carried in each, the amount must undoubtedly have exceeded this. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> It is also asserted that a second sum equal to
                        this had been either expended in the war or dispersed by the king during his
                        flight to Samothrace, and this was all the more surprising, since all that
                        money had been accumulated during the thirty years from the close of the war
                        with Philip either as profits from the mines or from other sources of
                        revenue, so that while Philip <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> was very
                        short of money, Perseus was able to commence his war with Rome with an
                        overflowing exchequer. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Last of all came
                        Paulus himself, majestic alike in the dignity of his personal presence and
                        the added dignity of years. Following his chariot were many distinguished
                        men, amongst them his two sons, Quintus Maximus and Publius Nasica. Then
                        came the cavalry, troop after troop, and the legionaries, cohort after
                        cohort. The legionaries were given 100 denarii each, the centurions twice as
                        much, and the cavalry three times that amount. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> It is believed that he would have doubled these grants
                        had they not tried to deprive him of the honour, or even if they had been
                        grateful for the actual amount which he did give them. </p>
                    <p> Perseus, however, was not the only instance during those days of triumph of
                        sudden changes in the fortunes of men. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He,
                        it is true, was led in chains through the city of his foes in front of his
                        conqueror's chariot, but Paulus, resplendent in gold and purple, was
                        suffering too. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Of the two sons whom he
                        kept with him as the heirs to his name and his house and to the sacred rites
                        of his yens-he had parted with two who had been adopted-the younger one, a
                        boy of about twelve, died five days before his triumph, and the elder, a boy
                        of fourteen, died three days after it. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        They ought to have been riding with their father, wearing the praetexta and
                        anticipating triumphs similar to his. A few days later M. Antonius, a
                        tribune of the plebs, summoned a meeting of the Assembly that Aemilius might
                        address it. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Following the practice of
                        other commanders, he gave an account of what he had done. It was a memorable
                        speech worthy of a Roman leader. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Although, Quirites, I do not suppose that
                        you are unaware of the good fortune and success which have marked my
                        administration, nor of the two thunderbolts which have within these last few
                        days fallen upon my house, seeing that you were at one time spectators of my
                        triumph, and at another <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> were watching
                        the obsequies of my children, still I ask you to allow me to make a
                        comparison in a befitting spirit between the prosperity of the republic and
                        my own private fortunes. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> "On my departure
                        from Italy I ordered the fleet to leave Brundisium at sunrise. In nine days
                        I brought up at Corcyra with all my ships. Five days later I offered
                        sacrifice to Apollo at Delphi on behalf of myself and of your fleets and
                        armies. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Four days brought me from Delphi
                        to the camp, where after taking over the army I made changes in certain
                        matters that were seriously interfering with the chances of victory. As the
                        enemy camp was unassailable, and the king could not be forced into an
                        engagement, I advanced and cleared the pass in spite of the force posted to
                        defend it, and advanced to Petra. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Here I
                        forced the king to give battle and defeated him. Macedonia submitted, and in
                        a fortnight I finished a war which for four years the consuls before me had
                        conducted in such a way that each handed on to his successor a more serious
                        task than he had received. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The fruits of
                        that victory showed themselves in further successes; the cities of Macedonia
                        made their surrender; the royal treasure fell into our hands; the king
                        himself was captured with his children in a temple at Samothrace, almost as
                        though the gods had delivered him into our power. Even I began to regard my
                        good fortune as something too great, and therefore distrusted it. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> I began to fear the perils of the sea, whilst
                        carrying the royal treasury into Italy and transporting my victorious army. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> "We had a favourable voyage, and after all
                        had reached Italy safely, and there was nothing more for me to pray for, my
                        one ardent desire was that in the usual turn of Fortune's wheel the change
                        might affect my house rather than the commonwealth. I hope, therefore, that
                        its continued prosperity has been secured by the signal calamity which has
                        overtaken me. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As though in mockery of
                        mortal grief, my triumph intervened between the death of my two sons. Both
                        Perseus and myself may now be regarded as noteworthy examples of the lot
                        which awaits men. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He, himself a captive,
                        has seen his children led as captives before him, but still, he has them
                        safe and sound; I, who have triumphed over him, went from the funeral of one
                        of my sons in my chariot to the Capitol, and returned to find the other at
                        the point of death. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Out of all my sons,
                        not one remains to bear the name of Lucius Aemilius Paulus. As though I had
                        a large family, two have been adopted by the Cornelian and Fabian houses;
                        there is not a Paulus left except myself. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        But your happiness and the good fortune of the republic are my consolation
                        in this ruin of my house." The self-restraint which this speech evinced made
                        a far greater impression upon his audience than if he had indulged in
                        tearful laments over his bereavement. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On December 1, Cn. Octavius celebrated his
                        naval victory over Perseus. That triumph was without prisoners and without
                        spoil. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He gave each member of the crews
                        seventy-five denarii; to the pilots twice as much; and to the captains four
                        times as much. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A meeting of the senate was
                        then convened, and the senators decided that Q. Cassius should conduct
                        Perseus and his son Alexander to Alba to remain there under guard.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The king was allowed to retain his
                        suite, his money, his silver plate and his household effects. Bithys the son
                        of Cotys, king of the Thracians was sent, together with the hostages, to
                        Carseoli, to be interned there. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The rest
                        of the captives who had been led in the triumphal procession were to be shut
                        up in prison. A few days later a deputation from Cotys arrived with a sum of
                        money for the ransom of his son and the other hostages. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> They were admitted to an audience of the senate, and
                        they especially urged that it was not of his own will that Cotys had
                        assisted Perseus; he had been compelled to give hostages, and they implored
                        the senate to allow them to be ransomed at such a figure as the senate
                        should fix. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The senate instructed the
                        praetor to tell them in reply that the senate bore in mind the friendly
                        relations which had existed between Rome and Cotys and the ancestors of
                        Cotys and the Thracian nation. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The giving
                        of hostages was itself the offence, and could not be alleged as an excuse,
                        for the Thracians had nothing to <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> fear
                        from Perseus, even had he kept the peace, much less when he was engaged in a
                        war with Rome. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> However, though Cotys had
                        preferred the favour of Perseus to the friendship of Rome, they would mete
                        out their treatment of him by what was consistent with their own dignity
                        more than by his deserts; they would send back his son and the hostages.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The beneficent acts of the people of
                        Rome were gratuitous; they preferred to leave the value of them in the
                        hearts of those who received them rather than to exact a cash payment for
                        them. Three commissioners were appointed T. Quinctius Flamininus, C.
                        Licinius Nerva and M. Caninius Rebilus-to conduct the hostages back to
                        Thrace, and each of the Thracian envoys received a present of 2000 ases.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Bithys was taken with the rest of the
                        hostages from Carseoli and sent to his father. The king's ships, which were
                        larger than had ever been seen before, were hauled up on to the Campus
                        Martius. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst the Macedonian triumph was still
                        fresh in men's minds and almost before their eyes, L. Anicius triumphed on
                        the day of the Quirinalia (Feb. 17) over Gentius and the Illyrians.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The spectacle as a whole showed rather
                        a general resemblance to the triumph of Paulus than a correspondence in
                        details. The general himself was a smaller man, and people contrasted the
                        position of the house of Anicius and his authority as praetor with the high
                        lineage of Aemilius and his rank as consul, and there could be no comparison
                        between Gentius and Perseus, or between the Illyrians <milestone n="3??"
                            unit="section"/> and the Macedonians, or between the spoils and wealth
                        carried in the two processions, or the amount of the donative to the
                        soldiers in the two armies. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But though the
                        recent triumph eclipsed this one, it was clear to the onlookers that in
                        itself it was by no means contemptible. The Illyrians were a nation
                        formidable both by land and sea, who felt secure in their strong fortified
                        positions, and Anicius had thoroughly subjugated them in a few days and
                        captured their king and all his family. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Many captured standards were carried in the procession, together with other
                        spoils, and the furniture of the palace, 27 pounds of gold, and 19 of
                        silver, besides 13,000 denarii and 120,000 silver pieces of Illyrian
                        coinage. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Before his chariot walked
                        Gentius, with his wife and children, Caravantius his brother, and several
                        Illyrian nobles. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Out of the booty each
                        legionary received 45 denarii, the centurions twice, and the cavalry three
                        times as much. Anicius gave to the Latin allies as much as to the Romans,
                        and to the seamen of the fleet as much as the soldiers received. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> The soldiers marched more joyously in this
                        triumph, and the general himself was the subject of many laudatory songs.
                        According to Antias, 200,000 sesterces were realised from the sale of that
                        booty, besides the gold and silver deposited in the treasury, but as it is
                        not clear to me how this sum was realised, I quote his authority instead of
                        stating it as a fact. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> By resolution of the
                        senate, Gentius, with his wife and children and brother, were interned in
                        Spoletium; the rest of the captives were thrown into prison in Rome. As the
                        Spoletians refused to be responsible for their safe-keeping, the royal
                        family were transferred to Iguvium. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                        remainder of the Illyrian spoils consisted of 220 swift barques. These Q.
                        Cassius was ordered by the senate to distribute amongst the Corcyraeans, the
                        Apolloniates and the Dyrrhachians. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls for the year had done nothing
                        worth recording in Liguria; the enemy never took the field, so they confined
                        themselves to devastating the country. They returned to Rome for the
                        elections, and on the first day M. Claudius Marcellus and C. Sulpicius Galba
                        were elected consuls. On the following day the election of praetors took
                        place. Those elected were L. Julius, L. Apuleius Saturninus, A. Licinius
                        Nerva, P. Rutilius Calvus, P. Quinctilius Varus and M. Fonteius. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The provinces assigned to them were the two home
                        jurisdictions, the two Spanish provinces, Sicily and Sardinia. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> This year was an intercalary one, the additional
                        day being the one following the Terminalia (Feb. 23). One of the augurs, C.
                        Claudius, died this year; the augurs chose T. Quinctius Flamininus in his
                        place; Q. Fabius Pictor, a Flamen Quirinalis, also died. During the year
                        Prusias went to Rome with his son Nicomedes. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> He entered the City amid a large concourse, and proceeded through the
                        streets to the tribunal of Q. Cassius the praetor, surrounded by a crowd of
                        citizens. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Addressing the praetor, he said
                        that he had come to pay reverence to the gods of the City, to salute the
                        senate and citizens of Rome, and to congratulate them on their victory over
                        Perseus and Gentius, and the extension of their sway by the subjugation of
                        the Macedonians and Illyrians. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On the
                        praetor informing him that the senate would grant him an audience on that
                        day, if he wished it, he requested to be allowed two days in which to visit
                        the temples of the gods and see the City and pay visits to his hosts and
                        friends. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> L. Cornelius Scipio, the quaestor
                        who had been sent to meet him at Capua, was appointed to take him round, and
                        a house in which he and his suite could find ample accommodation was hired
                        for him. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Three days afterwards he attended
                        a meeting of the senate. After congratulating them upon the victory, he
                        enumerated his own services in the war, and asked permission to sacrifice
                        ten full-grown victims in the Capitol in fulfilment of a vow, and one to
                        Fortune at Praeneste; these vows had been made for the victory of Rome. He
                        also requested that the alliance with him might be renewed, and that the
                        district taken from Antiochus, which, as the Romans had not assigned it to
                        any one, the Gauls had taken possession of, might be given to him.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Lastly, he commended his son to the
                        care and protection of the senate. </p>
                    <p> All who had commanded in Macedonia supported his requests, and, with one
                        exception, they were all granted. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> With
                        regard to the land, however, he was told that a commission would be sent to
                        investigate the question of ownership. If the territory belonged to Rome,
                        and had not been granted to any one, they should consider that no one was
                        more deserving of the grant than Prusias. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        If, however, it should turn out not to have belonged to Antiochus and had,
                        therefore, never been claimed by Rome, or should it prove to have been
                        actually granted to the Gauls, Prusias must pardon them if the people of
                        Rome were unwilling that anything should be granted to him to the injury of
                        another. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> To no one can a gift be grateful
                        when he knows that the giver can take it away whenever he pleases.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The senate accepted the commendation
                        of his son Nicomedes; the care with which the people of Rome protect the
                        sons of friendly monarchs was shown in the case of Ptolemy, King of Egypt.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> With this reply Prusias was
                        dismissed. Presents of . . . sesterces were ordered to he made to him and 50
                        pounds of silver plate. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The senate also
                        decided that presents should be made to Nicomedes of the same value as those
                        made to Masinissa's son Masgaba, and that the victims for sacrifice and the
                        other requisites, whether he wished to offer them at Rome or at Praeneste,
                        should be supplied to the king at the public cost, as in the case of the
                        magistrates. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> From the fleet at Brundisium
                        twenty warships were assigned to him for his use. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> Till the king had reached the fleet thus presented to
                        him, L Cornelius Scipio was to be his constant attendant, and was to defray
                        all expenses incurred by him and his suite. They say that the king was
                        wonderfully delighted with the kindness the people of Rome had shown towards
                        him. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> He refused to have any presents
                        purchased for himself, but he ordered his son to accept what the Roman
                        people gave him. This is what our historians say about Prusias. <milestone
                            n="19" unit="section"/> Polybius alleges that the king was unworthy of
                        his regal title; he was in the habit of meeting the ambassadors who were
                        sent to him with his head shaved, and wearing a freedman's cap, speaking of
                        himself as the manumitted slave of Rome, and wearing the distinctive dress
                        of this class on that account. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> At Rome,
                        too, when he entered the senate-house, he prostrated himself and kissed the
                        threshold and called the senators his protecting deities, with other
                        expressions more degrading to himself than complimentary to those who heard
                        him. After a stay of not more than thirty days in the City and the
                        neighbourhood he left for his kingdom. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> A
                        war in Asia was begun (between Eumenes and the Gauls) . . . </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
