<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>In Defense of Caius Rabirius</title>
    <title>Three orations on the Agrarian law, the four against Catiline, the orations for Rabirius,
     Murena, Sylla, Archias, Flaccus, Scaurus, etc.</title>
    <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
    <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
    <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
    <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
    <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
     <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
     <name>William Merrill</name>
     <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
     <name>David Smith</name>
    </respStmt>
    <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
    <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
      <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D. Yonge, B.
       A.</title>
      <imprint>
       <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
       <publisher>Henry G. Bohn, York Street, Covent Garden.</publisher>
       <date>1856</date>
      </imprint>
     </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  
  <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl n="CTS">
    <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
     <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
    </cRefPattern>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  
  <!--
    <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Corn.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="speech"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  -->
  
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
    <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
    <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2016-04-19" who="Lisa Cerrato">Minor changes; review of file conversion.</change>
   <change when="2016-03-14" who="Zach Himes">Converted section milestones to divs.</change>
   <change when="2015-12-13" who="Zach Himes">Cleaned up teiHeader. Converted to TEI P5 and EpiDoc.</change>
   <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
   <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
   <change when="2013-09-13" who="balmas01">reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version</change>
   <change when="2011-03-21" who="lcerrato">fixed typo in while to in which</change>
   <change when="2011-03-17" who="lcerrato">fixing gap tags against source</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-07-08" who="student">fixing place tags - AD</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09" who="rsingh04">more reorganizing of texts module by collection</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22" who="rsingh04">fixed references to Cic. Ver.</change>
   <change when="2007-01-04" who="packel">fixed the refsDecls for Cornelius</change>
   <change when="2006-05-05" who="packel">fixed date tags</change>
   <change when="2006-02-10" who="packel">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed thought you shall not perceive them to though...</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed: does not the precaution taken of assembling the senate in thus most defensible place thus to this</change>
   <change when="2005-08-01" who="packel">removed stray item tags</change>
   <change when="2005-07-25" who="packel">Converted to XML</change>
   <change when="2005-03-24" who="lcerrato">Marcus Aquillius changed to Manius Aquilius Agrarian 2.83</change>
   <change when="2005-03-23" who="lcerrato">changed Pro Font. 38 Marcus Aquillius to Manius Aquilius based on Latin and user report</change>
   <change when="2005-01-19" who="mimno">div1s missing type attributes</change>
   <change when="2004-06-14" who="lcerrato">changed Rob. Perd. 31 "heave" to "leave"</change>
   <change when="2003-07-01" who="yorkc">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
   <change when="2001-03-14" who="lcerrato">changed ought to he to ought to be in first oration against Cataline</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">really fix language ids</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">fix language codes</change>
   <change when="2000-03-04" who="dasmith">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
   <change when="2000-02-22" who="amahoney">fix a couple of broken bibl refs</change>
   <change when="1996-12-02" who="amahoney">replace the refsdecl, which disappeared somehow, and fix a couple of funny syntax errors</change>
   <change when="1996-11-30" who="lcerrato">revised and proofread again</change>
   <change when="1999-10-14" who="dasmith">Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt</change>
   <change when="1999-09-01" who="dasmith">Removed tag from attribute value.</change>
   <change when="1999-08-12" who="dasmith">Fixed refsDecl</change>
   <change when="1997-11-07" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-10-31" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-09-01" who="textgod">Added sections.</change>
   <change when="1997-08-18" who="textgod">Added to repository.</change>
   <change when="1997-07-14" who="DAS">ed.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 
 <text xml:lang="eng">
  <body>
   <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0474.phi012.perseus-eng3" subtype="translation">
   
   <head>THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO IN DEFENCE OF CAIUS RABIRIUS, ACCUSED OF TREASON.</head>
   
  <div type="commentary" subtype="section" resp="editor"> 
   <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
   <p>In the year A. U. C, 654, Lucius Saturninus, a tribune of the people, had been slain, in
    obedience to a decree of the senate, entrusting the safety of the republic to the consuls Caius
    Marius and Lucius Valerius Flaccus. Julius Caesar now suborned Titus Labienus, one of the
    present tribunes, to prosecute Rabirius, as being the person who had slain him, (the object of
    Caesar and his party being to put an end to, or at least a check upon, that prerogative of the
    senate by which, in a case of tumult, they could arm the city at once, by the customary vote,
    “<foreign xml:lang="lat">Videant consules nequid respublica detrimenti capiat</foreign>”; in
    obedience to which vote many seditious citizens had at different times been put to death
    without any trial, and this privilege of the senate had been a constant subject of complaint to
    the tribunes.) Julius Caesar procured himself to be appointed one of the <foreign xml:lang="lat">duumviri</foreign>, or two judges, who were to try the cause. Hortensius defended Rabirius,
    and proved that, though it would have been perfectly legal for Rabirius to slay Saturninus,
    still in point of fact he had nothing to do with his death, as he had been slain by a slave,
    who for the action had been emancipated by the people. Caesar, however, condemned Rabirius, who
    appealed to the people. And it was on the trial of this appeal that the following oration was
    delivered. Labienus would not allow Cicero to exceed half-an-hour in his defence; and, to raise
    the greater indignation against Rabirius, he exposed the picture of Saturninus in the rostra,
    as of one who had fallen a martyr to the liberties of the people. </p>
   <p>When, after the defence was over, the people were proceeding to vote, there was reason to
    apprehend some violence or foul play from the intrigues of the tribune. Accordingly Metellus,
    who was augur and also praetor that year, contrived to dissolve the assembly before they came
    to a vote; and the troubles that ensued in the latter part of the year prevented any farther
    attention being paid to the matter.</p></div>
  
   
   <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Although, O Romans, it is not my custom at the beginning of a speech to give any reason why I
    am defending each particular defendant, because I have always considered that the mere fact of
    the danger of any citizen was quite sufficient reason for my considering myself connected with
    him, still, in this instance, when I come forward to defend the life, and character, and all the
    fortunes of Caius Rabirius, I think I ought to give a reason for my undertaking this duty;
    because the very same reason which has appeared to me a most adequate one to prompt me to
    undertake his defence, ought also to appear to you sufficient to induce you to acquit him.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p> For the ancientness of my friendship with him, and the
    dignity of the man, and a regard for humanity, and the uninterrupted practice of my life, have
    instigated me to defend Caius Rabirius; and also the safety of the republic, my duty as consul,
    the very fact of my being consul since when I was made consul, the safety of the republic, and
    also that of each individual citizen in it was entrusted to me, compel me to do so with the
    greatest zeal. For it is not the actual offence, nor any desire to deprive Caius Rabirius in
    particular of life, nor is it any old, well grounded, serious enmity on the part of any citizen,
    which has brought him into this peril of his life. But the true design of this prosecution is,
    that that great aid which the majesty of the state and our dominion enjoys, and which has been
    handed down to us from our ancestors, may be banished from the republic; that the authority of
    the senate, and the absolute power of the consul, and the unanimity of all good men, may
    henceforth be of no avail against any mischief or ruin designed to the state; and therefore, as
    a handle for the destruction of all these weighty obstacles, the old age, and infirmity, and
    solitary condition of one man is attacked. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p>
   
   <milestone unit="para"/>Wherefore, if it is the part of a virtuous consul when he sees all the bulwarks of the
    republic undermined and weakened, to come to the assistance of his country; to bring succour to
    the safety and fortunes of all men; to implore the good faith of the citizens; to think his own
    safety of secondary consideration when put in competition with the common safety of all; it is
    the part also of virtuous and fearless citizens, such as you have shown yourself in all the
    emergencies of the republic, to block up all the avenues or sedition, to fortify the bulwarks of
    the state, to think that the supreme power is vested in the consuls, the supreme wisdom in the
    senate; and to judge the man who acts in obedience to them, worthy of praise and honour, rather
    than of condemnation and punishment. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p> Wherefore the labour in
    defending this man falls principally to my share; but the zeal for his preservation ought to be
    equally felt by me and by you. <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>For you ought to think, O Romans, that, in the memory of man, no affair more important, more
    full of peril to you, more necessary to be carefully watched by you, has ever been undertaken by
    a tribune of the people, nor opposed by a consul, nor brought before the Roman people. For there
    is nothing less at stake, O Romans, in this that there is no other object aimed at, than the
    preventing any public council from being active for the future in the republic, any union from
    being formed of good men against the frenzy and insanity of wicked citizens; any refuge, any
    protection, any safety from existing at the most critical extremity of the republic. 
   <milestone unit="para"/></p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus"><p> And, as this is the case, in the first place, (as is most
    necessary to be done, in such a contest for a man's life and reputation, and all his fortunes,)
    I entreat pardon and indulgence from the excellent and mighty
      <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>, and from all the other immortal gods and
    goddesses; by whose aid and protection this republic is governed much more than by any reason or
    wisdom of man. And I pray of them to grant that this day may have dawned for the salvation of
    this man, and for the welfare of the republic. And, in the second place, I beg and entreat you,
    O Romans,—you whose power comes nearest to the divine authority of the immortal gods,—that since
    at one and the same time the life of Caius Rabirius, a most unhappy and most innocent man, and
    the safety of the republic is entrusted to your hands and to your votes, you will display that
    mercy, as far as regards the fortunes of the individual, and that wisdom in what concerns the
    safety of the republic, which you are accustomed to exercise. 
   <milestone unit="para"/></p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p> Now, since, O Titus Labienus, you have sought to cramp my
    industry by a narrow space of time, and have denied the usual length of a defence which I was
    prepared to use, confining me to a single half-hour; I will comply with the conditions laid down
    by the accuser, (which is a most scandalous thing to have to do,) and yield to the power of our
    enemy, (which is a most miserable fate for a man to be compelled to,) although in prescribing to
    me this half-hour you have left me only the part of an advocate, and have ignored my <pb n="266"/> right as consul; because, though this time will be nearly sufficient for me to make our
    defence in, it will not allow time enough for preferring the complaints which we are entitled to
    prefer. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p> Unless, perhaps, you think it necessary for me to
    reply to you at some length about the sacred places and groves which you have said were violated
    by my client; though in making this accusation you never said anything more than that this
    charge had been made against Caius Rabirius by Caius Macer. And with respect to this matter I
    marvel that you recollect what his enemy Macer accused Caius Rabirius of, and forget what
    impartial judges decided on their oaths. </p></div><milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Must I needs make a long speech on the topics of peculation, or of burning the registers? of
    which charge Caius Curtius, a relation of Caius Rabirius, was most honourably acquitted, as was
    due to his virtue, by a most illustrious bench of judges. But Rabirius himself not only was
    never prosecuted on either of these charges, but never fell under any the very slightest
    suspicion of them; nor was any such idea ever breathed by any one. Or must I be careful to reply
    to what has been said touching his sister's son? who, you said, had been murdered by him, as he
    sought an excuse for putting off the trial on the pretext of a domestic calamity. For what is
    more natural than that his sister's husband should be dearer to him than his sister's son? and
    so much dearer; that he would deprive the one of life in a most cruel manner, in order to gain a
    two days' adjournment of his trial for the other? Or need I say much respecting the detention of
    another man's slaves contrary to the Fabian law, or of the scourging and putting to death of
    Roman citizens, contrary to the Porcian law, when Caius Rabirius is honoured with the zeal
    displayed in his behalf by all <placeName key="tgn,7010380">Apulia</placeName>, and by the
    eminent good-will of the state of <placeName key="tgn,7003005">Campania</placeName>; and when
    not only individuals, but I may almost say whole nations, have flocked hither to deliver him
    from danger, brought up from a greater distance than his name as a neighbour of theirs on their
    borders required? For why need I prepare a long speech on that point when it is set down in the
    count which assesses the damages, that he had regard to neither his own chastity nor to that of
    others? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p> Moreover, I suspect that it was on that account that I
    was limited by Labienus to half an hour, in order that I might not be able to say much on this
    question of chastity. Therefore, you perceive that this half-hour is too long for me to discuss
    those charges which especially require the care of an advocate. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>That other part about the death of Saturninus, you wished to be too short and narrow for my
    requirements; and it is one which requires and stands in need, not so much of the ingenuity of
    an orator, as of the authority of a consul. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus"><p> For as for the
    trial for treason, which, when you accuse me, you say has been put an end to by me, that is a
    charge against me; and not against Rabirius. And I wish, O Romans, that I was the first or the
    only person, who had abolished that in this republic. I wish that that, which he brings forward
    as a charge against me, might be an evidence of my peculiar glory. For what can be desired by
    any one which I should prefer to being said in my consulship to have banished the executioner
    from the forum, and the gallows from the Campus? But that credit belongs, in the first instance,
    O Romans, to our ancestors, who, after the kings had been expelled, did not choose to retain any
    vestige of kingly cruelty among a free people; and in the second instance, to many gallant men,
    who thought it fit that your liberty should not be an unpopular thing from the severity of the
    punishments with which it was protected but that it should be defended by the lenity of the
    laws. </p></div><milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Which, then, of us, O Labienus, is attached to the best interests of the people? you who think
    that an executioner and chains ought to be put in operation against Roman citizens in the very
    assembly of the people; who order a gallows to be planted and erected for the execution of
    citizens in the <placeName key="tgn,7006964">Campus Martius</placeName>, in the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia centuriata</foreign> in a place hallowed by the auspices, or I, who
    forbid the assembly to be polluted by the contagion of an executioner who think that the forum
    of the Roman people ought to be purified from all such traces of nefarious wickedness who urge
    that the assembly ought to be kept pure, the campus holy, the person of every Roman citizen
    inviolate, and the rights of liberty unimpaired? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p> Of a truth,
    the tribune of the people is very much devoted to the interests of the people,—is a guardian and
    defender of its privileges and liberties! The Porcian law forbade a rod to be laid on the person
    of any Roman citizen. This merciful man has brought back the scourge. The Porcian law protected
    the freedom of the citizens against the lictor. Labienus, that friend of the people, has handed
    them over to the executioner. Caius Gracchus passed a law that no trial should take place
    affecting the life of a Roman citizen without your orders. This friend of the people has
    compelled the duumvirs (without any order of yours being issued on the subject) not only to try
    a Roman citizen, but to condemn a Roman citizen to death without hearing him in his own defence.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p> Do you dare to make mention to me of the Porcian law, or of
    Caius Gracchus, or of the liberty of these men, or of any single man who has really been a
    friend of the people, after having attempted to violate the liberty of this people, to tempt
    their merciful disposition, and to change the customs, not only with unusual punishments, but
    with a perfectly unheard-of cruelty of language? For these expressions of yours, which you, O
    merciful and people-loving man, are so fond of; “Go, lictor, bind his hands,” are not only not
    quite in character with this liberty and this merciful disposition, but they are not suited to
    the times even of Romulus or of Numa Pompilius. Those are the songs suited to the torments in
    use in the time of Tarquin, that most haughty and in human monarch; but you, O merciful man, O
    friend of the people, delight to rehearse, “Cover his head—hang him to the ill-omened
    tree,”—words, O Romans, which in this republic have long since been buried in the darkness of
    antiquity, and have been overwhelmed by the light of liberty </p></div><milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>If, then, this had been a popular sort of proceeding, if it had had the least particle of
    equity or justice in it, would Caius Gracchus have passed it over? Forsooth, I suppose, the
    death of your uncle was a greater affliction to you, than the loss of his brother was to Caius
    Gracchus. And the death of that uncle whom you never saw is more painful to you, than the death
    of that brother, with whom he lived on the terms of the most cordial affection, was to him. <gap reason="lost"/>And you avenge the death of your uncle just as he would have wished to avenge
    the death of his brother, if he had been inclined to act on your principles. And that great
    Labienus, your illustrious uncle, whoever he was, left quite as great a regret behind him in the
    bosoms of the Roman people, as Tiberius Gracchus left? Was your piety greater than that of
    Gracchus? or your courage? or your wisdom? or your wealth? or your influence? or your eloquence?
    And yet all those qualities, if he had had ever so little of them, would have been thought great
    in him in comparison of your qualifications. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p> But as Caius
    Gracchus surpassed every one in all these particulars, how great do you suppose must be the
    distance which is interposed between him and you? But Gracchus would rather have died a thousand
    times by the most painful of deaths, than have allowed the executioner to stand in that
    assembly—a man whom the laws of the censors considered ought not only to be ejected out of the
    forum, but even to be deprived of the sight of the sky, of the breath of the atmosphere, and of
    a home in the city. This man dares to call himself a friend of the people, and me an enemy to
    your interests; when he has hunted out all the cruelties of punishments and of harsh language,
    not only as supplied by your recollection, and by that of your fathers, but from all the records
    of our annals, and all the histories of the kings; and I, with all my power, and all my
    ingenuity, and all my eloquence, and all my energy, have opposed and resisted his cruelty.
    Unless, perhaps, you are fond of such a condition of existence as even slaves would not be able
    by any possibility to bear, if they had not the hope of liberty held out to them. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p> The ignominy of a public trial is a miserable thing,—the deprivation of
    a man's property by way of penalty is a miserable thing,—exile is a miserable thing; but still,
    in all these disasters some trace of liberty remains to one. Even if death be threatened, we may
    die free men; but the executioner, and the veiling of the head, and the mere name of the gibbet,
    should be far removed, not only from the persons of Roman citizens—from their thoughts, and
    eyes, and ears. For not only the actual fact and endurance of all these things, but the bare
    possibility of being exposed to them,—the expectation, the mere mention of them even,—is
    unworthy of a Roman citizen and of a free man. Does not the kindness of their masters at one
    touch deliver our slaves from the fear of all these punishments; and shall neither our exploits,
    nor the purity of our past life, nor the honours which you have conferred on us, save us from
    the scourge, from the hangman's hook, and even from the dread of the gibbet? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"><p> Wherefore I confess, and even, O Titus Labienus, I avow and openly allege that
    you have been driven from that cruel, unreasonable, (I will not say tribunitian, but) tyrannical
    persecution, by my counsel, by my virtue, and by my influence. And although in that prosecution
    you neglected all the precedents of our ancestors, all the laws, all the authority of the
    senate, all religious feeling, and even the public observance due to the auspices, still you
    shall hear nothing of all this from me, now that I have so little time to speak in. We shall
    have abundant opportunity hereafter for a discussion on those points. </p></div><milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>At present we will speak of the accusation touching the death of Saturninus, and of the death
    of your most illustrious uncle. You say in impeachment of my client, that Lucius Saturninus was
    slain by Caius Rabirius. And Rabirius has already proved that to be false by the evidence of
    many men, when Quintus Hortensius defended him at great length. But I, if I had to begin the
    defence anew, would brave this charge, would acknowledge its truth, would avow it. I only wish
    that the state of my client's cause would give me the opportunity of making this statement, that
    Lucius Saturninus, the enemy of the Roman people, was slain by the hand of Caius Rabirius. That
    outcry has no effect on me, but it rather consoles me, as it shows that there are some citizens
    ignorant of the facts of the case, but not many. Never, believe me, never would the Roman people
    which is silent around me, have made me consul if it had supposed that I was going to be
    disturbed by your clamour. How much less is your noise now! Repress your murmurs, the evidence
    of your folly, and the proof of the scantiness of your numbers. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"><p> I would, I say, willingly confess, if I could with truth, or even if the cause were not
    already discussed, that Lucius Saturninus was shun by the band of Caius Rabirius; and I should
    think it a most glorious deed. But since I cannot do that, I will confess this, which will have
    less weight with regard to our credit, but not less with regard to the accusation—I confess that
    Caius Rabirius took up arms for the purpose of slaying Saturninus. What is the matter, Labienus?
    What more weighty confession do you expect from me; or what greater charge did you expect me to
    furnish against him? Unless you think that there is any difference between him who slew the man,
    and him who was in arms for the purpose of slaying him. If it was wrong for Saturninus to be
    slain, then arms cannot have been taken up against Saturninus without guilt;—if you admit that
    arms were lawfully taken up,—then you must inevitably confess that he was rightly slain.<gap reason="lost"/>
    </p></div><milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>A resolution of the senate is passed, that Caius Marius and Lucius Valerius, the consuls,
    shall employ the tribunes of the people and the praetors as they think fit; and shall take care
    that the empire and majesty of the Roman people be preserved. They do employ all the tribunes of
    the people except Saturninus, and all the praetors except Glaucia; they bid every one who
    desires the safety of the republic to take arms and to follow them. Every one obeys. Arms are
    distributed from the sacred buildings and from the public armouries to the Roman people, Caius
    Marius the consul distributing them. Here now, to say nothing of other points, I ask you
    yourself; O Labienus, when Saturninus in arms was in possession of the Capitol; when Glaucia,
    and Caius Saufeius, and even that Gracchus <note anchored="true"> This was a man of the name of
     Equitius Tismo, whom Saturninus gave out to be a son of Tiberius Gracchus. When Marius shut up
     the prisoners who had surrendered in the Curia Hostilia, and the people stripped off the roof;
     and threw the tiles down on them, this pseudo Gracchus was slain among the others.</note> just
    escaped from chains and the jail, were with him; I will add, too, since you wish me to do so,
    Quintus Labienus, your own uncle; but in the forum were Caius Marius and Lucius Valerius Flaccus
    the consuls, behind them all the senate, and that senate, too, whom even you yourselves (who try
    to render the conscript fathers of the present day unpopular, in order the more easily to
    diminish the power of the senate) are accustomed to extol; when the equestrian order-—what men
    the Roman knights, O ye immortal gods, then were!—when they supported, as they did in the time
    of our fathers, a great portion of the republic, and the whole dignity of the courts of justice;
    when all men, of all ranks, who thought their own safety involved in the safety of the republic,
    had taken arms;—what, then, was Caius Rabirius to do? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus"><p> I ask
    you yourself; I say, O Labienus,—when the consuls, in pursuance of the resolution of the senate,
    had summoned the citizens to arms; when Marcus Aemilius, the chief of the senate, stood in arms
    in the assembly; who, though he could scarcely walk, thought the lameness of his feet not an
    impediment to his pursuit of enemies, but only to his flight from them; when, lastly, Quintus
    Scaevola, worn out as he was with old age, enfeebled by disease, lame, and crippled, and
    powerless in all his limbs, leaning on his spear, displayed at the same time the vigour of his
    mind and the weakness of his body; when Lucius Metellus, Sergius Galba, Caius Serranus, Publius
    Rutilius, Caius Fimbria, Quintus Catulus, and all the men of consular rank who were then in
    existence, had taken arms in defence of the common safety; when all the praetors, all the nobles
    and youth of the city, united together, Cnaeus and Lucius Domitius, Lucius Crassus, Quintus
    Mucius, Caius Claudius, Marcus Drusus; when all the Octavii, Metelli, Julii, Cassii, Catos and
     <placeName key="perseus,Pompeii">Pompeii</placeName>; when Lucius Philippus, Lucius Scipio,
    when Marcus Lepidus, when Decimus Brutus, when this very man himself; Servilius, under whom you,
    O Labienus, have served as your general; when this Quintus Catulus, whom we see here, then a
    very young man; when this Caius Curio; when, in short, every illustrious man in the city was
    with the consuls;—what then did it become Caius Rabirius to do? Was he to lie hid, shut up, and
    concealed in some dark place, and to hide his cowardice under the protection of darkness and
    walls? Or was he to go into the Capitol, and there join himself to your uncle, and with the rest
    of those who were fleeing to death, on account of the infamy of their lives? Or was he to unite
    with Marius, Scarius, Catulus, Metellus, Scaevola,—in short, with all virtuous men, in a
    community not only of safety, but also of danger? </p></div><milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Even you yourself; O Labienus, what would you do in such a crisis? When your general system of
    indolence was compelling you to flight and lurking-places, while the villainy and frenzy of
    Lucius Saturninus was inviting you to the Capitol, while the consuls were summoning you to
    uphold the safety and liberty of your country; which authority, which invitation, which party
    would you prefer to follow, whose command would you select to obey? My uncle says he was with
    Saturninus. What if he was? Whom was your father with?—What if he was? Where were your
    relations, Roman knights?—What if he was? What was the conduct of all your prefecture, and
    district, and neighbourhood?—What if he was? What was the conduct of the whole Picene district;
    did they follow the frenzy of the tribune, or the authority of the consul? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus"><p> In truth, I affirm this; that that which you confess of your uncle, no man has
    ever yet confessed with respect to himself. No one, I say, has been found so profligate, so
    abandoned, so entirely destitute, not only of all honesty, but of every resemblance of and
    pretence to honesty, as to confess that he was in the Capitol with Saturninus. But your uncle
    was. Let him have been; and let him have been, though not compelled by the desperate condition
    of his own affairs, or by airy domestic distresses and embarrassments. Suppose it was his
    intimacy with Lucius Saturninus that induced him to prefer his friendship to his country,—was
    that a reason for Caius Rabirius also deserting the republic? for his not appearing in that
    armed multitude of good men? for his refusing obedience to the invitation and command of the
    consul? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus"><p> But we see that in the nature of things he must have
    adopted one of these three lines of conduct: he must either have been with Saturninus, or with
    the good men, or he must have been lying in bed—to lie hid was a state equal to the most
    infamous death; to be with Saturninus was the act of insanity and wickedness. Virtue, and
    honour, and shame, compelled him to range himself on the side of the consuls. Do you, therefore,
    accuse Caius Rabirius on this account, that he was with those men whom he would have been
    utterly mad to have opposed, utterly infamous if he had deserted them? <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But Caius Decianus, whom you often mention, was condemned, because, when he was accusing, with
    the earnest approval of all good men, a man notorious for every description of infamy, Publius
    Furius, he dared to complain in the assembly of the death of Saturninus. And Sextus Titius was
    condemned for having an image of Lucius Saturninus in his house. The Roman knights laid it down
    by that decision that that man was a worthless citizen, and one who ought not to be allowed to
    remain in the state, who either by keeping his image sought, to do credit to the death of a man
    who was seditious to such a degree as to become an enemy to the republic, or who sought by pity
    to excite the regrets of ignorant men, or who showed his own inclination to imitate such
    villainy. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus"><p> Therefore it does seem a marvellous thing to me,
    where you, O Labienus, found thus image which you have. For after Sextus Titius was condemned,
    no one could be found who would dare to have it in his possession. But if you had heard of that,
    or if, from your age, you could have known it, you certainly would never have brought that
    image, which, even when concealed in his house, had brought ruin and exile on Sextus Titius,
    into the rostrum, and into the assembly of the people; nor would you ever have driven your
    designs on those rocks on which you had seen the ship of Sextus Titius dashed to pieces, and the
    fortunes of Caius Decianus hopelessly wrecked. But in all these matters you are erring out of
    ignorance. For you have undertaken the advocacy of a cause which is older than your own
    recollections; a cause which was dead before you were born; that cause in which you yourself
    would have been, if your age had allowed you to be so, you are bringing before this court.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26" resp="perseus"><p> Do you not understand, in the first place, what sort of men,
    what sort of citizens they were whom, now that they are dead, you are accusing of the greatest
    wickedness? Are you not aware, how many of those who are still alive, you, by the same
    accusation, are bringing into peril of their lives? For if Caius Rabirius committed a capital
    crime in having borne arms against Lucius Saturninus, yet the age which he was then of might
    furnish him with some excuse by which to secure himself from danger. But how are we to defend
    Quintus Catulus, the father of this Catulus, a man in whom the very highest wisdom, eminent
    virtue, and singular humanity were combined? and Marcus Scaurus, a man of great gravity, wisdom,
    and prudence? or the two Mucii, or Lucius Crassus, or Marcus Antonius, who was at that time
    outside the city with a guard? all men than whom there was no one of greater wisdom or ability
    in the whole city; or how are we to defend the other men of equal dignity, the guardians and
    counselors of the republic, who behaved in the same way, now that they are dead? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27" resp="perseus"><p> What are we to say about those most honourable men and most excellent
    citizens, the Roman knights, who then combined with the senate in defence of the safety of the
    republic? What are we to say of the aerarian tribunes, <note anchored="true">“The <foreign xml:lang="lat">tribuni aerarii</foreign>, who constituted an order in the latter days of the
     republic, and who were, in fact, the representatives of the most respectable plebeians, were
     originally heads of tribes, who acted as; general inspectors and collectors of the <foreign xml:lang="lat">aes militare</foreign> for the payment of the troops.” “The charge of the
     treasury was originally entrusted to the quaestors and their assistants, the <foreign xml:lang="lat">tribuni aerarii</foreign>.” “Niebuhr supposes that the <foreign xml:lang="lat">tribuni aerani</foreign>, who occur down to the end of the republic, were only the successors
     of the tribunes of the tribes.” <foreign xml:lang="lat">Vide</foreign> Smith, Dict. Ant. pp. 19,
     20, 987, vv. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Aerarii</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="lat">Aerarium</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="lat">Tribunus</foreign>.</note> and of the men of all
    the other orders in the state, who then took up arms in defence of the common liberties of all?
     <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But why do I speak of all those men who obeyed the command of the consuls? What is to become
    of the reputation of the consuls themselves? Are we to condemn Lucius Flaccus, a man always most
    diligent in the service of the republic, and in the discharge of his duty as a magistrate, and
    in his priesthood, and in the religious ceremonies over which he presided, as guilty of
    nefarious wickedness and parricide, now that he is dead? And are we to mute with hum in this
    stigma and infamy, after death, the name of even Caius Marius? Are we, I say, to condemn Caius
    Marius now that he is dead, as guilty of nefarious wickedness, and parricide, whom we may
    rightly entitle the father of his country, the parent of your liberties, and of this republic?
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28" resp="perseus"><p> In truth, if Titus Labienus thought himself entitled to
    erect a gibbet in the <placeName key="tgn,7006964">Campus Martius</placeName> for Caius
    Rabirius, because he took up arms, what punishment ought to be devised for the man who invited
    him to do so? And if a promise was given to Saturninus, as is constantly asserted by you, it was
    not Caius Rabirius, but Caius Marius who gave it; and it was he too who violated it, if indeed
    it was broken at all. But what promise, O Labienus, could be given except by a resolution of the
    senate? Are you so complete a stranger in this city, are you so ignorant of our constitution and
    of our customs, as to be ignorant of this? Are we to think that you are living as a foreigner in
    a strange town, not bearing office in your own native city?—</p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29" resp="perseus"><p>“Well,” says he, “but what harm can all this now do Caius Marius, since he has no longer any
    feeling or any life?” Is it so? Would Caius Marius have spent his life in such labours and such
    dangers, if he had no hopes and no ideas of any glory which was to extend beyond the limits of
    his own life? No doubt, when he had routed the countless armies of the enemy in <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, and when he had delivered the city from siege, he thought
    that all his achievements would perish with himself. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30" resp="perseus"><p> Such is
    not the truth, O Romans. Nor is there any one among us who exerts himself amid the dangers of
    the republic with virtue and glory, who is not induced to do so by the hope he entertains of
    receiving his reward from posterity—therefore, while there are many reasons why I think that the
    souls of good men are divine and undying, this is the greatest argument of all to my mind, that
    the more virtuous and wise each individual is, the more thoroughly does his mind look forward to
    the future, so as to seem, in fact, to regard nothing <pb n="276"/> except what is eternal.
    Wherefore, I call to witness the souls of Caius Marius and of the other wise men and gallant
    citizens which seem to me to have emigrated from life among men to the holy habitations and
    sacred character of the gods, that I think it my duty to contend for their fame, and glory, and
    memory, no less than for the shrines and temples of my native land; and that if I had to take up
    arms in defence of their credit, I should take them up no less zealously than they took them up
    in defence of the common safety. In truth, O Romans, nature has given us but a limited space to
    live in, but an endless period of glory. <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Wherefore, if we pay due honour to those who have already died, we shall leave to ourselves a
    more favourable condition after death. But it O Labienus, you neglect those whom we are unable
    any longer to behold, do not you think that at least you ought to consult the interests of these
    men whom you see before you? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31" resp="perseus"><p> I say that there is no one of
    all those men who were at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> on that day, which day
    you are now bringing as it were before the court,—that there was no one of the youth of Rome,
    who did not take arms and follow the consuls; all those men, whose conduct you can form a
    conjecture about from their age, are now impeached by you of a capital crime, by your attack
    upon Caius Rabirius. But it was Rabirius who slew Saturninus. I wish that he had done so. I
    should not be deprecating punishment for him; I should demand a reward for him. In truth, if his
    freedom was given to Scaeva, a slave of Quintus Croto, who did slay Lucius Saturninus, what
    reward ought to have been given to a Roman knight in a similar case? And if Caius Marius,
    because he had caused drains to be cut, by which water was supplied to the temple of the
    excellent and mighty <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>, and because on the
     <placeName key="tgn,7006963">Capitoline Hill</placeName><gap reason="lost"/>
    </p></div><milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/><note anchored="true"> All the last chapter was discovered by Niebuhr in the <placeName key="tgn,7001168">Vatican</placeName>, and edited by him; it was discovered in a very corrupt
     and mutilated state, but it is translated as he edited it with his own supplementary additions,
     and completion of the legible words.</note><gap reason="lost"/>Therefore the senate, in its
    investigation into that cause, when I was pleading before it, was neither more diligent nor more
    severe than all of you were, when you by your dispositions, by your hands, and by your voices,
    declared your rejection of that distribution of the whole world, and of that very district of
     <placeName key="tgn,7003005">Campania</placeName>. 
   <milestone unit="para"/></p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33" resp="perseus"><p> I also proclaim, and assert, and denounce the same things
    which he does who is the originator of this trial. There is no king remaining, no nation, no
    people, whom you can fear. There is no foreign or external evil which can insinuate itself into
    this republic. If you wish this state to be immortal, if you wish your empire to be eternal, if
    you wish your glory to continue everlasting, then it is our own passions, it is the turbulence
    and desire of revolution engendered among our own citizens, it is intestine evil, it is domestic
    treason that must be guarded against. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34" resp="perseus"><p> And your ancestors have
    left you a great protection against these evils in these words of the consul, “Whoever wishes
    the republic to be safe.” Protect the legitimate use of these words, O Romans. Do not by your
    decision take the republic out of my hands; and do not take from the republic its hope of
    liberty, its hope of safety, its hope of dignity. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35" resp="perseus"><p> What should
    I do, if Titus Labienus were to make a slaughter of the citizens, like Lucius Saturninus? if he
    were to break open the prison? if he had occupied the Capitol with armed men? I should do what
    Caius Marius did. I should refer the matter to the senate; I should exhort you to defend the
    republic. I myself in arms should, with your aid, resist the armed enemy. Now, when there is no
    suspicion of arms, when I see no weapons, when there is no violence, or slaughter, or occupation
    of the Capitol and citadel, but only a mischievous prosecution, a cruel trial, a business
    undertaken by a tribune of the people contrary to the interests of the republic, I have not
    thought that I ought to summon you to arms, but that it was sufficient to exhort you to give
    your votes against those who are attacking your majesty. Therefore now I entreat, and beg, and
    implore all of you, not, as is the old custom, <gap reason="lost"/></p></div><milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>is afraid.—He who has received on his front all these scars, marks of his valour, in the cause
    of the republic, fears to receive any wound on his reputation. He, whom no attack of an enemy
    could ever move from his post, now is frightened at this onset of his fellow-citizens, to which
    he must necessarily yield. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37" resp="perseus"><p> Nor does he now ask of you an
    opportunity of living happily, but only one of dying honourably. He is anxious now, not to enjoy
    his own home, but not to be deprived of his family tomb. He now begs and prays for nothing else
    at your hands, beyond your abstaining from depriving him of his legitimate funeral rites, and of
    the privilege of dying at home. He entreats you to allow him who has never feared any danger of
    death in his country's cause, in that country to die. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>I have spoken now to the extent of the time allowed me by the tribune of the people. I beg and
    entreat of you to think this defence which I have made faithful as far as the danger of my
    friend is concerned, and as far as the safety of the republic is at stake, suited to the
    dignity, and to the duty of the consul.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38f"><p><gap reason="omitted"/></p></div>
  </div>
 </body>
 </text>

</TEI>
