<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
                  <title>Against Eutropius</title>
            <author>Claudian</author>
            <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
               <name>Bridget Almas</name>
               <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
               <name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder n="org:Mellon">The Mellon Foundation</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            <date type="release">2011-09-12</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>Claudian</title>
                  <author>Claudius Claudianus</author>
                  <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <pubPlace>London, England</pubPlace>
                     <date>1922</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <ref target="https://archive.org/details/claudian01clau#page/138/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl><p>Keyboarding</p></editorialDecl>
                     <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
                              <state unit="book" delim="."/>
                              <state unit="poem"/>
                     </refsDecl>
            </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="stoa0089.stoa008.perseus-eng1">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.1.p.139" TEIform="pb"/>
         <div1 type="book" n="1" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <p>
Let the world cease to wonder at the births of
creatures half human, half bestial, at monstrous
babes that affright their own mothers, at the howling
of wolves heard by night in the cities, at beasts that
speak to their astonied herds, at stones falling
like rain, at the blood-red threatening storm clouds,
at wells of water changed to gore, at moons that
clash in mid heaven and at twin suns. All portents
pale before our eunuch consul. O shame to heaven
and earth! Our cities behold an old woman decked
in a consul's robe who gives a woman's name to the
year.1 Open the pages of the Cumaean Sibyl, ye
pontifs; let wise Etrurian seers consult the lightning's
flash, and the soothsayer search out the awful
portent hidden in the entrails. What new dread
warning is this the gods give? Does Nile desert
his bed and leaving Roman soil seek to mix his
waters with those of the Red Sea? Does cleft
Niphates 2 once more let through a host of eastern
barbarians to ravage our lands? Does a pestilence
threaten us? Or shall no harvest repay the farmer?
</p>
         <p>What victim can expiate divine anger such as this?
</p>
         <p>What offering appease the cruel altars? The consul's
<pb id="v.1.p.141"/>
own blood must cleanse the consular insignia, the
monster itself must be sacrificed. Whatever it be
that fate prepares for us and shows forth by such an
omen, let Eutropius' death, I pray, avert it all.
</p>
         <p>Fortune, is thy power so all-embracing? What
is this savage humour of thine? To what lengths
wilt thou sport with us poor mortals? If it was thy
will to disgrace the consul's chair with a servile
occupant let some <q direct="unspecified">consul</q> come forward with
broken chains, let an escaped jail-bird don the robes
of Quirinus — but at least give us a man. There are
grades even among slaves and a certain dignity;
that slave who has served but one master holds a
position of less infamy. Canst thou count the
waves of the sea, the grains of Africa's sands, if so
thou canst number Eutropius' masters. How many
owners has he had, in how many sale-catalogues has
he appeared, how often has he changed his name!
</p>
         <p>How often has he been stripped while buyer consulted
doctor whether there lurked any flaw by reason
of some hidden disease! All repented having bought
him and he always returned to the slave-market
while he could yet fetch a price. When he became
but a foul corpse-like body, a mass of senile pendulous
flesh, his masters were anxious to rid their
houses of him by giving him away as a present and
made haste to foist the loathsome gift on an unsuspecting
friend. To so many different yokes did he
submit his neck, this slave, old in years but ever
new to the house; there was no end to his servitude
though many beginnings.
</p>
         <p>He is destined from his very cradle to bloody
tortures; straight from his mother's womb he is
hurried away to be made a eunuch; no sooner born
<pb id="v.1.p.143"/>
than he becomes a prey to suffering. Up hastens
the Armenian, skilled by operating with unerring
knife to make males womanish and to increase their
loathly value by such loss. He drains the body's
life-giving fluid from its double source and with one
blow deprives his victim of a father's function and
the name of husband. Eutropius lay doubtful of
life, and the severed sinews drew a numbness deep
down into his furthest brain.
</p>
         <p>Are we to praise the hand that robbed an enemy
of his strength? Or shall we rather blame the fates?
</p>
         <p>It would have been better had he remained a man;
his very disgrace has proved a blessing to him. Had
he had his full manly vigour he would still have been
a slave.
</p>
         <p>After this he is dragged from one Assyrian mart
to another; next in the train of a Galatian slave-
merchant he stands for sale in many a market and
knows many diverse houses. Who could tell the
names of all his buyers? Among these Ptolemy,
servant of the post-house,1 was one of the better
known. Then Ptolemy, tired of Eutropius' long
service to his lusts, gives him to Arinthaeus; — gives,
for he is no longer worth keeping nor old enough
to be bought. How the scorned minion wept at Ms
departure, with what grief did he lament that
divorce! <q direct="unspecified">Was this thy fidelity, Ptolemy? Is
this my reward for a youth lived in thine arms,
for the bed of marriage and those many nights spent
together in the inn? Must I lose my promised
liberty? Leav'st thou Eutropius a widow, cruel
wretch, forgetful of such wonderful nights of love?
How hard is the lot of my kind! When a woman
grows old her children cement the marriage tie and
<pb id="v.1.p.145"/>
a mother's dignity compensates for the lost charms
of a wife. Me Lucina, goddess of childbirth, will
not come near; I have no children on whom to rely.
Love perishes with my beauty; the roses of my
cheeks are faded. What wits can save my wretched
back from blows? How can I, an old man, please?</q>
So saying he entered upon the skilled profession
of a pander. His whole heart was in his work;
he knew his business well and was master of every
stratagem for the undoing of chastity. No amount
of vigilance could protect the marriage -bed from
his attack; no bars could shut him out. He would
have haled even Danae from her refuge in the
brazen tower. He would represent his patron as
dying of love. Was the lady stubborn, he would
win her by his patience; was she greedy, by a gift;
flighty, he would corrupt her with a jest. None
could arrest the attention of a maidservant with
so neat a touch as he, none twitch aside a dress so
lightly and whisper his shameful message in her
ear. Never was any so skilled to choose a scene
for the criminal meeting, or so clever at avoiding
the wrath of the cuckold husband should the plot
be discovered. One thought of Lais of Corinth, to
whom the enamoured youth of that city brought
wealth from its twin seas, who, when her grey
hair could no longer go crowned with roses, when
the emulous crowd of her admirers ceased nightly to
haunt her doors and but few were left to knock thereat,
when before the mirror's verdict age shrank back
in horror from itself, yet stood, still faithful to her calling,
and as a pander dressed others for the part, haunting
still the brothel she had loved so well and so long,
and still pandering to the tastes old age forbade her.
<pb id="v.1.p.147"/>
Hence sprang Eutropius' fame; for, though a
eunuch's one virtue be to guard the chastity of the
marriage-chamber, here was one (and one only)
who grew great through adulteries. But the lash
fell as before on his back whenever his master's
criminal passion was through him frustrated. Then
it was in vain that he prayed for forgiveness and
reminded his lord of all those years of faithful
service; he would find himself handed over to a
son-in-law as part of the bride's dowry. Thus he
would become a lady's-maid, and so the future
consul and governor of the East would comb his
mistress' locks or stand naked holding a silver
vessel of water wherein his charge could wash
herself. And when overcome by the heat she
threw herself upon her couch, there would stand
this patrician fanning her with bright peacock
feathers.
</p>
         <p>And now his skin had grown loose with age; his
face, more wrinkled than a raisin, had fallen in by
reason of the lines in his cheeks. Less deep the
furrows cloven in the cornfield by the plough, the
folds wrought in the sails by the wind. Loathsome
grubs ate away his head and bare patches appeared
amid his hair. It was as though clumps of dry
barren com dotted a sun-parched field, or as if a
swallow were dying in winter sitting on a branch,
moulting in the frosty weather. Truly, that the
outrage to the consul's office might one day be the
greater, Fortune added to her gift of wealth this
brand upon his brow, this deformity of face. When
his pallor and fleshless bones had roused feelings
of revulsion in his masters' hearts, and his foul
complexion and lean body offended all who came
<pb id="v.1.p.149"/>
in contact with him, scaring children, disgusting
those that sat at meat, disgracing his fellow-slaves,
or terrifying as with an evil omen those that met
him; when his masters ceased to derive any advantage
from that withered trunk (for his wasted limbs
refused even to make the beds or cut wood for the
kitchen fire, while his faithless nature forbade their
entrusting him with the charge of gold or vesture
or the secrets of the house — who could bring him to
entrust his marriage-chamber to a pander?), then at
last they thrust him from their houses like a troublesome
corpse or an ill-omened ghost. He was now
free — for everyone despised him. So a shepherd
chains up a dog and fattens him with milk while
yet his strength avails to guard the flock and, ever
watchful, to scare away wolves with his barking.
</p>
         <p>But when later this same dog grows old and dirty
and droops his mangy ears he looses him, and, taking
off his collar, at least saves that.
</p>
         <p>Universal contempt is sometimes a boon. Driven
out by all, he could freely range amid every sort of
crime, and open a way for destiny. Oh thou,
whosoe'er thou art, that boldest sway in Olympus,
was it thy humour to make such mockery of mankind?
</p>
         <p>He who was not suffered to perform the
duties of a slave is admitted to the administration
of an empire; him whom a private house scorned
as a servant, a palace tolerates as its lord. When
first the consular residence received this old vixen,
who did not lament? Who grieved not to see an oft-
sold corpse worm itself into the sacred service of the
emperor? Nay, the very palace-servants, holding a
prouder rank in slavery, murmured at such a colleague
and long haughtily scorned his company.
<pb id="v.1.p.151"/>
See what manner of man they seek to connect with
the annals of Rome: the very eunuchs were ashamed
of him. At first of no account, he lay hid, the most
unknown unit of an unregarded throng, till thanks
to the mad folly of Abundantius 1 (who brought
ruin on the empire of the East and, ere that, upon
himself) he was advanced from the most menial
office to the highest honours. What a happy dispensation
of providence it is that in this world the
results of ill counsel fall first upon its instigators!
</p>
         <p>Thus the seer who advised Busiris to placate the
Thunderer's wrath, what time Nile's flood had long
run dry, with a stranger's blood himself first stained
that tyrant's altar with his own and fell a victim
of the horrid sacrifice he had advised. Thus he who
made the brazen bull and devised that new form of
torture, casting the deadly bronze as an instrument
of torment, was (at the bidding of the Sicilian tyrant)
the first to make trial of the unhanselled image,
and to teach his own bull to roar. So with Eutropius:
on no man's goods did he sooner seize than on those
of him by whom he had been raised to power;
none did he drive sooner into exile and thus, by the
condemnation of his patron, was to thank for one
righteous action.
</p>
         <p>When this half-man, worn out with age, had
been raised to that pinnacle of glory for which he
never would have dared to pray, of which never to
dream; when he had seen law at his feet, the heads
of the nobility inclined before him, and fortune heaping
such gifts upon one whose only hope and prayer
had been to gain his freedom, he straightway forgot
and banished three years later to Pity us, thanks to the
machinations of Eutropius.
<pb id="v.1.p.153"/>
his former masters, and his slave's mind swelled high
within him. The prisons were filled with degraded
nobles, Meroe and the plains of Ethiopia re-echoed
to the weeping of exiles; the desert rang with the
punishment of men; the temple of Jupiter Ammon
in Africa was stained with gentle blood.
</p>
         <p>Nothing is so cruel as a man raised from lowly
station to prosperity; he strikes everything, for he
fears everything; he vents his rage on all, that all
may deem he has the power. No beast so fearful as
the rage of a slave let loose on free-born backs;
their groans are familiar to him, and he cannot be
sparing of punishment that he himself has undergone;
remembering his own master he hates the
man he lashes. Being a eunuch also he is moved
by no natural affection and has no care for family
or children. All are moved to pity by those whose
circumstances are like their own; similitude of ills
is a close bond. Yet he is kind not even to eunuchs.
</p>
         <p>His passion for gold increases — the only passion
his mutilated body can indulge. Of what use was
emasculation? The knife is powerless against
reckless avarice. That hand so well practised in
petty thefts, accustomed to rifle a cupboard or
remove the bolt from the unwatched coffer, now
finds richer spoils and the whole world to rob. All
the country between the Tigris and Mount Haemus
he exposes for sale at a fixed price, this huckster of
empire, this infamous dealer in honours. This man
governs Asia for the which his villa has paid. That
man buys Syria with his wife's jewels. Another
repents of having taken Bithynia in exchange for
his paternal mansion. Fixed above the open doors
of his hall is a list giving the provinces and their
<pb id="v.1.p.155"/>
prices: so much for Galatia, for Pontus so much,
so much will buy one Lydia. Would you govern
Lycia? Then lay down so many thousands. Phrygia?
</p>
         <p>A little more. He wishes everything to be marked
with its price to console him for his own fortune and,
himself so often sold, he wants to sell everything.
</p>
         <p>When two are rivals he suspends in the balance
their opposed payment; along with the weight
the judge inclines, and a province hangs wavering
in a pair of scales.
</p>
         <p>Ye gods, are ye not ashamed that whole peoples
are sold beneath the hammer? At least let it
shame you of the seller, when a slave, a chattel the
law counts dead, possesses so many kingdoms and
retails so many cities. Did Cyrus' victory oust
mighty Croesus from his throne that Pactolus and
Hermus should roll their waves for a eunuch?
</p>
         <p>Did Attains make you, Rome, his heir, was Antiochus
confined within the appointed bounds of Taurus,
did Servilius enjoy a triumph over the hitherto
unconquered Isaurians, did Egypt fall before
Augustus, and Crete before Metellus, to ensure
Eutropius a sufficient income?1 Cilicia, Judaea,
Sophene, all Rome's labours and Pompey's triumphs,
are there to sell.
</p>
         <p>Why heap up these riches? Hast thou children
to succeed to them? Marry or be married, thou
canst never be a mother or a father: the former
nature hath denied thee, the latter the surgeon's
knife. India may enrich thee with enormous jewels,
Arabia with her spices, China with her silks; none so
needy, none so poverty-stricken as to wish to have
Eutropius' fortune and therewith Eutropius' body.
</p>
         <p>And now his mind, forgetful of its true nature and
<pb id="v.1.p.157"/>
drunken with riches, makes sport of wretched law
and the affairs of men. A eunuch is judge. Why
now wonder that he is consul? Whatever he does
is a prodigy. Can the annals of the law show cases
so mishandled? What age or what country has
ever witnessed a eunuch's jurisdiction? That
nought might remain undisgraced, nought unattempted,
he even makes him ready to outrage
arms, heaps portent on portent and wanton folly
seeks to outdo itself. Mars blushed, Bellona scoffed
and turned her from the disgrace of the East whene'er
with arrows strung and flashing quiver the aged
Amazon practises battle or hurries back as arbiter
of peace and war to hold parley with the Getae.
</p>
         <p>Our enemies rejoiced at the sight and felt that at
last we were lacking in men. Towns were set ablaze;
walls offered no security. The countryside was
ravaged and brought to ruin. Mid-ocean alone
gave hope. Women of Cappadocia were driven into
captivity across the river Phasis; stolen from the
stalls of their homesteads, the captive herds drink
the snowy streams of Caucasus, and the flocks
exchange the pastures of Mount Argaeus1 for the
woods of Scythia, Beyond the Cimmerian marshes,
defence of the Tauric tribes, the youth of Syria are
slaves. Too vast for the fierce barbarians are the
spoils; glutted with booty they turn to slaughter.
</p>
         <p>Yet Eutropius (can a slave, an effeminate, feel
shame? Could a blush grace such a countenance?),
Eutropius returns in triumph. There follow companies
of foot, squadrons like their general, maniples
of eunuchs, an army worthy Priapus' standards.
</p>
         <p>His creatures meet him and embrace their saviour
on his return.2 Great is his self-esteem; he struggles
<pb id="v.1.p.159"/>
to swell out his pendulous cheeks and feigns a heavy
panting; his lousy head dust-sprinkled and his face
bleached whiter by the sun, he sobs out some
pitiful complaint with voice more effeminate than
effeminacy's self and tells of battles. In tremulous
tones he calls his sister to witness that he has spent
his strength for his country's need; that he yields
to envy and cannot stand up against the storms of
jealousy and prays to be drowned in the foaming
seas. Would God his prayer had been granted!
</p>
         <p>Thus speaking, he wipes away the silly tears,
sighing and sobbing between each word; like a
withered old dame travelled far to visit her son's
daughter — scarce seated aweary and already she
asks for wine.
</p>
         <p>Why busy thy foul self with wars? Why attempt
battle on the bloody field? 'Tis to the arts of that
other Minerva thou shouldst apply thyself. The
distaff, not the dart should be thine; thine to spin
the thread, and, cunning craftsman that thou art,
to urge on the spinning-maids when lazy; thine
to wind the snowy wool for thy mistress' weaving.
</p>
         <p>Or, wouldst thou be a devotee, let Cybele, not Mars,
be the object of thy worship. Learn to imitate the
madness of the Corybantes to the accompaniment
of rolling drums. Thou may est carry cymbals,
pierce thy breast with the sacred pine, and with
Phrygian knife destroy what yet is left of thy
virility. Leave arms to men. Why seek to divide
the two empires and embroil loving brothers in
strife? Madman, remember thy former trade;
'twere more fitting thou shouldst endeavour to
reconcile them.
</p>
         <p>It is for deeds like this that Eutropius demands
<pb id="v.1.p.161"/>
this year of office, to ensure that by his efforts alone
he leaves nothing not dishonoured, ruining the army
as its general, the courts as their judge, the imperial
fasti as a consul.
</p>
         <p>No portent so monstrous but time past has given
it birth and the labour of bygone centuries produced
it. Legend tells us that Oedipus married his mother
and Thyestes his daughter; Jocasta bare brothers
to her husband, Thyestes's daughter gave birth to
her own brother. Athenian tragedy tells the sad
tale of Thebes and the baneful war of Troy. Tereus
was changed into a bird, Cadmus into a snake; Scylla
looked in amaze on the dogs that girt her waist.
</p>
         <p>Ancient story relates how one was transformed into
a tree and thus attached to earth, how another grew
wings and flew, how a third was clothed with scales
and yet another melted into a river. But no country
has ever had a eunuch for a consul or judge or general.
</p>
         <p>What in a man is honourable is disgraceful in an emasculate.
</p>
         <p>Here is an example to surpass all that is most
laughable in comedy, most lamentable in tragedy.
</p>
         <p>A pleasant sight in truth to see him strain his
sapless limbs beneath the weight of the toga, borne
down by the wearing of his consular dress; the
gold of his raiment rendered his decrepitude even
more hideous. 'Twas as though an ape, man's
imitator, had been decked out in sport with precious
silken garments by a boy who had left his back and
quarters uncovered to amuse the guests at supper.
</p>
         <p>Thus richly dressed he walks upright and seems the
more loathsome by reason of his brilliant trappings.
</p>
         <p>Dressed in white the senate, perhaps even his
master, 1 accompanies the dishonoured fasces. Behold
a portent! A lictor more noble than the
<pb id="v.1.p.163"/>
consul, and a man about to grant to others a liberty
which he has not yet himself won. He mounts the
lofty platform and amid a torrent of self-laudation
boasts of a prophetic dream he had in Egypt 1 and
of the defeat of tyrants which he foretold. No
doubt the goddess of war stayed her avenging hand
and waited till that emasculate Tiresias, that
unmanned Melampus, could crawl back with oracles
culled from farthest Nile.
</p>
         <p>Loud sang the prophetic birds in warning. The
year shuddered at the thought of bearing Eutropius'
name, and Janus proclaimed the madness of the
choice from his two mouths, forbidding a eunuch
to have access to his annals. Had a woman assumed
the fasces, though this were illegal it were nevertheless
less disgraceful. Women bear sway among the
Medes and swift Sabaeans; half barbary is governed
by martial queens. We know of no people who
endure a eunuch's rule. Worship is paid to Pallas,
Phoebe, Vesta, Ceres, Cybele, Juno, and Latona;
have we ever seen a temple built or altars raised to
a eunuch god? From among women are priestesses
chosen: Phoebus enters into their hearts; through
their voices the Delphian oracle speaks; none but
the Vestal Virgins approach the shrine of Trojan
Minerva and tend her flame: eunuchs have never
deserved the fillet and are always unholy. A woman
is born that she may bear children and perpetuate
the human race; the tribe of eunuchs was made for
servitude. Hippolyte fell but by the arrow of
Hercules; the Greeks fled before Penthesilea's
axe; Carthage, far-famed citadel, proud Babylon
with her hundred gates, are both said to have been
built by a woman's hand. What noble deed did
<pb id="v.1.p.165"/>
a eunuch ever do? What wars did such an one
fight, what cities did he found? Moreover, nature
created the former, the hand of man the latter,
whether it was from fear of being betrayed by her
shrill woman's voice and her hairless cheeks that
clever Semiramis, to disguise her sex from the
Assyrians, first surrounded herself with beings like
her, or the Parthians employed the knife to stop
the growth of the first down of manhood and forced
their boys, kept boys by artifice, to serve their lusts
by thus lengthening the years of youthful charm.
</p>
         <p>At first the rumour of Eutropius' consulship
seemed false and invented as a jest. A vague story
spread from city to city; the crime was laughed at
as one would laugh to hear of a swan with black
wings or a crow as white as privet. Thus spake
one of weighty character: <q direct="unspecified">If such things are
believed and swollen lies tell of unheard of monsters,
then the tortoise can fly, the vulture grow horns,
rivers flow back and mount the hills whence they
spring, the sun rise behind Gades and set amid the
Carmanians of India; I shall soon see ocean fit
nursery for plants and the dolphin a denizen of the
woods; beings half-men, half-snails and all the vain
imaginings of India depicted on Jewish curtains.</q>
         </p>
         <p>Then another adds, jesting with a more wanton
wit: <q direct="unspecified">Dost thou wonder? Nothing great is there
that Eutropius does not conceive in his heart. He
ever loves novelty, ever size, and is quick to taste
everything in turn. He fears no assault from the
rear; night and day he is ready with watchful
care; soft, easily moved by entreaty, and, even
in the midst of his passion, tenderest of men, he
never says 'no,' and is ever at the disposal even of
<pb id="v.1.p.167"/>
those that solicit him not. Whatever the senses
desire he cultivates and offers for another's enjoyment.
That hand will give whatever thou wouldest have. He
performs the functions of all alike; his dignity loves
to unbend. His meetings 1 and his deserving labours
have won him this reward,2 and he receives the consul's
robe in recompense for the work of his skilful hand.</q>
         </p>
         <p>When the rumour concerning this disgrace of the
eastern empire was known to be true and had
impressed belief on Roman ears, Rome's goddess
thus spake: <q direct="unspecified">Is Eutropius worthy of mine ire? Is
such an one fit cause for Roman grief?</q> So saying
the mighty goddess winged her way through the
heavens and with one stroke of her pinions passed
beyond the Po and approached the camp of her
emperor. It happened that even then the august
Honorius, assisted by his father-in-law Stilicho, was
making answer to the Germans who had come of
their own accord to sue for peace. From his lofty
throne he was dictating laws to the Cauci and giving
a constitution to the flaxen-haired Suebi. Over
these he sets a king, with those he signs a treaty
now that hostages have been demanded; others he
enters on the list as serviceable allies in war, so that in
future the Sygambrians will cut off their flowing locks
and serve beneath our banners. Joy and love so fill
the goddess' heart that she well nigh weeps, so great
is her happy pride in her illustrious foster-child. So
when a bullock fights in defence of the herd his mother
lifts her own horns more proudly; so the African
lioness gazes with admiration on her cub as he grows
to be the terror of the farmsteads and the future
king of beasts. Rome lays aside her veil of cloud and
towers above the youthful warrior, then thus begins.
<pb id="v.1.p.169"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>Examples near at hand testify to the extent
of my power now thou art emperor. The Saxon
is conquered and the seas safe; the Picts have
been defeated and Britain is secure. I love to see
at my feet the humbled Franks and broken Suebi,
and I behold the Rhine mine own, Germanicus.1
Yet what am I to do? The discordant East envies
our prosperity, and beneath that other sky, lo!
wickedness flourishes to prevent our empire's
breathing in harmony with one body. I make no
mention of Gildo's treason, detected so gloriously
in spite of the power of the East on which the rebel
Moor relied. For w hat extremes of famine did we not
then look? How dire a danger overhung our city, had
not thy valour or the ever-provident diligence of thy
father-in-law supplied corn from the north in place of
that from the south! Up Tiber's estuary there sailed
ships from the Rhine, and the Saône's fertile banks
made good the lost harvests of Africa. For me the
Germans ploughed and the Spaniards' oxen sweated;
my granaries marvel at Iberian corn, nor did my
citizens, now satisfied with harvests from beyond the
Alps, feel the defection of revolted Africa. Gildo, however,
paid the penalty for his treason as Tabraca can
witness. So perish all who take up arms against thee!
</p>
               <p>Lo! on a sudden from that same clime comes
another scourge, less terrible indeed but even more
shameful, the consulship of Eutropius. I admit I
have long learned to tolerate this unmanned tribe,
ever since the court exalted itself with Arsacid
pomp and the example of Parthia corrupted our
morals. But till now they were but set to guard
jewels and raiment, and to secure silence for the
imperial slumber. Never beyond the sleeping-
<pb id="v.1.p.171"/>
chamber did the eunuch's service pass; not their
lives gave guarantee of loyalty but their dull wits
were a sure pledge. Let them guard hidden store
of pearls and Tyrian-dyed vestments; they must
quit high offices of state. The majesty of Rome
cannot devolve upon an effeminate. Never have
we seen so much as a ship at sea obey the helm
in the hands of a eunuch-captain. Are we then so
despicable? Is the whole world of less account
than a ship? Let eunuchs govern the East by all
means, for the East rejoices in such rulers, let them
lord it over cities accustomed to a woman's sway:
why disfigure warlike Italy with the general brand
and defile her austere peoples with their deadly
profligacy? Drive this foreign pollution from out
the boundaries of manly Latium; suffer not this
thing of shame to cross the Alps; let it remain
fixed in the country of its birth. Let the river
Halys or Orontes, careless of its reputation, add
such a name to its annals: I, Rome, beg thee by
thy life and triumphs, let not Tiber suffer this
disgrace — Tiber whose way was to give the consulship
to such men as Dentatus and Fabius though
they asked not for it. Shall the Field of Mars witness
the canvassing of an eunuch? Is Eutropius to stand
with Aemilii and Camilli, saviours of their country?
Is thy office, Brutus, now to be given to a Chrysogonus
or a Narcissus 1? Is this the reward for giving
up thy sons to punishment and setting the citizen's
duty before the father's grief? Was it for this that
the Tuscans made their camp on the Janiculum and
Porsenna was but the river's span from our gates?
For this that Horatius kept the bridge and Mucius
braved the flames? Was it all to no purpose that
<pb id="v.1.p.173"/>
chaste Lucretia plunged the dagger into her bosom
and Cloelia swam the astonished Tiber? Were the
fasces reft from Tarquin to be given to Eutropius?
Let Hell ope her jaws and all who have sat in my
curule chair come and turn their backs upon their
colleague. Decii, self-sacrificed for your country's
good, come forth from your graves; and you, fierce
Torquati; and thou, too, great-hearted shade of poor
Fabricius. Serranus, come thou hither, if now thou
ploughest the acres of the holy dead and cleavest
the fallow lands of Elysium. Come Scipios, Lutatius,
famed for your victories over Carthage, Marcellus,
conqueror of Sicily, rise from the dead, thou
Claudian race, you progeny of Curius. Cato, thou
who wouldst not live beneath Caesar's rule, come
thou forth from thy simple tomb and brave the
sight of Eutropius. Immortal bands of Bruti and
Corvini, return to earth. Eunuchs don your robes
of office, sexless beings assume the insignia of Rome.
They have laid hands on the toga that inspired
Hannibal and Pyrrhus with terror. They now despise
the fan and aspire to the consul's cloak. No longer
do they carry the maidenly parasol for they have
dared to wield the axes of Latium.
Unhappy band, leave your womanly fastnesses,
you whom the male sex has discarded and the female
will not adopt. The knife has cut out the stings of
love and by that wounding you are pure. A mixture
are you of two ages — child and greybeard and nought
between. Take your seats, fathers in name alone.
Come new lords, come sterile senate, throng your
leader Eutropius. Fill the judgement-seat, not the
bedchamber. Change your habits and learn to follow
the consul's chair, not the woman's litter.
<pb id="v.1.p.175"/>
               </p>
               <p>I would not cite examples from remote antiquity
nor count the countless magistrates of past
history whom he thus outrages. But think how the
reverence due to all past ages will be impaired, on
how many centuries one man's shame will set its
mark. Amid the annals that record the name of
Arinthaeus,1 his master, will be found the slave,
and he will enter his own honours as equal to those
of his owner. The slaves of Egypt's kings have
ever been a curse to the world; behold I suffer
from a worse than Pothinus and bear a wrong more
flagrant than that of which Egypt was once the scene.
</p>
               <p>Pothinus' sword at Alexandria spilled the blood of a
single consul; 2 Eutropius brings dishonour on all.
</p>
               <p>If the fate of subjects cannot move thee, yet
have thou regard for princes, for your common cause,
and remove this stain on royalty. The consulship
is the sole office the emperor deigns to accept;
alternately the honour passes to Court and Senate.
Thou who hast thyself been four times consul spare
succeeding consuls this infamy. I pray thee, protect
the fasces, so often thine, from the pollution of a
eunuch's hand; let not the omens handed down in
our sacred books, let not those robes of mine wherewith
I have subdued everything within Ocean's
stream, be plunged in so great darkness and trodden
under foot. What kind of wars can we wage now
that a eunuch takes the auspices? What marriage,
what harvest will be fruitful? What fertility, what
abundance is possible beneath a consul stricken with
sterility? If eunuchs shall give judgement and
determine laws, then let men card wool and live like
the Amazons, confusion and licence dispossessing
the order of nature.
<pb id="v.1.p.177"/>
               </p>
               <p>What need of further words? Why, Stilicho, dost
thou delay to conquer because ashamed to fight?
Knowest thou not that the viler a foe the greater
the rejoicing at his overthrow? His defeat of the
pirates extended the fame of great Pompey; his
victory in the Servile War gave an added glory to
Crassus. Thou acceptest my charge: I recognize
the clamour that terrified the East and drove Gildo
and his Moors to their destruction. Why sound the
trump of war? No need to attack him with javelin
or spear. At the crack of the whip will be bowed
the back that has felt its blows. Even so when
after many years the Scythian army came back
from the wars and was met on the confines of its
native land by the usurping crowd of slaves who
sought to keep their returning masters from their
country; with displayed whips they routed the armed
ranks; back from its enterprise the familiar terror
drove the servile mob, and at threat of the lash the
bondsman's sword grew dull.</p>
            </q>
            <pb id="v.1.p.179"/>
         </p>
         <pb id="v.1.p.3" TEIform="pb"/>
         </div1>
               <div1 type="book" n="2" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                        <div2 type="poem" n="praef19" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <p>

The nobly born Eutropius who but lately wielded
the reins of supreme power once more fears the
familiar blows; and, soon to feel the wonted shackles
about his halting feet, he laments that his threats
against his masters have idly vanished. Fortune,
having had enough of her mad freak, has thrust
him forth from his high office and restored him to his
old way of life. He now prepares to hew wood with
axe other than the consular and is at last scourged
with the rods he once proudly carried. To the
punishment set in motion by him when consul he
himself as consul succumbed; the year that brought
him his robe of office brought him his exile. That
omen of evil augury for the people turns against
itself, the portent of that consulship brings ruin to
the consul. That name erased, our annals breathe
once more, and better health is restored to the
palace now that it has at last vomited forth its poison.
</p>
         <p>His friends deny him, his accomplices abandon him;
in his fall is involved all the eunuch band, overcome
not in battle, subdued not by strife — they may not
die a man's death. A mere stroke of the pen has
wrought their undoing, a simple letter has fulfilled
Mars' savage work.
<pb id="v.1.p.181"/>
The unsexed tyrant has been routed from out his
fastness in the women's quarters and, driven from
the bedchamber, has lost his power. Thus sadly,
when her lover's fidelity wavers and a former
favourite has been recalled, does a mistress leave
his house. With handfuls of dust he sprinkles his
scanty hairs and floods his wrinkles with senile
tears; as he Hes in humble supplication before the
altars of the gods his trembling voice seeks to soften
the anger of the women. His countless masters
gather around, each demanding back his slave,
useless except for chastisement. For loathsome
though he is and fouler in mind even than in face,
yet the very anger they feel against him will make
them pay; he is worth buying simply to punish.
</p>
         <p>What land or country wilt thou now visit, eunuch?
</p>
         <p>Here hate surrounds thee, there thy popularity is
fled; both courts have uttered thy condemnation
in either half of the world; never wert thou of the
West, now the East repudiates thee too. I
marvel that thou, blind Sibyl,1 who foretold'st the
fates of others, art silent about thine own. No
longer does fallacious Nile interpret thy dreams; no
longer, poor wretch, do thy prophets see visions.
</p>
         <p>What doth thy sister? Will she dare to embark with
thee and bear thee faithful company over the
distant seas? Mayhap she scorns the couch of an
impoverished eunuch, and now that she herself is rich
will not love thee who now art poor. Thou dost confess
thou wert the first to cut a eunuch's throat, but
the example will not secure thine own death. Live
on that destiny may blush. Lo! this is he whom so
many cities have held in awe, whose yoke so many
peoples have borne. Why lament the loss of that
<pb id="v.1.p.183"/>
wealth thy son shall inherit? In no other way
couldst thou have been father to an emperor.1 Why
insatiably weary heaven with a woman's plaints?
</p>
         <p>A haven of refuge is prepared for thee on the shores
of Cyprus. Thou hast plunged the world in war with
barbary; the sea, believe me, is safer than the land.
</p>
         <p>No longer wilt thou strike terror into the Armenians
with javelin and bow, no more scour the plain on thy
fleet charger. The senate of Byzantium has been
deprived of thy loved voice; uncertainty holds the
august assembly that is now deprived of thy counsels.
</p>
         <p>Hang up thy toga, retired consul; hang up thy quiver,
veteran soldier; return to Venus' service; that is thy
true calling. The pander's hand knows not to serve
Mars featly; Cytherea will right gladly take back
her slave. Dancing fills the island of Cyprus, home
of the happy loves; there purity commands no
respect. Paphian maidens gaze forth from the high
cliffs, anxious till the wave has brought thy bark safe
to land. Yet fear I lest the Tritons detain thee in
the deep to teach them how they may seduce the
sportive Nereids, or that those same winds which
hindered Gildo's flight may seek to drown thee in the
sea. Tabraca owes its fame to the overthrow of the
Moor; may Cyprus win prestige from thy shipwreck.
</p>
         <p>In vain will thy last breath be spent in calling on the
dolphin to carry thee to shore: his back bears only
men. 2 Hereafter should any eunuch attempt to
emulate thine actions let him turn his eye towards
Cyprus and abate his pride.
<pb id="v.1.p.185"/>
         </p>
         <pb id="v.1.p." TEIform="pb"/>
                        </div2>            
                        <div2 type="poem" n="20" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <p>

Ashes of Phrygia and you last remnants of the
ruined East (if any such remain), the augury was but
too true, too clear the threats of heaven: now that
the blow has fallen what use to learn the presagings of
this year of portents? The sailor is more cautious;
he foresees the violence of the North wind and hauls
in his canvas before the swelling storm. Of what
avail to acknowledge a mistake when his vessel is
already sunk? Can tears extenuate a crime? The
sinister auspices of your consul live on; the atonement
due to unmoved fate remains fixed. Ere the
deed was done you should have realized its horror;
you should have erased the blot ere it had dried.
</p>
         <p>When the body is overwhelmed by long-standing
disease 'tis all in vain that thou makest use of healing
medicines. When an ulcer has penetrated to the
marrow of the bones the touch of a hand is useless,
steel and fire must sane the place that the wound
heal not on the surface, like any moment to re-open.
</p>
         <p>The flame must penetrate to the quick to make a
way for the foul humours to escape; in order that,
once the veins are emptied of corrupted blood, the
<pb id="v.1.p.187"/>
fountain-head of the evil may be dried up. Nay,
even limbs are amputated to assure the healthy
Ufa of the rest of the body. Think you the Court
fitly cleansed by Eutropius' exile in Cyprus? The
world avenged by the banishment of a eunuch? Can
any ocean wash away that stain? any age bring
forgetfulness of so great a crime?
</p>
         <p>Ere yet he had donned the consul's robe there
came a rumbling from the bowels of the earth; a
hidden madness shook the subterranean caverns and
buildings crashed one on another. Chalcedon,
shaken to the foundations, tottered like a drunken
man, and Bosporus, straying from his course, flooded
the cities on his either bank. The shores of the strait
came together and the sailors once more had to avoid
the Clashing Rocks, torn from their foundation and
errant. Surely such presages were sent by the
sister deities of Styx, rejoicing that under this consul
at last all peoples were delivered into their hands.
</p>
         <p>Soon arose divers forms of ruin: here the fire-god
spread his flames; there Nereus, god of the sea,
brake his bounds. Here men's homes were burned,
there flooded. Ye gods, what punishment do ye hold
in store for the scoundrel whose rise to power was
marked by such portents? O'ercome us, Neptune,
with thy trident and overwhelm our defiled soil
along with all the guilt. One city we yield to the
Furies, a scapegoat for the sins of the world.
</p>
         <p>Once the way was open for portents, prodigies of
every sort hasted to disclose themselves. Rain of
blood fell, children of weird form were born and
offspring discordant with their breed. Statues wept,
not seldom the herds dared to speak, and wild beasts
braved an entrance into the city. Then seers raved
<pb id="v.1.p.189"/>
strangely and frenzied hearts were everywhere
ablaze, stirred by the fires of the dread god Phoebus.
</p>
         <p>Yet even had no god warned us, whose mind shall
be so dull as to doubt that the year of an emasculate
consul must be fatal to those lands? Blind folly
ever accompanies crime; of the future no account
is taken; sufficient for the day is its short-lived
pleasure; heedless of loss passion plunges into forbidden
joys, counting the postponement of punishment
a gain and believing distant the retribution
that even now o'erhangs. In face of such portents
I would not have entrusted Camillus' self with the
fasces, let alone a sexless slave (oh! the shame of
it!), to yield it to whom were, for men, a disgrace,
even though every oracle decreed it, and the insistent
deities gave pledges of prosperity.
</p>
         <p>Look back in the annals of crime, read o'er all
past history, unroll the volumes of Rome's story.
</p>
         <p>What can the Capri of Tiberius' old age, what can
Nero's theatre offer like to this? 1 A eunuch, clad
in the cloak of Romulus, sat within the house of
the emperors; the staled palace lay open to the
eager throng of visitors; hither hasten senators,
mingling with the populace, anxious generals and
magistrates of every degree; all are fain to be the
first to fall at his feet and to touch his hand; the
prayer of all is to set kisses on those hideous wrinkles.
</p>
         <p>He is called defender of the laws, father of the
emperor, and the court deigns to acknowledge a
slave as its overlord. Ye who come after, acknowledge
that it is true! Men must needs erect monuments
to celebrate this infamy; on many an anvil
groans the bronze that is to take upon it the form of
this monster. Here gleams his statue as a judge,
<pb id="v.1.p.191"/>
there as a consul, there as a warrior. On every side
one sees that figure of his mounted on his horse;
before the very doors of the senate-house behold a
eunuch's countenance. As though to rob virtue of
any place where she might sojourn undefiled, men
labour to befoul every street with this vile image.
</p>
         <p>May they rest for ever undisturbed, indisputable
proofs of our eternal shame; such is my prayer.
</p>
         <p>Beneath the statues one reads flattering titles and
praises too great even for men. Do they tell of
his noble race and lineage while his owners are still
alive? What soldier brooks to read that singlehanded
he, Eutropius, won great battles? Are
Byzas 1 and Constantine to be told that he is the
third founder of Rome? Meanwhile the arrogant
pander prolongs his revels till the dawn, stinking
of wine and scattering money amid the crowd to
buy their applause. He spends whole days of
amusement in the theatres, prodigal of another's
money. But his sister and spouse (if such a prodigy
can be conceived) wins the favour of Rome's matrons
by entertainments, and, like a chaste wife, sings the
praises of her eunuch husband. 'Tis her he loves,
her he consults on all matters of importance, be it of
peace or war, to her care he entrusts the keys of the
palace, as one would of a stable or empty house. Is
the guardianship of a mighty empire thus naught? Is
it thus he makes a mockery of a world's obedience?
</p>
         <p>Winter, passing into spring, had now felt the
returning warmth of Zephyrus' breezes and the
earliest flowers had oped their buds when, in the
lap of peace, they were preparing the annual journey
to thy walls, Ancyra. 'Twas Eutropius' device that
weariness of the sea 2 might not come upon him,
<pb id="v.1.p.193"/>
but a roaming summer might slide away in pleasure
journeys. But so magnificent was their return, you
would have imagined they brought conquered Persia
in their train and had drunk of the waters of Indus.
</p>
         <p>Look you! Mars, returning from the distant lands of
the yellow-haired Geloni, was re-seeking the lands
of Thrace in his bloody chariot. Pangaeus subsided
beneath his wheels, the mountain snows cried out
under his sounding axle. Scarce had the father
stayed on Haemus' summit and, reining in his
coursers, looked upon the toga-clad woman, when he
smiled a cruel smile and shook his gleaming crested
helm; then he addressed Bellona, implacable goddess,
who, her raiment all stained with blood, was
combing her snake-hair, fattened on the slaughter of
Illyrians.
</p>
         <p>Sister, shall we never succeed in curing the East of
effeminacy? Will this corrupt age never learn true
manliness? Argaeus yet reeks with those heaps of
dead Cappadocians not yet cold; Orontes is still pale
from misery. But they only remember evil while
they suffer it; give them a moment's respite and
all their slaughter fades from their minds unfelt;
little they reck of bloodshed that is past.
</p>
         <p>Seest thou this foul deed? Why veil thy face
with thine hair? See what crimes a short spell of
peace has wrought! what a curse has the sheathed
sword proved! The year that has known no war has
had a eunuch for its consul. The consulship would
have been at an end had a like spirit animated Italy;
this age-long office had fallen amid mockery and
no traces been left of its trampled rights, had not
Stilicho, heedful of the empire and of the character
and morals of a past age, banished from Tiber's city
<pb id="v.1.p.195"/>
this shameful name and kept Rome unsullied by an
unheard of crime. He has given us a harbour to
which the exiled majesty of Latium and the disgraced
fasces might retire; he has given us annals
wherein, abandoning the East, an age polluted with
servile stains might find a refuge.
</p>
         <p>
            <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>How like to its lord the inhabitants of the palace!
Turn your eyes to the city walls. Surely they at
least mutter disapprobation, though fear forbids
them speak out? Do they not condemn him in
their hearts? No: list the plaudits of the senate,
of the lords of Byzantium, of the Grecian citizens
of Rome. O people worthy of such a senate, senate
worthy of such a consul! To think that all these
bear arms and use them not, that manly indignation
reminds not of their sex those many whose thighs
bear a sword! Has my descendants' robe of office
sunk so low? Is Brutus' renown thus brought to
scorn?
</p>
               <p>Romulus, forgive thy sire for coming so tardy
an avenger of those outraged fasces. Right soon
will I make them pay for this joy with liberal tears.
Why delayest thou, Bellona, to sound the trumpet of
hell and to arm thyself with the scythe wherewith
thou mowest the people to the ground? Foment
discord, banish pleasures. I am aweary of the
devastation of Thrace and Macedon, of vengeance
twice wreaked on races already buried. Arouse less
accustomed destruction; spread fire and sword
beyond the seas, make a beginning of new devastation.
Seek not now thy foe on Riphaeus' heights:
what boots it to rouse the storm of war amid Caucasia's
ravines? Ostrogoths and Gruthungi together
inhabit the land of Phrygia; 'twill need but a touch
<pb id="v.1.p.197"/>
to precipitate them into revolt; readily does nature
return to her old ways. So be it. Since our soldiers'
valour is numbed and they have learned to obey an
unmanned master, let a stranger from the north
avenge our outraged laws and barbarian arms
bring relief to disgraced Rome.</p>
            </q>
         </p>
         <p>So spake he and thundered with his shield nigh as
loud as the ruler of the gods when he shakes his
aegis from out the lowering cloud. Athos replies,
Haemus re-echoes; again and again shaken Rhodope
repeats the hoarse uproar. Hebrus raised from out
the wondering waters his horns hoary with frost,
and bloodless Ister froze in fear. Then the god cast
his javelin,1 heavy with steel, and stiff with knotted
shaft, a mighty weapon such as none other god
could wield. The clouds part before its onset and
give it free passage; through the air it speeds o'er
seas and mountains by one mighty cast and comes
to earth amid the plains of Phrygia. The ground
felt the shock; Hermus blessed with Dionysus' vines
groaned thereat, Pactolus' golden urn shuddered,
all Dindymus bent his forest fleece and wept.
</p>
         <p>Bellona, too, hastens forth with speed no less than
that of Mars' whistling spear; a hundred ways of
hurt she pondered and at last approached Tarbigilus,2
fierce leader of the Getic squadron. It chanced he
had but late returned with empty hands from a
visit to Eutropius; disappointment and indignation
aggravated his ferocity, and poverty, that can incite
<pb id="v.1.p.199"/>
the gentlest heart to crime, inflamed his savage
breast. Taking upon her the similitude of his
wife she comes to meet him; proudly she steps forth
like the barbarian queen, clothed in linen raiment.
</p>
         <p>Close to her breast a brooch fastened her dress that
trailed behind her; she had bound her locks into a
coil that a polished circlet confined, and bidden her
green snakes turn to gold. She hastens to greet
him on his return and throws her snowy arms about
his neck, instilling the poison of the furies into his
soul by her kisses. Guilefully to stir his rage she
asks if the great man has been generous to him;
if he brings back rich presents. With tears he
recounts his profitless journey, his useless toil, the
pride and insults, moreover, which he had to bear
at the eunuch's hands. At once she seized the
favourable moment, and tearing her cheek with
her nails, discloses her complaints.
</p>
         <p>
            <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>Go then, busy thyself with the plough, cleave the
soil, bid thy followers lay aside their swords and
sweat o'er the harrow. The Gruthungi will make
good farmers and will plant their vines in due
season. Happy those other women whose glory is
seen in the towns their husbands have conquered,
they whose adornment is the spoils so hardly won
from an enemy, whose servants are fair captives
of Argos or Thessaly, and who have won them
slaves from Sparta. Fate has mated me with too
timid, too indolent a husband, a degenerate
who has forgotten the valour of Ister's tribes, who
deserts his country's ways, whom a vain reputation
for justice attracts, while he longs to live as a husbandman
by favour rather than as a prince by
plunder. Why give fair names to shameful weak-
<pb id="v.1.p.201"/>
ness? Cowardice is called loyalty; fear, a sense of
justice. Wilt thou submit to humiliating poverty
though thou bearest arms? Wilt thou weep unavenged,
though so many cities open to thee their
undefended gates?
</p>
               <p>Dost thou fear the consequences? Rome's old
way was to reward merit and vent on rebels a hate
that knew no bound. Now he who breaks a treaty
wins riches, while he who observes one lives in want.
The ravager of Achaea and recent devastator of
defenceless Epirus is lord of Illyria 1; he now enters
as a friend within the walls to which he was laying
siege, and administers justice to those whose wives
he has seduced and whose children he has murdered.
Such is the punishment meted out to an enemy,
such the vengeance exacted for wholesale slaughter
— and dost thou still hesitate? Hast thou regard
to the small numbers of thy followers? Nay, have
done with peace: war will give thee allies. Nor
would I urge thee so instantly hadst thou to face
men. It is another sex that is in arms against
thee; the world has entrusted itself to the protection
of eunuchs; 'tis such leaders the eagles
and standards of Rome follow. Time it is thou
didst return to a barbarian life; be thou in thy
turn an object of terror, and let men marvel at
thy crimes who despised thy virtues. Laden with
booty and plunder thou shalt be a Roman when it
pleases thee.</p>
            </q>
         </p>
         <p>So saying she suddenly changed into an ill-omened
bird, a loathsome sight with its hooked beak and
plumage blacker than Hell's darkness, and perched,
a sinister augury, on an old tomb.
</p>
         <p>So soon as repose from terror came to his freed
<pb id="v.1.p.203"/>
heart, and his stiffened hair sank down again, he
made all haste to carry out the commands of the
goddess. He told his followers all that he had seen
and urged them to follow him. Rebellious Barbary
had found a champion and openly threw off the
Latin yoke.
</p>
         <p>That part of Phrygia which lies towards the north
beneath the cold constellation of the Wain borders
on Bithynia; that towards the sunset on Ionia,
and that towards the sunrise on Galatia. On two
sides runs the transverse boundary of Lydia while
the fierce Pisidians hem it in to the south. All
these peoples once formed one nation and had
one name: they were of old called the Phrygians,
but (what changes does time not bring about?)
after the reign of a king Maeon, were known as
Maeones. Then the Greeks settled on the shores
of the Aegean, and the Thyni from Thrace cultivated
the region now called Bithynia. Not long since a
vast army of Gauls, nomad hitherto, came at last
to rest in the district; these laid by their spears,
clothed them in the civilized robe of Greece and
drank no longer from Rhine's, but from Halys',
waters. All antiquity gives priority to the Phrygian,
even Egypt's king had perforce to recognize it
when the babe, nourished at no human breast, first
opened his Ups to lisp the Phrygian tongue. 1
Here fell the pipe once hurled into the marshes
of Libya, what time the stream reflected Minerva's
disfigured countenance.2 Here, too, there perished,
conquered by Apollo's lyre, the shepherd Marsyas
whose flayed skin brought renown to the city of
<pb id="v.1.p.205"/>
Celaenae. Hence flow four broad auriferous rivers.
</p>
         <p>Small wonder that the waters in which King Midas
bathed so often glitter with the rare metal. Two flow
north, two southwards. Dindymus gives birth to
the river Sangarius, which, swollen by the clear
stream of the Gallus, hastens on to the Euxine, the
sea of the Amazon. The conjoined streams of
Marsyas and Meander make for the Icarian main
and Mycale's strand. Marsyas flows fast and straight
while his course is his own; mingled with thy waters.
</p>
         <p>Meander, he goes slowly — unlike the Saône whose
waters are hastened by the Rhone's inflowing.
</p>
         <p>Between these rivers is a sun-kissed plain; kindly
is it to the com, thick-set with vines and displaying
the fruit of the grey-green olive; rich, too, in horses,
fertile in flocks, and wealthy with the purple-veined
marble that Synnada quarries.
</p>
         <p>Such was Phrygia then when the gods allowed it
to be ravaged by Getic brigands. The barbarian
burst in upon those cities so peaceful, so easy of
capture. There was no hope of safety, no chance
of escape. Long and peaceful ages had made the
crumbling stones of their battlements to fall.
</p>
         <p>Meanwhile Cybele was seated amid the hallowed
rocks of cold Ida, watching, as is her wont, the
dance, and inciting the joyous Curetes to brandish
their swords at the sound of the drum, when, lo, the
golden-turreted crown, the eternal glory of her
blessed hair, fell from off her head and, rolling from
her brow, the castellated diadem is profaned in the
dust. The Corybantes stopped in amazement at
this omen; general alarm checked their orgies
and silenced their pipes. The mother of the gods
wept; then spake thus in sorrow.
<pb id="v.1.p.207"/>
            <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>This is the portent that agèd Lachesis foretold
long years ago. My fallen crown assures me that
Phrygia's final crisis is upon her. Alas for the blood
that shall redden Sangarius' waves; for all the
corpses that shall retard Meander's slow stream.
The hour is fixed irrevocably; such, long since, was
my son's, the Thunderer's, will. A like disaster
awaits the neighbouring peoples; in vain does
Lydia invoke the thyrsus of Bacchus in her defence.
Now fare thee well, land of Phrygia, farewell, walls
doomed to the flames, walls that now rear aloft
proud towers but will soon be levelled with the
ground and the bare earth. Farewell, dear rivers:
never more shall I hold my inspired revels in your
grottoes; no more shall my chariot leave the traces
of its wheels on Berecynthus' heights.</p>
            </q>
         </p>
         <p>So spake
she, and turned her drums to strains of mourning.
</p>
         <p>Attis filled his devoted country with holy lamentations
and Cybele's tawny lions burst into tears.
</p>
         <p>Eutropius, although this terrible revolt could not
be hid and although rumour had spread everywhere
the dread news, none the less affects to ignore it and
shuts his eyes to the empire's peril. 'Twas some
poor troop of wandering brigands; such wretches
call for punishment not war; a judge — so he brags
— not a general should crush their strength. Even
so the great Libyan bird, hard pressed by the cries
of its pursuers, runs o'er the burning sands and
flies through the dust, curving its wings like sails
to catch the breeze; but when it clearly hears
the footsteps close behind it, it forgets its flight,
standing with closed eyes and hiding its head,
believing, poor fool, it cannot be seen by those
whom itself cannot see. None the less Eutropius
<pb id="v.1.p.209"/>
sends towering promises with new gifts, if haply
his foe may pause at his entreaty. But the barbarian,
in whose heart was once waked the old love
of plunder, refuses to submit to a slave; for him
the gifts of fear have no charm; haughtily he
disdains any rank,1 even the highest, for under
such a consul what honour would not be disgrace?
</p>
         <p>When Eutropius saw that no prayers could move
him nor any gold win him over; when messenger
after messenger returned, his mission unfulfilled, and
all hopes of an alliance were at an end, he at last
recognized the necessity for war and summoned the
council to his palace. Thither they came — wanton
lads and debauched greybeards whose greatest
glory was gluttony, and whose pride it was to diversify
the outraged banquet. Their hunger is only
aroused by costly meats, and they tickle their palates
with foods imported from overseas, the flesh of the
many-eyed fowl of Juno,2 or of that coloured bird
brought from farthest Ind that knows how to speak.
</p>
         <p>Not the Aegean, not deep Propontis, not Maeotis'
lake afar can sate their appetites with fish. Perfumed
garments are their care, their pride to move
foolish laughter with their silly jests. On their
adornment and toilette they bestow a woman's care
and find even the silk they wear too heavy a burden.
</p>
         <p>Should the Hun, the Sarmatian, strike at the city's
gates yet trouble they for nought but the theatre.
</p>
         <p>Rome they despise and reserve their admiration
for their own houses — may Bosporus' waters overwhelm
them! Skilful dancers they and clever judges
of charioteers.
</p>
         <p>Some sprung from the dregs of the people are
generals; some magistrates — though their legs and
<pb id="v.1.p.211"/>
ankles are still scarred and livid with their wearing
of the fetters of servitude and though their branded
foreheads deny their owners' right to office and
disclose their true title. Among them Eutropius
holds the first place; Hosius, on whom he relies,
comes next. He of a truth is more popular, a
cunning artificer of justice who knows well how to
steam his cases; at times boiling with anger, yet
well able to render down that anger when aroused. 1
These sit enthroned, joint rulers of the eastern
empire, the one a cook the other a pander. The
backs of both are scarred with the whip, each was
a slave though of a different kind. The one had
been bought and sold a hundred times, the other
brought up a dependant in a Spanish household.
</p>
         <p>When, therefore, the chief men were gathered
together for consultation in this strait and to
comfort the sickness of the state, forthwith they
forget Phrygia and, setting aside the question of war,
start their accustomed fooling and engage in disputes
about the Circus. With heat as fierce as it is pointless
they wrangle what boy can best whirl quivering
limbs in an easy somersault or sweep the marble
floor with his drooping locks; who can most twist
his flanks into a boneless arch; who can best suit
his gestures to his words and his eyes to his character.
</p>
         <p>Some recite speeches from tragedy, others chant
the play of Tereus, others again that of Agave,
never before staged.
</p>
         <p>Eutropius chides them; the present moment,
says he, demands other spectacles than these;
it is war which now should claim all their care.
</p>
         <p>For his part (for he is an old man and a weary) it is
enough to defend the frontiers of Armenia; single-
<pb id="v.1.p.213"/>
handed he cannot cope with all these perils. They
must pardon his age and send younger men to the
war: — it is as though a hated forewoman were sitting
among a crowd of poor working-girls and bidding
them in her raucous voice ply the loom and gain
their livelihood, while they beg to be allowed the
enjoyment of a holiday, to lay aside their tasks and
visit their friends; angered at her refusal and
wearied of their work they crush the threads in their
hands and wipe away their gentle tears with the
cloth.
</p>
         <p>Sudden from out that trembling throng upleaps
bold Leo 1 with his vast bulk, he whose single prowess
Cyclopean hunger could scarce match, whom starving
Celaeno could not outvie. 'Tis to this fact that he
is said to have owed his name. Bold (when his
foe was absent), brave (as a speaker), great in bulk
but small of heart, once a highly skilled spinner
of thread and a cunning carder, none other could
so well cleanse the dirt from out the fleece and fill
the baskets, none other pull the thick wool over
the iron teeth of the comb as could he. He was
then Eutropius' Ajax and far and near he raged,
shaking not a huge shield compact of seven layers
of ox-hide, but that belly of his, laden with continuous
feastings, as he sat lazily among old dames
and distaffs. At length he arose and, panting,
said, <q direct="unspecified"> What unwonted sluggishness is this, my
friends? How long must we sit closeted in the
women's apartments and suffer our perils to increase
by reason of our sloth? Fate weaves for us a network
of ill while we waste our time in useless vows.
This difficult task demands my action; never was
my hand slow to use iron. Let but Minerva favour
<pb id="v.1.p.215"/>
mine attempts and the work begun will be the work
completed. Now will I render proud Tarbigilus,
whose madness has caused all this turmoil, of less
weight than a ball of wool, the faithless Gruthungi I
will drive before me like a flock of wretched sheep;
and when I have restored peace I will set the women
of Phrygia once more beside their ancient spinning.</q>
         </p>
         <p>So saying he sat down again. Great clamour
and applause filled the council-chamber, applause
such as rises from the rows of spectators in the
theatre when some curled youth impersonates
Niobe turned to stone, or Hecuba in tears. Straightway
Leo unfolds his banners and starts on the journey
whence there is to be no return. To the accompaniment
of the screech-owl's ill-omened cry he bids
march the host destined so soon to feed the vultures
of Mygdonia.
'Tis a well-favoured army, enamoured of the city's
shade, ever present at the games, anxious to shine
in the baths, not to bear sun-scorch and rain, and oh!
how different to that former army who, 'neath the
leadership of Stilicho, endured under arms the
frosts of Thrace and were wont to winter in the open
air and break with their axes the frozen waters of
Hebrus for a draught. Changed is the leader
and changed their character. Byzantium's luxury
and Ancyra's pomp 1 have destroyed their vigour.
</p>
         <p>No longer does the cavalry ride ahead of the foot;
suitable ground is not chosen for camps; no constant
change of sentries safeguards the ramparts, no
scouts are sent forward to discover which roads to
take or which to avoid; their evolutions are performed
without drill or discipline, in confusion they stray
hither and thither amid dark forests, along narrow
<pb id="v.1.p.217"/>
paths in unexplored valleys. So goes a horse that
has lost his rider, thus a ship whose helmsman
has been drowned is swept to the abyss, chance
guiding her and not the stars. So too the sea
monster 1 is dashed to pieces against the rocks
when it has lost the comrade fish that swam before
it and guided its course through the waves, piloting
the great beast with the motion of its tiny tail
according to the compact which is between it and
its huge companion. Aimlessly the monster swims
all unguided through the deep; then, surprised in
the shallow water and knowing not how to return to
the sea, pants and to no purpose dashes its gaping
jaws against the rocks.
</p>
         <p>Tarbigilus feigns retreat and raises the presumptuous
hopes of Leo, then suddenly he bursts all
unexpected upon the wine-sodden army, as, overcome
by the heavy feast, they brag over their cups
of leading the foe in chains. Some are slain as they
lift their sluggish limbs from the couch, others
know not any break between sleep and death.
</p>
         <p>Others rush pell-mell into a neighbouring swamp
and heap the marsh high with their dead bodies.
</p>
         <p>Leo himself, swifter than deer or antelope, fled
trembling on his foam-flecked horse, and it falling
under his weight Leo sank in the mire and on all
fours fought his way through the clinging slime.
</p>
         <p>Held up at first by the thick mud, his fat body
gradually settles down panting like a common pig,
which, destined to grace the coming feast, squeals
when Hosius arms him with flashing knife, and
gathers up his garments, pondering the while what
portions he will transfix with spits, which pieces of
the flesh he will boil and how much sea-urchin
<pb id="v.1.p.219"/>
stuffing will be needed to fill the empty skin. The
work of preparation goes on apace, Bosporus echoes
to many a blow and the savoury smell envelops
Chalcedon.
</p>
         <p>Suddenly a gentle breeze stirs the foliage behind
Leo's back. He thinks it an arrow, and terror,
taking a missile's place, does duty for a wound.
</p>
         <p>Untouched and stricken only by fear he breathes
his last. Degenerate Roman, by whose advice didst
thou exchange the comb for the sword, thine
ancestral calling for the field of battle? How
much better to praise in safety the work of the
weavers at their looms and keep out. the cold by
means of morning feasts. Here thou hast suffered
a wretched death; here, while thou soughtest to
shirk thy spinning, the Fates have at last spun for
thee the final thread.
</p>
         <p>Now spreading rumour shakes the palace, pale
with terror upon terror. It told how that the army
was destroyed, the troops butchered, the plain of
Maeonia red with slaughter, Pamphylia and Pisidia
o'errun by the enemy. On all sides rings the
dread name of Tarbigilus. He is now said to be
bearing down upon Galatia, now to be meditating
an attack on Bithynia. Some say he has crossed
the Taurus and is descending upon Cilicia, others
that he has possessed himself of a fleet and is
advancing both by land and sea. Truth is doubled
by panic's fancy; they say that from the ships
far cities are seen ablaze, that the straits are aglow
and that ashes driven by the wind catch in the sails
of every ship at sea.
</p>
         <p>Amid all this confusion comes a yet more terrible
<pb id="v.1.p.221"/>
rumour — that Babylon is again in arms and, under a
new monarch, 1 threatens our Empire; the Parthians,
long inactive, and now scorning slothful ease, seek
to put an end to the peace imposed by Rome.
</p>
         <p>Rare among the Medes is the murder of a king, for
punishment falls on the regicide's whole family.
</p>
         <p>Thus equal obedience is offered to their overlords,
cruel as well as kind. But what would not the year
of Eutropius' consulship dare? 'Tis that has stricken
down our faithful ally Sapor and roused the Persians'
swords against their own king; that has cast
the torch of the Furies across the Euphrates, there
to kindle rebellion, that no quarter of the globe
may escape carnage.
</p>
         <p>Then indeed men's hearts failed them, their courage
ebbed away amid all these storms; surrounded
as they were on every side by the din of war, at
last they recognized the wrath of heaven and their
consul's evil omen, learning too late — schooled by
the stubborn issue — their now irrevocable doom.
</p>
         <p>They say that the twin sons of Iapetus formed our
first parents of the same materials but with unequal
skill. Those whom Prometheus fashioned, and with
whose clay he mingled abundant ether, foresee
the distant future and, thanks to their more careful
making by a better workman, are thus prepared
to meet what fate has in store for them. Those
framed of baser clay by the sorry artificer the Greek
poets so well call Epimetheus, men through whose
limbs no ethereal vigour spreads — these, like sheep,
cannot avoid the dangers that o'erhang them,
nor foresee aught. Not till the blow has fallen do
they protest and weep too late the accomplished
deed.
<pb id="v.1.p.223"/>
There now shone forth but one hope of salvation
— Stilicho. Him the expectation of whose visits
the consciousness of deeds ill-done had ever rendered
bitter and unpleasant, him whose approach even as
far as the Alps afflicted the Byzantines with fear of
death and punishment, all now wish to come, repentant
of their former wrongdoing. To him they
look as to a star amid this universal shipwreck of
war; to him innocent and guilty alike address their
prayers. So children whose sire carries merchandise
across the sea, wrapt up in their amusements and
heedless of their studies, wander afield more joyfully
now that their guardian is absent, yet, should a
dangerous neighbour invade their defenceless home
and seek to drive them forth unprotected as they
are from their fireside, then they beg their father's
help, call upon his name with useless cries and
all to no purpose direct their gaze towards the
shore.
</p>
         <p>All admit that they deserve punishment and
death for deserting Stilicho and entrusting themselves
to the governance of slaves. Long they stood
dazed with altered thoughts, and as their senses
slowly return they marvel at the results of their
own madness and turn away their eyes; flinging
down his rods the lictor shudders, and the dishonoured
axes fall of their own accord. Even so
the Maenads returning to Thebes from the Aonian
mount, their thyrses dripping with Pentheus' blood,
learning the true character of their dreadful hunting
and seeing the head cast by the mother herself,
hide them in the darkness and lament the end of
their madness. Thereupon suppliant Aurora turned
her flight towards powerful Italy, her hair no
<pb id="v.1.p.225"/>
longer aureole-crowned and she no more bright of
countenance nor clothed with the saffron of the dawn.
</p>
         <p>She stands wan with woe, even as when she buried
Memnon in his Phrygian grave. Stilicho recognized
her and stayed, well knowing the reason of her visit.
</p>
         <p>Long time she clasped his victorious hand and at
length amid tears and sighs addressed him.
<q direct="unspecified">Why art thou so wearied of the world whereon
I shine? Leavest thou me thus to be the sport and
laughing-stock of slaves and carest only for Italy,
thou that wert once my guide and my leader?
Since thy victory over the tyrant Eugenius I have
not seen thee. Has victory thus robbed me of
thee and given thee to Gaul? Rufinus was the
prime cause of the trouble; 'twas he who wrought
disunion between the two empires. But when he
aimed at more there met him an army returning in
righteous wrath, an army still strong, still mindful
of its former prowess. For a moment I was dazzled
by the mirage of liberty: I hoped that Stilicho
would once more hold the reins of our empire. Alas
for my short-sighted happiness! The world had
begun to form one single empire under the rule
of the two brothers (for who, with the awful example 1
so fresh in his mind, would dare embark upon a
like venture?) when suddenly (it is a monstrous
story which scarce bears the telling) a eunuch came
forward as Rufinus' heir. Thus fortune brought
back my former miseries with this one difference —
that of changing my master's sex.
At first he kept his crimes hidden behind the
doors of his chamber, an unseen and timid ruler;
power was his that all envied, yet only a eunuch's,
nor dared he yet arrogate to himself the right of
<pb id="v.1.p.227"/>
governing the state or of trampling on the laws.
But when he had banished the good and, retaining
the dregs of the people, had chosen therefrom
advisers of no worth; when his creature Hosius
stood on his one side and Leo on the other, then
indeed his self-confidence waxed and his lust for
power broke forth into open flame. Patrician and
consul he brought defilement on the honours he
sold; even greater defilement on those he carried
himself. The very standards and trumpets of war
grew feeble; a palsy seized upon our swords.
What wonder the nations rejoiced and we became
the easy prey of any who would subdue us? Gone
are ploughs and ploughmen; the East is more a desert
than Thrace and snowy Haemus. Alas! how many
cities, how long unused to war's alarms, have perished
in a single invasion! Not long since a mounted band
coming from Araxes' farthest banks threatened the
walls of Antioch and all but set fire to the chief city
of the fair province of Syria. Laden with spoil and
rejoicing in the vast carnage it had wrought the band
returned with none to bar its passage; now it
pursues its victorious career inflicting on me wound
upon wound. 'Tis not now Caucasus nor cold Phasis
that send forces against me; wars arise in the very
centre of my empire. Time was when the Gruthungi
formed a Roman legion; conquered we gave them
laws; fields and dwelling-places we apportioned
them. Now they lay waste with fire Lydia and
the richest cities of Asia, ay, and everything that
escaped the earlier storm. 'Tis neither on their
own valour or numbers that they rely; it is our
cowardice urges them on, cowardice and the treason
of generals, through whose guilt our soldiers now
<pb id="v.1.p.229"/>
flee before their own captives, whom, as Danube's
stream well knows, they once subdued; and those
now fear a handful who once could drive back all.
Meanwhile the palace devotes its attention to
dances and feastings, and cares not what be lost so
something remain. But lest our salesman lose
aught by this dismemberment of the empire he
has divided each remaining province into two, and
forces the two halves, each under its own governor,
to compensate him for the loss of other provinces.
'Tis thus they give me back my lost peoples: by
this ingenious device they increase the number of
my rulers while the lands they should rule are lost.
In thee is now my only hope; in place of
Minerva's supplicating branch I offer thee my tears.
Help me in my distress. Save me from this tyranny
of a slave master; do not condemn all for the fault
of a few, and let not a recent offence cancel
former merits. Grant me now my request; extreme
danger ever exonerates from blame. Camillus, though
justly angered at his banishment, forebore not to
succour his country when in flames. I seek not to
draw thee away from Italy; thou art enough
defence for both empires. Let both have the benefit
of thine illustrious arms; let the same shield defend
us and one hero work the salvation of a twofold
world.</q>
            <pb id="v.1.p.231"/>
         </p>
                                 </div2>
                        </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>