<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 38</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="book">
                <head>Arraignment of Scipio Africanus</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst the war was going on in Asia, even
                        Aetolia did not remain free from disturbance. The Athamanians were the cause
                        of the trouble. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After the expulsion of
                        Amynander, the country was held down by the governors whom Philip had
                        established and provided with troops, and their arbitrary and lawless rule
                        made the people feel keenly the disappearance of their king. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> He was spending his time of exile in Aetolia, and
                        the letters of his friends and their description of the condition of
                        Athamania led him to hope that he might recover his crown. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> He sent messengers to Argithea, their capital, to
                        inform their leaders that if he were fully assured of the sympathies of his
                        compatriots, he would obtain assistance from the Aetolians and enter the
                        country with the members of the Aetolian council and their captain-general,
                        Nicander. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When he saw that they were
                        prepared for all eventualities, he told them at very short notice the day on
                        which he intended to enter Athamania with an army. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The movement against the Macedonians was begun by four
                        men; they each selected six comrades, then feeling no confidence in so small
                        a number, which was more adapted to conceal than to execute their project,
                        they doubled the number of their fellow-conspirators. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Having thus grown to fifty-two, they formed themselves
                        into four parties; one was to make for Heraclea, a second for Tetraphylia
                        where the royal treasure used to be kept, the third was to go to Theudoria,
                        and the fourth to Argithea. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They had all
                        agreed to show themselves in the forums without making any disturbance, as
                        though they had come on private business, and on a fixed day they were to
                        raise the populations in the different cities and expel the Macedonian
                        garrisons from their citadels. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When the
                        day came and Amynander was on the frontier with 1000 Aetolians, the
                        Macedonian garrisons were simultaneously driven out of the four cities, and
                        letters were sent to all the other cities urging them to shake themselves
                        free from the tyranny of Philip and win back their ancestral and legitimate
                        monarchy. The Macedonians were expelled from all parts of the country.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Xeno, the commandant of the garrison
                        in Theium, intercepted the message sent to that city, and by seizing the
                        citadel was able to stand a siege for a few days. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> At last that place, too, surrendered to Amynander, and
                        the whole of Athamania, with the exception of the fort of Athenaeum, which
                        lay close to the frontier of Macedonia, was now in his power. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On hearing of the revolution in Athamania,
                        Philip started off with a force of 6000 men, and after an extraordinarily
                        rapid march arrived at Gomphi. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Here he
                        left the greater part of his army, who were unable to keep up such long
                        marches, and went on with 2000 men to Athenaeum, the one place that had been
                        retained by his troops. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> From here he tried
                        to secure some of the places nearest to him, but he soon found that they
                        were all hostile, and accordingly he returned to Gomphi. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Re-entering Athamania with the whole of his force, he
                        sent Xeno forward with 1000 infantry to seize Ethopia, a good position for
                        commanding Argithea. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When Philip saw that
                        his men were in occupation of the place, he encamped near the temple of
                        Jupiter Acraeus. Here he was detained a whole day by a terrible storm; the
                        next day he decided to advance against Argithea. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst his men were on the march they suddenly caught
                        sight of the Athamanians running up to some high ground which commanded
                        their line of march. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At this sight the
                        leading ranks halted and there was confusion throughout the column, as the
                        men all asked themselves what would happen if the column went down into the
                        valley where it was commanded by those heights. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Philip wanted to push rapidly through the pass, but the
                        confusion that had been caused compelled him to recall the head of the
                        column and order them to counter-march along the way they had come.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At first the Athamanians followed them
                        quietly at some distance, but when the Aetolians had joined them, they left
                        it to them to harass the enemy's rear while they themselves closed in on
                        their flank, and some making a short cut through country they were familiar
                        with, seized the head of the pass. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                        confusion amongst the Macedonians was such that their recrossing of the
                        river resembled a precipitate flight rather than an orderly march, and they
                        left many men and arms behind. Here the pursuit stopped and the Macedonians
                        got back safely to Gomphi and from there withdrew into Macedonia. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> The Athamanians and Aetolians mustered from all
                        sides round Ethopia with the object of expelling Xeno and his 1000
                        Macedonians. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Feeling their position to be
                        insecure they left Ethopia and took up a position on higher and more
                        precipitous ground. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Athamanians,
                        however, found out the approaches, attacked them from several different
                        points and drove them from the heights. Scattered in flight and unable to
                        find their way through pathless thickets and over rocky ground with
                            <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> which they were unfamiliar, they
                        were killed or made prisoners, many in their panic fell down the cliffs, and
                        only a very few succeeded in making their escape with Xeno to the king.
                        Subsequently a truce was arranged for the burial of those who had fallen.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> His crown recovered, Amynander sent a
                        delegation to the senate and another to the Scipios, who were staying at
                        Ephesus after the battle with Antiochus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        He asked to be allowed to remain on a peaceful footing with Rome, and in
                        excusing himself for having sought the aid of the Aetolians in winning back
                        his ancestral throne, threw the whole responsibility for the war on Philip.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> From Athamania the Aetolians marched
                        into Amphilochia, and the voluntary surrender of the majority of the
                        population made them masters of the whole country. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> After recovering Amphilochia which had formerly
                        belonged to them, they invaded Aperantia, hoping for equal success, and this
                        State also to a large extent surrendered without offering any resistance.
                        The Dolopians had never been under Aetolia; they had formed part of Philip's
                        dominions. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At first they flew to arms, but
                        when they learnt that the Amphilochians had joined the Aetolians, that
                        Philip had fled from Athamania and his force had been cut up, they too
                        revolted from him and joined the Aetolians. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> With these States all round them, the Aetolians considered themselves
                        secure on every side from the Macedonians. But in the midst of their
                        security they received intelligence of the defeat of Antiochus at the hands
                        of the Romans in Asia, and not long after, their envoys returned from Rome
                        bringing no hope of peace and announcing that the consul Fulvius had already
                        landed in Greece with an army. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Appalled at
                        these tidings they begged Rhodes and Athens to send delegates to Rome so
                        that with the support of these friendly nations their own petitions which
                        had been lately rejected might find readier access to the ear of the senate.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They then sent their leaders to Rome
                        as their last hope, having taken no precautions to avoid war until the enemy
                        was almost in sight. M. Fulvius had now brought his army up to Apollonia and
                        was consulting the Epirot leaders as to where he should open the campaign.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They thought the best course would be
                        to begin with an attack on Ambracia, which had by that time joined the
                        Aetolian League. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They pointed out that if
                        the Aetolians came to its relief, the open and level country afforded a
                        favourable field of battle; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> if they
                        avoided an engagement, the siege would be by no means a difficult one as
                        there was abundance of timber in the neighbourhood for constructing the
                        raised galleries and all the other siege works; the Aretho, a navigable
                        river and well adapted for transporting all necessary materials, flowed past
                        the very walls; and in the last place, summer, the season for active
                        operations, was approaching. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Induced by these considerations the consul
                        advanced through Epirus, but when he came to Ambracia he saw that its siege
                        would be a serious undertaking. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Ambracia
                        lies at the foot of a rugged eminence which the natives call Perranthes.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The city on the side where the wall
                        skirts the river and the plain looks to the west; the citadel built on the
                        hill lies to the east. The Aretho, which rises in Athamania, falls into the
                        gulf named after the city-the Ambracian Gulf. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> In addition to the protection afforded by the river on
                        the one side and the hill on the other, the city was enclosed by a strong
                        wall more than four miles in circumference. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> Fulvius constructed two entrenched camps at a short distance from each
                        other in the direction of the plain and one fort on a height over against
                            <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> the citadel, and made preparations
                        for connecting the whole by a rampart and fosse, so that those shut up in
                        the city would not be able to leave it, nor would it be possible to
                        introduce succours from outside. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the
                        news of the siege of Ambracia reached them, the Aetolian national council
                        assembled at Stratus, on the summons of Nicander, their captain-general.
                        Their first intention was to march thither with all their forces and raise
                        the siege, but when they found that a great part of the city was already
                        invested and that the Epirot camp was fixed on the level ground the other
                        side the river, they divided their forces. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Eupolemus with 1000 light infantry succeeded in entering the city at a point
                        where the lines were not yet closed. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Nicander intended to make a night attack with the rest of the troops upon
                        the Epirot camp, as the Romans would find it difficult to come to their
                        assistance with the river between them. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        On second thoughts, however, the risk seemed too great in case the Romans
                        took the alarm and endangered his retreat, so he marched away and ravaged
                        Acarnania. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The lines of investment were at length
                        closed and the siege works which the consul was preparing to bring up
                        against the walls completed. He now commenced an assault from five different
                        points. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On the side of the city
                        overlooking the plain where the approach was easiest he brought up three
                        siege-engines, at equal distances from each other, at a place called the
                        Pyrrheum, another near the Aesculapium, and the fifth against the citadel.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As he shook the walls with the
                        battering-rams and sheared off the parapet by scythe blades fixed on long
                        poles the defenders were dismayed at the sight and at the terrific noise of
                            <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> the blows delivered by the rams, but
                        when they saw that the walls were still standing, their courage revived and
                        they hammered the rams by means of swing beams with heavy masses of lead,
                        large stones and stout beams of wood; they dragged with iron grapples the
                        poles with the scythe blades inside the walls and broke off the blades.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Their night attacks on the parties
                        guarding the engines, and sorties by day against the outposts, spread alarm
                        on the other side. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> While this was the
                        state of things in Ambracia the Aetolians had returned from their plundering
                        raid to Stratus. Here Nicander hit upon a bold stroke by which he hoped to
                        raise the siege. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> His intention was to
                        introduce a certain Nicodamus into the city with 500 Aetolians, and he fixed
                        the night and the hour at which an attack was to be made from the city on
                        the hostile works directed against the Pyrrheum whilst he himself threatened
                        the Roman camp. By this double attack, all the more alarming because made in
                        the night, he hoped to secure a brilliant success. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Nicander moved forward in the dead of the night and
                        after passing some of the advanced posts unobserved and forcing his way
                        through others by a determined onslaught, climbed over the lines connecting
                        the different works and penetrated into the city. His arrival raised the
                        hopes of the besieged and emboldened them to attempt any adventure however
                        hazardous. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When the appointed night
                        arrived he made a sudden attack on the works. His attempt did not meet with
                        a corresponding success, for no attack was made from outside, either because
                        the Aetolian commander was afraid to move or because he deemed it more
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> important to carry assistance to
                        the Amphilochians, who had been lately won over and whom Philip's son
                        Perseus, who had been sent to recover Dolopia and Amphilochia, was attacking
                        with his utmost strength. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As stated above, the Roman engines were
                        directed against the Pyrrheum at three separate points, and against each of
                        these the Aetolians were making simultaneous attacks, though not with the
                        same weapons or the same force. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Some went
                        up with lighted torches, others carried tow and pitch and fire-darts; the
                        whole of their line was lit up by the flames. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> At the first onset they overwhelmed many of the guards;
                        then when the noise of the tumult and clamour reached the camp, the consul
                        gave the signal and the Romans, seizing their weapons, poured out of all the
                        gates to help their comrades. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Only at one
                        point was there a real fight between sword and fire; at the two others the
                        Aetolians after attempting, rather than sustaining, a conflict retreated
                        without effecting anything. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A desperate
                        struggle raged in one quarter; here the two generals, Eupolemus and
                        Nicodamus, at the head of their respective divisions urged on the combatants
                        and encouraged them with the almost certain hope of Nicander's coming up as
                        he had promised and taking the enemy in the rear. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> This hope for some time kept up their spirits, but when
                        they failed to receive the agreed signal from their comrades and found that
                        the numbers of the enemy were increasing, their courage waned and at last
                        they gave up the attempt, and finding their retreat almost cut off, fled in
                        disorder back to the city. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They succeeded,
                        however, in setting some of the siege-works on fire after losing
                        considerably more than they had themselves killed of the enemy. If the
                        preconcerted plan of operations had been successful, there is no doubt that
                        at least one section of the siege-works would have been carried with a great
                        slaughter of the Romans. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Ambracians
                        and Aetolians in the city not only abandoned all further attempts that
                        night, but during the remainder of the siege showed themselves much less
                        enterprising, as they felt they had been betrayed. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> No more sorties were made against the enemy's posts;
                        they confined themselves to fighting in comparative safety from the walls
                        and towers. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Perseus heard that the Aetolians were
                        approaching, he raised the siege of the city which he was attacking and,
                        after devastating their fields, left Amphilochia and returned to Macedonia.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Aetolians, too, were called away
                        by the ravages which were being committed on their sea-board. Pleuratus,
                        king of the Illyrians, had sailed into the Gulf of Corinth with sixty ships,
                        reinforced by the Aetolian vessels from Patrae, and was devastating the
                        maritime districts of Aetolia. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A force of
                        1000 Aetolians was despatched against him and by taking direct roads they
                        were able to meet him at <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> whatever point
                        his fleet had, in its cruising in and out of the indented coast, tried to
                        effect a landing. At Ambracia the Romans had battered down the walls in
                        several places and partially laid bare the city, but they could not force
                        their way into it. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As fast as the wall was
                        destroyed a new one was raised in its place and the citizens stood in arms
                        on the fallen masonry to bar all approach. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Finding that he was making very little progress by direct assault, the
                        consul decided to construct a secret passage underground after first
                        covering the place whence it started with vineae. Working day and night they
                        succeeded for a considerable time in escaping the observation of the enemy,
                        not only whilst they were digging but also whilst carrying away the earth.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Suddenly the sight of a conspicuous
                        mound of soil gave the townsmen an indication of what was going on. To avert
                        the danger of the wall being undermined and a way into the city being thrown
                        open, they began to run a trench inside the wall in the direction of the
                        place covered with vineae. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When they had
                        excavated as low as the bottom of the secret passage would probably be, they
                        remained perfectly silent, and by placing their ears <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> against different places in the side of the trench they
                        caught the sound of the enemy diggers. As soon as they heard this they broke
                        through straight into the tunnel. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> There
                        was no difficulty in doing this, for they quickly found themselves in an
                        open space where the wall had been underpinned with timber props by the
                        enemy.1 As the trench and tunnel now opened into one another the two parties
                        of diggers commenced a fight with their digging tools. Very soon armed
                        bodies came up on both sides and an underground battle began in the dark.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The besieged closed up the tunnel in
                        one place by stretching a screen of goats' hair across and improvising
                        barricades, and they adopted a novel device against the enemy which was
                        small but effective. A hole was bored through the bottom of a cask in which
                        an iron pipe was inserted. and an iron cover perforated with several holes
                        was prepared to fit the other end. The cask was then filled with light
                        feathers, the cover fastened on, and through the holes some long spears-the
                        so-called "sarissae"-were inserted to keep off the enemy. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> The cask was now placed with its head towards the
                        tunnel and a light was placed amongst the feathers which were blown into a
                        blaze by a pair of smith's bellows inserted in the pipe. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> The tunnel was soon filled with a dense smoke, rendered
                        all the more pungent from the horrid smell of the burning feathers, and
                        hardly a man could endure it. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst this was the state of things in
                        Ambracia, the Aetolians decided to open negotiations with the consul. In
                        view of the fact that on one side Ambracia was undergoing a siege, on
                        another the coast was being threatened by a hostile fleet, whilst on the
                        third side <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> Amphilochia and Dolopia were
                        being harried by the Macedonians, and that the Aetolians were not strong
                        enough to confront their various enemies collectively, the captain-general
                        convened a meeting of the Aetolian League and consulted the national leaders
                        as to what was to be done. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They were
                        unanimously of opinion that they must sue for peace, on equal terms, if
                        possible; failing that, on any terms, if they were not intolerable.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was in reliance upon Antiochus,
                        they said, that they had undertaken the war; now that Antiochus had been
                        worsted both on land and sea and driven beyond the Taurus almost to the ends
                        of the world, what hope was there of sustaining the war? <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Phaeneas and Damoteles must take such steps as they
                        thought best in the interests of Aetolia, and consistent with their own
                        honour, for what counsel, what choice had their fortunes left them?
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Furnished with these instructions, the
                        envoys implored the consul to spare the city and to take pity on a nation
                        which had once been an ally and had been driven to madness-they would not
                        say by their wrongs, but at all events, by the wretched conditions under
                        which they lived. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The punishment they
                        deserved for their share in the war with Antiochus ought not to outweigh the
                        services they had rendered in the war against Philip. At that time no great
                        gratitude had been shown them; they ought not now to pay an excessive
                        penalty. The consul told them in reply that the Aetolians had frequently
                        asked for peace, but seldom with the honest intention of keeping it. They
                        must follow the example of Antiochus whom they had dragged into the war.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He had ceded not only those few cities
                        whose liberty had been the cause of quarrel, but the whole of Asia on this
                        side the Taurus-a rich and fertile realm. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        He, the consul, would not listen to any proposals unless the Aetolians laid
                        down their arms. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They must first give up
                        their arms and all their horses; then they must pay 1000 talents; half the
                        sum to be paid down at once, if they wished to have peace. And in addition
                        to these terms it must be stipulated in the treaty that they would have the
                        same friends and the same enemies as Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The envoys felt these to be onerous terms,
                        and as they knew the fierce and fickle temper of their countrymen they left
                        without giving any decided answer. They wished to discuss the whole position
                        thoroughly with the captain-general and the national leaders and come to
                        some decision as to what ought to be done. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        They were received with clamorous protests and reproaches. "How long," they
                        were asked, "were they going to let matters drag on after receiving definite
                        orders to bring back peace at any price?" Their return journey to Ambracia
                        was a disastrous one. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Acarnanians with
                        whom they were at war had posted an ambush close to the road on which they
                        were travelling; they were made prisoners and conducted to Tyrrhenum for
                        safe keeping. This interrupted the peace negotiations. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The delegates who had been sent from Athens and Rhodes
                        to support the Aetolians were already with the consul, when Amynander, who
                        had obtained a safe-conduct, arrived in the Roman camp. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> He was more concerned for the city of Ambracia, where
                        he had passed most of his years of exile, than for the Aetolians. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> When the consul learnt from them what had
                        happened to the Aetolian envoys, he sent orders for them to be brought from
                        Tyrrhenum, and on their arrival the negotiations commenced. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Amynander, whose main interest was in Ambracia, did his
                        utmost to induce the place to surrender. He approached the walls and held
                        conversations with the leaders, but finding that he was making no progress,
                        he at last obtained the consul's permission to enter the city and succeeded
                            <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> by argument and entreaty in
                        persuading them to place themselves in the hands of the Romans. The
                        Aetolians found a strong advocate also in C. Valerius, the son of the
                        Valerius Laevinus who was the first to establish friendly relations with
                        them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He was also half-brother of the
                        consul. </p>
                    <p> After stipulating for the safe departure of their auxiliary troops, the
                        Ambracians opened their gates. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then the
                        Aetolians accepted the following conditions: They were to pay 500 Euboean
                        talents; 200 at once, the remaining 300 to be spread over six years; the
                        prisoners and refugees were to be restored to the Romans; they were not to
                        retain within their League any city which from the day when T. Quinctius
                        landed in Greece had either been taken by or entered into friendly relations
                        with the Romans. Although these conditions were much less onerous than they
                        had expected, they asked to be allowed to lay them before their council.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Here there was a brief debate on the
                        question of the cities which had been confederated with them. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> They felt their loss keenly; it was as though
                        they were being torn from their living body; nevertheless they were
                        unanimous in deciding that the terms must be accepted. The Ambracians gave
                        the consul a gold crown 150 lbs. in weight. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                        /> The statues in bronze and marble and the paintings with which Ambracia,
                        as the royal residence of Pyrrhus, had been more richly adorned than any
                        other city in that part of the world were all carried away, but beyond these
                        nothing was injured or interfered with. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul left Ambracia for the interior
                        of Aetolia and fixed his camp at Amphilochian Argos, twenty-two miles
                        distant from Ambracia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Here the Aetolian
                        delegates at last arrived, the consul meantime wondering what had delayed
                        them. On their informing him that the Aetolian Council accepted the
                        conditions of peace, he told them to go to Rome to appear before the senate;
                        the Rhodians and Athenians were also allowed to go to plead for them; and
                        the consul also allowed his brother, C. Valerius, to accompany them.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After their departure be crossed over
                        to Cephallania. In Rome the delegates found the ears and minds of the
                        leading men preoccupied by the accusations which Philip had brought against
                        them. Through his representatives, in his despatches he had asserted that
                        Dolopia, Amphilochia and Athamania had been wrested from him, and his
                        garrisons and even his son Perseus had been expelled from Amphilochia.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The senate consequently refused to
                        listen to them. The Rhodians and Athenians, however, obtained a hearing. The
                        Athenian spokesman, Leon the son of Hicesias, is said to have moved them by
                        his eloquence. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Making use of a common
                        simile he compared the people of Aetolia to a calm sea which has become
                        agitated by the winds. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> "As long as they
                        were faithful to Rome," he said, "their peace-loving temperament kept them
                        quiet, but when Thoas and Dicaearchus sent a blast from Asia and Menestas
                        and Damocritas from Europe, then that storm arose which dashed them against
                        Antiochus as against a rock." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After a good deal of rough-handling the
                        Aetolians at last succeeded in getting the terms of peace settled.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They were as follows: "The nation of
                        the Aetolians shall uphold sincerely and honestly the majesty and dominion
                        of the Roman people; they shall not suffer to pass through their territories
                        or in any way assist any army which may be led against the friends and
                        allies of Rome; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> they shall count the
                        enemies of Rome as their enemies and bear arms against them and wage war
                        against them equally with Rome; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> they shall
                        restore to the Romans and their allies the deserters, the refugees and the
                        prisoners, save and except any who have escaped from captivity and returned
                        to their homes and then been taken captive a second time, and any prisoners
                        from amongst those who were fighting against Rome at the time when the
                        Aetolians formed a part of the Roman forces. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> Of the others, all who are known shall be handed over without reserve or
                        subterfuge to the magistrates at Corcyra within 100 days; those who have not
                        then been discovered shall be delivered up as soon as they are found.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Aetolians shall surrender forty
                        hostages, such as the consul in his discretion shall choose, not less than
                        twelve or more than forty years of age. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> No
                        magistrate or commander of cavalry or public secretary shall be taken as a
                        hostage, nor any one who has been previously held as a hostage by the
                        Romans. Cephallania shall be excluded from the terms of peace." <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> As to the indemnity which they were to pay and
                        the method of payment, the understanding with the consul held good. If they
                        preferred to pay it in silver rather than in gold, they might do so provided
                        that ten silver pieces were taken as the equivalent of one gold piece.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> "Concerning the cities, the
                        territories, the populations, which have at any time been incorporated in
                        the Aetolian League-those of them which have either been subjugated or
                        voluntarily surrendered to Rome during the consulships of T. Quinctius,
                        Cneius Domitius, or the consuls which followed them, none of these must the
                        Aetolians seek to recover. The Oeniadae with the city and the soil shall
                        belong to the Acarnanians." Such were the terms upon which peace was
                        concluded with the Aetolians. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Almost at the very time when M. Fulvius
                        was thus engaged in Aetolia, the other consul, Cneius Manlius, was warring
                        in Gallograecia. I will now proceed to narrate the events of this war. The
                        consul went to Ephesus at the beginning of spring and took over the troops
                        from L. Scipio. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After holding a review of
                        the army he addressed the soldiers. He began by eulogising their valour in
                        bringing the war with Antiochus to a close in a single battle, and went on
                        to encourage them to begin a fresh war against the Gauls. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> This nation, he reminded them, had gone to the
                        assistance of Antiochus, and so intractable was their temper that the
                        removal of Antiochus beyond the Taurus would be useless unless the power of
                        the Gauls was broken. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He concluded his
                        address with a few sincere and unaffected words about himself. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> The soldiers were delighted and frequently
                        applauded him; they looked upon the Gauls as simply a division of Antiochus'
                        army, and now that the king was overcome they did not think that there would
                        be much aggressive energy in the Gauls when left to themselves. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> Eumenes was in Rome at the time and the consul
                        regarded his absence as ill-timed, since he was familiar with the country
                        and the population and was personally interested in the destruction of the
                        power of the Gauls. The consul sent, therefore, for his brother Attalus, who
                        was at Pergamum, and pressed him to take his part in the war. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Attalus promised on his own behalf and on that of
                        his subjects to assist him, and was sent back to muster troops. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> A few days later the consul advanced from Ephesus
                        and was met at Magnesia by Attalus with 1000 infantry and 500 cavalry. His
                        brother Athenaeus was under orders to follow with the rest of the forces,
                        and the defence of Pergamum was entrusted to men whom he believed to be
                        loyal subjects of their king. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The consul
                        warmly approved of the young man's action and advanced with the whole of his
                        forces to the Maeander. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Here he
                        entrenched himself, and as the river was unfordable, vessels had to be
                        collected to carry the army over. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After crossing the Maeander they marched
                        to Hiera Come. Here there was a noble temple to Apollo and an oracular
                        shrine; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> it is said that the priests
                        delivered the responses in smooth and graceful verses. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> From this place, after a two days' march, they reached
                        the river Harpasus. Here they were met by a deputation from Alabandi, who
                        came with a request to the consul to compel, either by his personal
                        authority or his arms, a revolted stronghold to return to its former
                        allegiance. Here, too, came Eumenes' brother Athenaeus with the Cretan
                        Leusus and Corragus of Macedonia. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They
                        brought with them 1000 infantry drawn from various nationalities and 300
                        cavalry. The consul despatched a military tribune with a small force to
                        reduce the stronghold and it was restored to the people of Alabandi; he
                        himself continuing his march encamped at Antiochia on the Maeander.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This river rises at Celaenae; the city
                        was once the capital of Phrygia. The population migrated a short distance
                        from the old city and built a new one, which received the name of Apamea
                        after Apama, the sister of King Seleucus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The river Marsyas which rises not far from the sources of the Maeander flows
                        into that river, and the story goes that it was at Celaenae that Marsyas
                        contested the palm of song with Apollo. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        The Maeander rises at the highest part of Celaenae and runs through the
                        middle of the city. Its course then lies through Caria and Ionia and it
                        finally empties itself into the bay between Priene and Miletus. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Whilst the consul was in camp at
                        Antiochia, Seleucus the son of Antiochus came to furnish corn for the army,
                        in pursuance of the treaty obligation with Scipio. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> There was a slight difficulty raised in the case of the
                        auxiliaries under Attalus because Seleucus maintained that Antiochus had
                        only agreed to supply corn to the Roman soldiers. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The dispute was settled by the firmness of the consul,
                        who sent a tribune from the headquarters tent to give notice that the Roman
                        soldiers were not to take the corn before the troops of Attalus had received
                        their share. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> From Antiochia they marched
                        to a place called Gordiutichi, and a further three days' march brought them
                        to Tabae. This place lies within the frontiers of Pisidia, in that part
                        which looks towards the Pamphylian sea. As this country was unwasted by war,
                        its population were in a bellicose mood. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        On this occasion they made a vigorous attack on the Roman column and at
                        first created some confusion, but when it became evident that they were
                        outmatched in numbers and in courage and were driven back to their city,
                        they craved for mercy and offered to surrender the city. A fine of 25
                        talents of silver and 10,000 medimni of wheat was imposed upon them.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> On these terms they were allowed to
                        surrender. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Three days after this they reached the
                        river Casus and advanced to attack the city of Eriza, which they captured at
                        the first assault. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Continuing their march
                        they came to Thabusion, a fortified place commanding the Indus. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> This river got its name from a mahout who was
                        thrown from his elephant. They were now not far from the city of Cibyra, but
                        no deputation came from Moagetes, the faithless and cruel tyrant of that
                        city. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In order to ascertain his attitude
                        the consul sent an advance-party of 4000 infantry and 500 cavalry under C.
                        Helvius. This force was already entering his territory when envoys met them
                        with the announcement that the tyrant was ready to comply with the consul's
                        orders. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They begged Helvius to enter their
                        territory peaceably and to restrain his soldiery from plundering their
                        fields; they also brought 15 lbs. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> of gold
                        made into a crown. Helvius promised to protect their fields from pillage and
                        told them to go to the consul. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When they
                        had spoken in a similar strain to him, he replied: "We Romans have received
                        no proofs of goodwill on the part of the tyrant towards us, and it is a
                        matter of common knowledge that he is the sort of man whom we ought to think
                        of punishing rather than treating as a friend." <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The envoys were greatly perturbed at these words and
                        simply requested him to accept the golden crown and to allow the tyrant to
                        visit him in person with liberty to speak and clear himself of suspicions.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The consul gave permission and the
                        next day the tyrant arrived. His dress and his retinue were hardly equal to
                        those of a private citizen of moderate means; his language was abject and
                        broken, and he sought to excuse himself by pleading the poverty of his
                        cities and his dominions. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Besides Cibyra
                        he had the city of Sylleum and a place called Alimne, and out of these
                        cities he promised, though somewhat doubtfully, to raise 25 talents, but
                        only by robbing himself and his subjects. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        "Really," replied the consul, "this trifling is intolerable! After trying,
                        unblushingly, to fool us through your envoys, you actually keep up the same
                        effrontery now you are here. You say 25 talents will exhaust your
                        government. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Very well, then, unless you
                        pay down 500 talents in three days, look out for the plunder of your fields
                        and the investment of your city." <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Though
                        appalled by the threat, the tyrant still persisted in his presence of
                        poverty. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Shuffling, whimpering and
                        shedding crocodile tears, he was at last brought to a fine of 100 talents,
                        and in addition 10,000 medimni of corn. All this was carried through in six
                        days. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From Cibyra the army was led through the
                        district of Sinda, and after crossing the Caularis formed camp. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The following day they marched past the Caralite
                        marshes and made a halt at Madamprum. On their further advance towards Lacos
                        the inhabitants fled from the city, and finding it devoid of men but filled
                        with abundance of every kind, the Romans sacked it. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Then they went on to the sources of the Lysis and the
                        following day reached the Cobulatus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        Termessians had captured the city of Isionde and were now attacking the
                        citadel. Shut up within their walls the only hope left to them was help from
                        the Romans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They sent to the consul to
                        implore his assistance; shut up in their citadel with their wives and
                        children, they were daily looking forward to death either by sword or
                        famine. The consul gladly seized the pretext for a march into Pamphylia, and
                        raised the siege, granting peace to Termessus on the payment of 50 talents
                        of silver. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Aspendus and the other cities
                        in Pamphylia were treated in the same way. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Leaving Pamphylia and resuming his march he encamped at the river Taurus,
                        and the next day at a place called Xyline Come. From there he marched
                        continuously till he reached the city of Cormasa. The next city to this was
                        Dursa, which they found deserted by the panic-stricken inhabitants, but
                        abundantly supplied with all manner of stores. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> On his advance past the marshes a deputation came to
                        him from Lysinoe to surrender their city. From this point he entered the
                        territory of Sagalassus, a fertile district rich in all kinds of fruits.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Its Pisidian inhabitants are by far
                        the best soldiers in that part of the world. Their military superiority, the
                        fruitfulness of their soil, their large population, and the situation of
                        their exceptionally strong city make them a brave people. As no envoys
                        appeared when the consul reached their frontiers, he sent out plundering
                        parties into their fields. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At last, as
                        they saw their crops carried off and their cattle driven away, their
                        stubbornness yielded. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The envoys whom
                        they sent agreed to pay a fine of 50 talents, 20,000 medimni of wheat and an
                        equal amount of barley, and on these terms they obtained peace. Making a
                        further advance to the source of the Rhotris he encamped at a village called
                        Acoridos Come. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The next day Seleucus
                        arrived from Apamea. The consul sent the sick and all the baggage which was
                        not needed to Apamea, and after <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> being
                        supplied with guides by Seleucus, he marched into the plain of Metropolis,
                        and the next day to Dyniae in Phrygia. A further advance brought him to
                        Synnada. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> All the cities round had been
                        deserted by their inhabitants, and the army was so heavily laden with the
                        booty from these places that they took a whole day to traverse the five
                        miles to Old Beudi, as it is called. His next halt was at Anabura; the day
                        following he encamped at the source of the Alander, and on the third day at
                        Abassium. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> As he had now reached the
                        frontiers of the Tolostobogii he remained encamped for several days. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A large body of Gauls, induced either by
                        want of room or desire for plunder and convinced that none of the nations
                        through whom they intended to pass was a match for them in arms, marched
                        under the leadership of Brennus into the country of the Dardani. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Here a quarrel arose, and as many as 20,000 of
                        them left Brennus and went off under two of their chiefs, Lonorius and
                        Lutarius, into Thrace. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Fighting with those
                        who opposed their progress and exacting tribute from those who asked for
                        peace, they reached Byzantium. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Here they
                        remained for some time in occupation of the coast of the Propontis, all the
                        cities in that region being tributary to them. When reports from those
                        acquainted with Asia of the fertility of its soil reached their ears, they
                        were seized with the desire of crossing over to it, and after capturing
                        Lysimachia by treachery and making themselves masters of the whole of the
                        Chersonese, they moved down to the Hellespont. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> They were all the more eager to make the passage when
                        they saw that there was only a narrow strait which separated them, and they
                        sent to Antipater, the governor of the coastal district, asking him to
                        arrange for their transport. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The matter
                        took longer than they expected, and a fresh quarrel broke out between the
                        chiefs. Lonorius, with the greater part of the host, returned to Byzantium;
                        Lutarius took two decked ships and three light barques from some Macedonians
                        who had been sent by Antipater, ostensibly as negotiators, but really as
                        spies, and in these vessels he transported one detachment after another,
                        night and day, until he had carried his whole force across. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Not long afterwards, Lonorius, with the assistance of
                        Nicomedes king of Bithynia, sailed across from Byzantium. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The re-united Gauls assisted Nicomedes in his war
                        against Ziboetas, who was holding a part of Bithynia, and it was mainly
                        owing to them that Ziboetas was defeated and the whole of Bithynia brought
                        under the rule of Nicomedes. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> From Bithynia they went further into Asia.
                        Out of the 20,000 men not more than 10,000 were carrying arms, yet so great
                        was the terror they inspired in all the nations west of the Taurus, that
                        those who had no experience of them, <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> as
                        well as those who had come into contact with them, the most remote as well
                        as their next neighbours, all alike submitted to them. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> They were made up of three tribes, the Tolostobogii,
                        the Trocmi and the Tectosagi, and in the end they divided the conquered
                        territory of Asia into three parts, each tribe retaining its own tributary
                        cities. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The coast of the Hellespont was
                        given to the Trocmi, the Tolostobogii took Aeolis and Ionia, and the
                        Tectosagi received the inland districts. They levied tribute on the whole of
                        Asia west of the Taurus, but fixed their own settlement on both sides of the
                        Halys. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Such was the terror of their name
                        and the growth of their numbers that at last even the kings of Syria did not
                        dare to refuse the payment of tribute. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        The first man in Asia to refuse was Attalus the father of Eumenes, and
                        contrary to universal expectation, fortune favoured his courageous action;
                        he proved himself superior in a pitched battle. The Gauls, however, were not
                        so far disheartened as to renounce their supremacy in Asia; their power
                        remained unimpaired down to the war between Antiochus and Rome. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> Even then, after the defeat of Antiochus, they
                        quite expected that owing to their distance from the sea the Romans would
                        not advance so far. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As it was this enemy, so much dreaded by
                        all the people in that part of the world, that was to be met in war, the
                        consul paraded his soldiers and delivered the following speech to them:
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> "I am quite aware, soldiers, that of
                        all the nations of Asia the Gauls have the highest military reputation.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This fierce people, after wandering
                        and warring over almost the entire world, have taken up their abode amongst
                        the gentlest and most peaceable race of men. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> Their tall stature, their long red hair, their huge shields, their
                        extraordinarily long swords; still more, their songs as they enter into
                        battle, their war-whoops and dances, and the horrible clash of arms as they
                        shake their shields in the way their fathers did before them-all these
                        things are intended to terrify and appal. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        But let those fear them to whom they are strange and startling, such as the
                        Greeks and Phrygians and Carians. We Romans are familiar with Gaulish
                        tumults and know how they come to nothing. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Once in the old days when our ancestors met them for the first time, they
                        fled from them at the Alia; from that time for the last 200 years they have
                        routed and slain them like so many herds of cattle, and almost more triumphs
                        have been won over the Gauls than over the rest of the world put together.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Our experience has taught us this-if
                        you withstand their first rush with its wild excitement and blind fury,
                        their limbs become powerless with sweat and fatigue, their weapons hang
                        idly; their flabby bodies and, when their fury has spent itself, their
                        flabby spirits, too, are prostrated by sun and dust and thirst, even though
                        you did not lift a sword against them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> We
                        have made trial of them, not only legions against legions, but man against
                        man. T. Manlius and M. Valerius have shown how steady Roman courage can get
                        the better of Gaulish frenzy. M. Manlius flung down single-handed the Gauls
                        who were climbing the Capitol. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And,
                        besides, those ancestors of ours had to deal with genuine Gauls bred in
                        their own land; these are degenerates, a mongrel race, truly what they are
                        called-Gallograeci. Just as in the case of fruits and cattle, the seed is
                        not so effective in keeping up the strain as the nature of the soil and
                        climate in which they are reared are in changing it. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> "The Macedonians who occupy Alexandria,
                        Seleucia, Babylonia and their other colonies throughout the world, have
                        degenerated into Syrians and Parthians and Egyptians. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Massilia, situated amongst Gauls, has contracted
                        something of the temperament of its neighbours. How much of the rough and
                        stern discipline of Sparta has survived amongst the Tarentines? <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> Everything grows most vigorously in its own
                        home; when planted in an alien soil its nature changes and it deteriorates
                        into that from which it gets its subsistence. As in the battle with
                        Antiochus you slew the Phrygians in spite of their heavy Gaulish arms, so
                        you will slay them now, you the victors, they the vanquished. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> I am more afraid of our gaining too little glory
                        in this war than of gaining too much. Antiochus has often routed and
                        scattered them. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Do not imagine that it is
                        only wild beasts which preserve their ferocity when newly-captured but after
                        being fed for some time at the hands of men grow tame. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> Nature works in the same way in softening the savagery
                        of men. Do you suppose that these men are the same as their fathers and
                        grandfathers were? Driven from their home by want of room they wandered
                        across the rugged coast of Illyria, and after traversing the whole length of
                        Paeonia and Thrace and fighting their way through warlike nations took
                        possession of these countries. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> After
                        becoming hardened and savage by all they had to go through, they have found
                        a home in a land which makes them fat with bountiful supplies of every kind.
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> All the ferocity which they brought
                        with them has been tamed by a most fertile soil, a most genial climate and
                        the gentle character of the people amongst whom they have settled.
                            <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> You, sons of Mars, believe me, will
                        have to be on your guard against the attractions of Asia and shun them from
                        the very first; such power have the pleasures of other lands to weaken and
                        destroy your energies, so easily can the habits and practices of the people
                        round you affect you. It is, however, fortunate for us that though they
                        cannot oppose you with anything like the strength they once could, they
                        still enjoy their former reputation amongst the Greeks. <milestone n="19"
                            unit="section"/> You will therefore gain as much credit with our allies
                        in conquering as if the Gauls you defeat had retained <milestone n="20??"
                            unit="section"/> all the courage of old days." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After dismissing his men he sent
                        messengers to Eposognatus, who was the only Gaulish chief who had remained
                        friendly to Eumenes and refused assistance to Antiochus against the Romans.
                        The consul then resumed his advance; on the first day he reached the Alander
                        and the day after, a village called Tyscon. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> Here a deputation arrived from Oroanda begging for peace. They were
                        ordered to pay 200 talents, and the consul allowed them to return home and
                        report his demand to their government. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        From there he marched to Plitendum, his next halting-place being Alyatti.
                        Here the messengers sent to Eposognatus returned in company with envoys from
                        the chief, who begged the consul not to commence hostilities against the
                        Tectosagi, as he would go to them himself and persuade them to submit. His
                        request was granted. Then the army entered a tract of country called Axylon.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It derives its name from the character
                        of the soil; not only does it bear nothing in the shape of timber, but not
                        even brambles or thorn bushes grow here, or anything which can serve for
                        fuel. The inhabitants use cow-dung instead of wood. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst the Romans were encamped at Cuballum, a
                        fortified place in Gallograecia, a body of enemy cavalry appeared making a
                        great tumult. Their sudden attack not only threw the Roman outposts into
                        confusion but caused some losses amongst them. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> As the tumult reached the camp, the Roman cavalry
                        hurrying out from all the gates routed the Gauls and put them to flight, and
                        a considerable number of the fugitives were slain. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consul, aware that he was now in the
                        enemy's country, advanced with caution, keeping his force well together and
                        throwing out scouting parties. Marching continuously, he came to the river
                        Sangarius, and as there was no possibility of fording it, he decided to
                        construct a bridge. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Sangarius rises in
                        the Adoreos range and flowing through Phrygia mingles its waters with the
                        Tymbris on the frontier of Bithynia, and with its volume thus increased
                        flows through Bithynia and empties itself into the Propontis. It is not,
                        however, so remarkable for its size as for the vast quantity of fish with
                        which it supplies the inhabitants. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When
                        the bridge was completed the army crossed the river and as they were
                        marching along the bank they were met by the "Galli" or priests of the Mater
                        Magna from Pessinus with their insignia, who prophesied in mystic and
                        oracular verses that the goddess was granting the Romans safety and victory
                        in the war and the sovereignty of the country in which they were. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> The consul welcomed the omen and fixed his camp
                        for the night on that very spot. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The next
                        day he arrived at Gordium. This is not a large place but it possesses a
                        widely-known and much-frequented market; a larger one, in fact, than most
                        inland towns. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> It is almost equally
                        distant from three seas, the Hellespont, the Euxine at Sinope, and the sea
                        which washes the shores of Cilicia, and also adjoins the territories of
                        several large populations, who for the sake of mutual commercial advantages
                        have made this their business centre. The Romans found it deserted, the
                        inhabitants having fled, and stored with goods of every description.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Whilst they were encamped here,
                        envoys from Eposognatus arrived with the intelligence that he had
                        interviewed the Gaulish chiefs but could not make them listen to reason.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> They were abandoning their villages
                        and farms in the open country, and together with their wives <milestone
                            n="15??" unit="section"/> and children were carrying their portable
                        property and driving their flocks and herds before them towards Olympus.
                        Here they intended to defend themselves by arms and their strong position.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Subsequently, more definite information
                        was received from Oroanda to the effect that the Tolostobogii had actually
                        occupied Olympus; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> that the Tectosagi going
                        in a different direction had established themselves on another mountain
                        called Magaba, and that the Trocmi had left their wives and children in the
                        care of the Tectosagi and gone to the assistance of the Tolostobogii. The
                        chiefs of these three tribes were Ortiagon, Comboiomarus and Gaulotus.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Their main reason for adopting this
                        mode of warfare was that by holding the principal heights in the country,
                        provided with everything they might require for an indefinite period, they
                        hoped to wear out the enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They never
                        imagined he would venture to approach them over such steep and difficult
                        ground; if he did make the attempt they believed that even a small force
                        would be sufficient to dislodge him or throw him back in confusion; whilst
                        if he remained inactive at the foot of the mountain he would be unable to
                        endure the cold and hunger. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Though the
                        height of their position was itself a protection, they drew a trench and
                        constructed other defences round the peaks on which they were established.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Missile weapons they troubled
                        themselves very little about as they thought the rocky ground would supply
                        them with plenty of stones. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As the consul had anticipated that the
                        fighting would not be at close quarters but would involve an attack upon
                        positions from a distance, he accumulated a large quantity of javelins,
                        light infantry spears, arrows and leaden balls and small stones suitable for
                        hurling from slings. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Provided with these
                        missile weapons, he marched towards Olympus and encamped about four miles'
                        distance from the mountain. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On the morrow
                        he sent Attalus with 500 cavalry to reconnoitre the ground and the situation
                        of the Gaulish camp. While thus engaged a body of hostile cavalry, twice as
                        large as his own force, sallied from their camp and put him to flight; some
                        of his men were killed and several wounded. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> The next day the consul went out with the whole of his cavalry to
                        explore, and as none of the enemy appeared outside their lines he made the
                        circuit of the mountain in safety. He noticed that towards the south the
                        ground rose in gentle slopes and was covered with soil; on the north the
                        cliffs were precipitous and almost vertical. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> There were only three possible roads-everywhere else it was
                        inaccessible-the one up the middle of the mountain free from rocks, and two
                        which were difficult, one on the south-east and the other on the north-west.
                        After making these observations he encamped for the day close to the foot of
                        the mountain. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The following day, after he
                        had offered the sacrifices and the first victims had given favourable omens,
                        he advanced against the enemy. The army was formed into three divisions;
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> the largest he commanded in person and
                        began the ascent where it afforded the easiest approach; his brother, L.
                        Manlius, was ordered to advance from the southeastern side as far as the
                        ground allowed of his doing so safely, but if he came to a dangerous or
                        precipitous part he was not to struggle against the difficulties of the path
                        nor try to force his way over insuperable obstacles. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> In that case he was to turn and march across the face
                        of the mountain and unite his division with the one which the consul was
                        leading. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> C. Helvius was to work gradually
                        round the lower slopes of the mountain and then take his division up the
                        north-eastern side. Attalus' auxiliaries were also formed into three
                        divisions, Attalus himself accompanying the consul. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The cavalry and elephants were left on the level ground
                        at the bottom, and their commanders were under orders to watch carefully the
                        progress of the action and render prompt assistance wherever it was
                        required. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Gauls feeling confident that on two
                        sides they were unassailable directed their attention to the southern slope.
                        To close all access on this side they sent 4000 men to seize a height which
                        commanded the road, distant rather less than a mile from their camp, where,
                        as in a fort, they might prevent the enemy's advance. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> When they saw this, the Romans made ready for battle.
                        Somewhat in front of the legions went the velites, the Cretan archers and
                        slingers and the Tralli and Thracians under Attalus. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The heavy infantry advanced slowly as the ground was
                        steep and they held their shields in front of them, not because they
                        expected a hand-to-hand contest, but simply to avoid the missiles.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> With the discharge of missiles the
                        battle began, and at first it was fought on even terms as the Gauls had the
                        advantage of their position, the Romans that of the variety and abundance of
                        their missile weapons. As the struggle went on, however, it became anything
                        but equal; the shields of the Gauls though long were not broad enough to
                        cover their bodies, and being flat also afforded poor protection. Moreover,
                        they had no weapons but their swords, and as they could not come to close
                        quarters these were useless. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They tried to
                        make use of stones, but as they had not got any ready, they had to use what
                            <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> each man in his hurry and confusion
                        could lay hands on, and unaccustomed as they were to these weapons, they
                        could not make them more effective by either skill or strength. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> On all sides they were being hit by the arrows
                        and leaden bullets and javelins which they were powerless to ward off;
                        blinded by rage and fear they did not see what they were to do, and they
                        found themselves engaged in the kind of fighting for which they were least
                        fitted. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In close fighting where they can
                        receive and inflict wounds in turn, their fury stimulates their courage; so
                        when they are being wounded by missiles flung from a distance by an unseen
                        foe and there is no one against whom they can make a blind rush, they dash
                        recklessly against their own comrades like wild beasts that have been
                        speared. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Their practice of always fighting
                        naked makes their wounds more visible, and their bodies are white and fleshy
                        as they never strip except in battle. Consequently more blood flowed from
                        them, the open gashes appeared more horrible, and the whiteness of their
                        bodies showed up the stain of the dark blood. Open wounds, however, do not
                        trouble them much. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Sometimes, where it is
                        a surface bruise rather than a deep wound, they cut the skin, and even think
                        that in this way they win greater glory in battle. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> But when the head of an arrow has gone in or a leaden
                        bullet buried itself and it tortures them with what looks like a slight
                        wound and defies all their efforts to get rid of it, they fling themselves
                        on the ground in shame and fury at so small an injury threatening to prove
                        fatal. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> So they were lying about
                        everywhere, and some who rushed down on their enemy were being pierced with
                        missiles from all sides; those who got to close quarters the velites slew
                        with their swords. These soldiers carry a shield three feet long, javelins
                        in their right hand for use at a distance and a Spanish sword in their
                        belts. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> When they have to fight at close
                        quarters they transfer the javelins to their left hands and draw their
                        swords. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Few of the Gauls now survived,
                        and when they found themselves worsted by the light infantry and the legions
                        coming on, they fled in disorder back to their camp, which was full of
                        tumult and panic, as the women and children and other noncombatants were all
                        crowded there together. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The Romans took
                        possession of the heights from which the enemy had fled. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> L. Manlius and C. Helvius in the meanwhile
                        had marched up as far as the mountain-side afforded a path, and when they
                        came to a place where it was impossible to advance they each turned towards
                        the only <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> part which was accessible, and
                        as though by mutual understanding, they followed the consul at some distance
                        from each other. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Necessity compelled them
                        to adopt now what would have been the best course at the outset, for over
                        such difficult ground supports have often proved of the greatest use; when
                        the first line has been thrown into disorder the second line can shelter
                        them and go into action fresh and unshaken. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> When the foremost ranks of the legions had gained the heights which the
                        light infantry had captured, the consul ordered his men to rest and recover
                        their breath. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He pointed to the bodies of
                        the Gauls scattered over the ground and said: "If the light infantry could
                        fight as they have done, what may I not expect from the legions, from those
                        who are fully armed, from the valour of my bravest soldiers? Surely after
                        the light infantry have driven the enemy in confusion into their camp, you
                        legionaries must storm and capture it." <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        During this halt the light infantry had been busy collecting the missiles
                        which were lying everywhere, in order that they might have a sufficient
                        supply, and the consul now ordered them to advance. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> As they approached the camp, the Gauls, fearing lest
                        their entrenchments should afford them insufficient protection, were
                        standing in arms in front of the rampart. They were at once overwhelmed by a
                        general discharge of missiles, for the greater their numbers and the closer
                        their formation so much more surely did every weapon find its mark. In a few
                        minutes they were driven inside their lines, leaving only strong bodies to
                        guard the camp gates. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A heavy shower of
                        missiles was now directed upon the masses in the camp, and the mingled
                        shrieks of women and children showed that many of them were hit. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Against those who were holding the gates the
                        legionaries hurled their javelins. They were not wounded by them, but their
                        shields were pierced, and thus hopelessly entangled together they were not
                        able long to resist the Roman attack. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As the gates were now open, the Gauls fled
                        in every direction from the camp before the victors burst in. Blindly they
                        dashed along the paths and over places where there was no path; no
                        precipices, no cliffs stopped them; they feared nothing but the enemy.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Most of them fell headlong from the
                        heights; they died, maimed and crushed. The consul kept his men from
                        plundering the captured camp and ordered them to do their best to pursue and
                        harass the enemy and increase his panic. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        When the second division under L. Manlius came up, he forbade them also to
                        enter the camp, and sent them off at once in pursuit. After placing the
                        prisoners in charge of the military tribunes he joined in the pursuit, for
                        he believed that the war would be at an end if as many as possible were
                        killed or made prisoners whilst they were in such a state of panic.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After the consul had gone, C. Helvius
                        came up with his division, and was unable to restrain his men from
                        plundering the camp, and so by a most unfair chance the booty went to those
                        who had no share of the fighting. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                        cavalry stood for a long time knowing nothing of the battle or the victory
                        which their comrades had won. Then they rode, wherever their horses could
                        travel, after the Gauls dispersed round the mountain, and either killed or
                        took them prisoners. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was not easy to get at the number of
                        those killed, for the flight and the carnage extended over <milestone
                            n="7??" unit="section"/> all the spurs and ravines of the mountain, and
                        a great many losing their way had fallen into the deep recesses below; many,
                        too, were killed in the woods and thickets. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> Claudius, who states that there were two battles on Olympus, puts the
                        number of killed at 40,000; Valerius Antias, who is usually more given to
                        exaggeration, says that there were not more than 10,000. The prisoners, no
                        doubt, amounted to 40,000, because <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> they
                        had carried with them a multitude of both sexes and all ages, more like
                        emigrants than men going to war. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                        enemy's weapons were gathered into a heap and burnt, and the consul ordered
                        the troops to collect the rest of the booty. That portion which was to go to
                        the State he sold; the rest he distributed with most scrupulous fairness
                        amongst the soldiers. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He then paraded
                        them, and after warmly commending the services which the whole army had
                        rendered, he conferred rewards on each according to their merit, especially
                        on Attalus, who was unanimously applauded, for the exemplary courage and
                        untiring energy which the young prince had shown in facing toils and dangers
                        was only equalled by his modesty. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Now came the campaign against the
                        Tectosagi, and the consul commenced his advance against them. In a three
                        days' march he reached Ancyra, a city of importance in that district, and
                        the enemy were only ten miles distant from it. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst he was here in camp a remarkable incident
                        occurred in connection with a female prisoner. The wife of a chief named
                        Orgiagon, a woman of exceptional beauty, was with other captives in the
                        custody of a centurion who was notorious even amongst soldiers for his
                        licentiousness and greed. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At first he made
                        improper proposals to her, but finding that she treated them with
                        abhorrence, he took advantage of her servile condition and violated her.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then, to assuage her anger and shame
                        at the outrage, he held out hopes to her of returning to her friends, but
                        not as a lover would have done without ransom. He stipulated for a certain
                        weight of gold, and to prevent his men from knowing anything about it, he
                        allowed her to choose one of the prisoners and send a message by him to her
                        friends. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A spot by the river was fixed
                        upon where not more than two of her friends were to come with the gold on
                        the following night and receive her. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There
                        happened to be amongst the prisoners one of her own slaves, and this man was
                        conducted by the centurion beyond the ramparts as soon as it was dark.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The following night two of her friends
                        and the centurion with his captive met at the place. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst they were showing him the gold, which amounted
                        to an Attic talent-the sum agreed upon-the woman speaking in her own
                        language ordered them to draw their swords and cut off the centurion's head
                        while he was counting out the gold. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Wrapping up the murdered man's head in her robe, she took it to her husband,
                        who had fled home from Olympus. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Before
                        embracing him she flung down the head at his feet, and whilst he was
                        wondering whose head it could possibly be, or what such an unwomanly act
                        could mean, she told him about the outrage she had endured and the revenge
                        she had taken for her violated chastity. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        It is recorded that by the purity and strictness of her life she maintained
                        to the very last the honour of a deed so worthy of a matron. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst the consul was in camp at Ancyra he
                        was visited by envoys from the Tectosagi, who begged him not to advance any
                        further until he had had a conference with their <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> kings, and assured him that there were no terms of
                        peace which they would not prefer to war. The next day was fixed for the
                        interview; the spot selected was one that seemed to be halfway between
                        Ancyra and the Gaulish camp. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consul
                        went there at the appointed time with an escort of 500 cavalry, but as not a
                        single Gaul was in sight he returned to camp. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The envoys reappeared and excused the absence of the
                        chiefs on religious grounds; they promised that some of their principal men
                        would come, as matters could be equally well transacted with them.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consul said that he would send
                        Attalus to represent him. Both parties came; Attalus with an escort of 300
                        cavalry. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The terms of peace were
                        discussed, but no final result could be reached in the absence of the
                        leaders; so it was arranged that the consul should meet the chiefs on the
                        following day. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Gauls had a double
                        object in delaying negotiations; first, to gain time, so that they might
                        transport their property, which might, they feared, expose them to danger,
                        across the Halys, together with their wives and children; secondly, because
                        they were hatching a plot against the consul, who was not taking any
                        precautions against treachery at the conference. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> For this purpose they had selected out of their entire
                        force 1000 men of proved daring, and the design would have succeeded if
                        fortune had not defended the law of nations which they intended to violate.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Roman troops were sent to collect
                        forage and wood near the place of the conference, as this appeared to the
                        military tribunes to be the safest course, since they would have the consul
                        and his escort between them and the enemy. Another detachment of 600 mounted
                        men was stationed nearer their camp. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On receiving Attalus' assurance that the
                        kings would come and that the negotiations could be completed, the consul
                        started from the camp with the same escort as before. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> He had ridden nearly five miles and was not far from
                        the appointed place when he suddenly saw the Gauls coming on at full gallop
                        with hostile intent. Halting his force and bidding them prepare themselves
                        and their arms for battle, he met the first charge firmly without giving
                        ground. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Then when the weight of numbers
                        began to tell he slowly retired, keeping his ranks unbroken, but at last
                        when there was more danger in remaining on the field than safety in keeping
                        their ranks, they all broke and fled. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        Thus scattered they were hard pressed by the Gauls, as they cut them down,
                        and a large proportion of them would have been destroyed had not the 600 who
                        were posted to protect the foragers met them in their flight. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> They had heard the shouts of alarm amongst their
                        comrades, and hurriedly getting their weapons and horses ready they came
                        fresh into the fight when it was almost over. This turned the fortunes of
                        the day. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> and the panic recoiled from the
                        defeated on to the conquerors. The Gauls were routed in the first charge,
                        and as the foragers came running up from the fields, the enemy found
                        themselves met on every side, with hardly any way of escape open. The Romans
                        on fresh horses were pursuing those which were tired and exhausted, and few
                        escaped. No prisoners were taken. By far the greater number paid the death
                        penalty for their breach of good faith. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        Furious at this treachery the Romans advanced in full strength against the
                        enemy the following day. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul spent two days in making a
                        close inspection of the natural features of the mountain that he might be
                        familiar with every detail. The next day, after taking the auspices and
                        offering the sacrifices, he led out his army. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> It was formed into four divisions; two of these he
                        intended to take up the middle of the mountain, the two others were to
                        ascend the sides and take the Gauls in both flanks. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The dispositions of the enemy were as follows: the
                        Tectosagi and the Trocmi, who formed his main strength, numbering 50,000
                        men, held the centre; the cavalry, 10,000 strong, were dismounted as horses
                        were useless on that broken ground, and formed the right wing; the
                        Cappadocians under Ariarathes and the Morzian auxiliaries, in all about
                        4000, were posted on the left. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The consul
                        placed his light infantry in the first line as he had done in the battle on
                        Olympus, and took care that they should have an equally ample supply of
                        weapons at hand. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When they approached the
                        enemy all the features of the former battle were reproduced except that the
                        courage of the one side was raised by their recent victory and that of the
                        other side depressed, for the enemy though not yet themselves defeated,
                        looked upon the defeat of their fellow-countrymen as tantamount to their
                        own. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As the battle began, so it ended in
                        the same way. A perfect cloud of missiles overwhelmed the Gauls. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> None durst run forward from his entrenchments
                        lest he should expose his naked body to the certainty of being hit from all
                        sides, and whilst they remained standing within their lines in close
                        formation, they received more wounds the more densely they were packed, as
                        though each man was specially aimed at. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        The consul thought that the sight of the standards of the legions would put
                        the already demoralised Gauls to instant flight, and accordingly he retired
                        the light infantry and other skirmishers within the ranks of the legions and
                        ordered an advance. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Gauls, unnerved by the memory of the
                        defeat of the Tolostobogii, exhausted by their long standing and their
                        wounds, with the javelins sticking in their bodies, did not wait for the
                        first charge and battle-shout of the Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> They fled towards their camp, but few gained the shelter of their
                        entrenchments; the greater number rushed past them right or left, where-ever
                        their eagerness to escape carried them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        The victors pursued them up to their camp, slaying them from behind, but
                        once at the camp they stopped in their eagerness for plunder; no one
                        continued the pursuit. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Gauls held
                        their ground somewhat longer on the wings, as it took longer to reach them;
                        they did not, however, wait for the first discharge of missiles. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> As the consul could not keep his men from looting
                        the camp, he sent the other two divisions in instant pursuit. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> They followed them up for a considerable distance
                        and killed in all some 8000 men in the flight; there was no attempt at
                        fighting. The survivors crossed the Halys. A large part of the Roman army
                        passed the night in the enemy's camp; the rest the consul led back to their
                        own camp. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The day following, the consul
                        counted up the prisoners and the booty; the amount of the latter was as
                        great as even a nation that was always bent on rapine, and had for many
                        years held by force of arms all the country west of the Taurus, could
                        possibly have amassed. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After the Gauls had
                        collected from their scattered flight, most of them wounded, without arms,
                        and stripped of all their belongings, they sent to the consul to sue for
                        peace. Manlius ordered them to go to Ephesus. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> He himself, anxious to get out of the cold district
                        near the Taurus-it was now the middle of autumn-led his victorious army back
                        to the coast for their winter quarters. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these operations in Asia things
                        were quiet in the other provinces. In Rome the censors T. Quinctius
                        Flamininus and M. Claudius Marcellus revised the roll of senators.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> P. Scipio Africanus was for the third
                        time selected to lead the Senate, and only four members were struck off the
                        roll, none of whom had held any curule office. The censors showed great
                        forbearance also in revising the list of equites. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> They contracted for the building of the substructure on
                        the Capitol over the Aequimelium and also the laying down of a paved road
                        from the Porta Capena to the temple of Mars. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> The Campanians asked the Senate to decide where their census should be
                        taken, and it was decreed that it should be taken in Rome. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> There were very heavy floods this year; on twelve
                        several occasions the Tiber inundated the Campus Martius and the low-lying
                        parts of the City. After Cn. Manlius had brought the war against the Gauls
                        in Asia to a close, the other consul, M. Fulvius, now that the Aetolians
                        were subjugated, sailed across to Cephallania, and sent round to the
                            <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> various cities in the island to ask
                        them which they preferred-surrender to the Romans or the chances of war.
                        Fear prevented them all from refusing to surrender, and they gave the
                        hostages, which the consul demanded in proportion to their scanty resources.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Peace beyond their hopes had now
                        dawned upon the Cephallanians, when suddenly, for some unknown reason, one
                        city that of Same, revolted. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They said
                        that, as their city occupied an advantageous position, they were afraid that
                        the Romans might compel them to live elsewhere. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Whether this was an invention on their part, and their
                        breach of the peace was due to imaginary fears, or whether the matter had
                        been talked about amongst the Romans and so come to their ears, is quite
                        uncertain. What is certain is that after giving hostages they closed their
                        gates, and though the consul sent these hostages to the walls to appeal to
                        the sympathies of their fellow-citizens and kinsmen, they refused to abandon
                        their opposition. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As no peaceable reply
                        was given, the siege of the city was begun. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                        /> The consul had all the siege-engines brought from Ambracia, and the
                        soldiers rapidly completed what works had to be made. The rams began to
                        batter the walls in two directions. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nothing was left undone by the Samaeans in
                        the way of defence against siege-works or assaults. Their method of
                        resistance was mainly two-fold. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On the one
                        hand, where the wall was destroyed they always built a strong one inside
                        close to it, and on the other they made sudden sorties, at one time against
                        the siege-works, at another against the outposts. In these actions they
                        generally proved superior. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> One method was
                        discovered of keeping them back; a simple one, but worth mentioning.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A hundred slingers were sent for from
                        Aegium, Patrae and Dymae. These men had been in the habit, as their fathers
                        had before them, of practicing with their slings, with which they used to
                        hurl into the sea the round stones lying on the beach. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> In this way they gained a more accurate and longer
                        range than the Baliaric slingers. Their slings, too, were not made of a
                        single strap, like those of the Baliarics and other nations, but they
                        consisted of three thongs, stiffened by beings sewn together. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> This prevented the bullet from flying off at
                        random when the thong was let go; when fixed in the sling it could be so
                        whirled round as to fly out as though from the string of a bow. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> They used to send their stones through rings at a
                        great distance, as targets, and were thus able to hit not only the head but
                        whatever part of the face they aimed at. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        These slings kept the Samaeans from making such frequent or such daring
                        sorties; so much so in fact that they called to the Achaeans from their
                        walls and begged them to retire for a time and remain quiet spectators while
                        they fought with the Roman outposts. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Same
                        sustained a siege of four months. Day by day some of their scanty numbers
                        fell or were wounded, and the survivors became exhausted in mind and body.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At last the Romans surmounted the
                        wall and forced their way through the citadel which they call the Cyatis-the
                        city extends on the west down to the sea-and appeared in the forum. When the
                        Samaeans found that the city was partly captured by the enemy they took
                        refuge in the larger citadel with their wives and children. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> The next day they surrendered; the city was
                        sacked, and the whole of its population sold into slavery. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After settling matters in Cephallania and
                        placing at garrison in Same, the consul sailed to the Peloponnesus, whither
                        the people of Aegium and the Lacedaemonians had for some time urged him to
                        go. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Either as a concession to its
                        importance or owing to its convenient situation, Aegium had been the
                        meeting-place of the Council of the League ever since it had been formed.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This year for the first time
                        Philopoemen tried to do away with this custom, and was preparing to bring in
                        a law enacting that the Assembly should be held in each city of the League
                        in turn. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Just before the consul's visit
                        the Damiourgi (the supreme magistrates) of the various States had convened a
                        meeting of the League at Aegium, whilst Philopoemen the captain-general had
                        summoned them to Argos. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As they would
                        evidently almost all meet there, the consul, though he was in favour of
                        Aegium, went to Argos. Here the question was debated, and when he saw that
                        the Assembly were inclined towards Argos, he gave way. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The Lacedaemonians then drew his attention to their
                        grievances. The main cause of anxiety to their city was the threatening
                        attitude of the exiles, many of whom were living in forts and villages which
                        they had seized on the Laconian coast. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                        Lacedaemonians chafed under this state of things; they wanted to have access
                        to the sea somewhere or other in case they wanted to send a mission to Rome
                        or elsewhere, and also that they might have a free port in which to receive
                        merchandise and necessaries from abroad. They made an attack by night upon a
                        maritime village called Las. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The villagers
                        and exiles were at first terror-struck by the unlooked-for attack, but
                        before it was day they collected in a body and without much difficulty drove
                        the Lacedaemonians out. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then the whole of
                        the coast took alarm and all the forts and villages and the exiles who had
                        made their homes there sent a joint appeal to the Achaeans for help. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From the first, Philopoemen had championed
                        the cause of the exiles and had always tried to persuade the Achaeans to
                        abridge the power and influence of the Lacedaemonians. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He now summoned a council to hear the envoys, and on
                        his initiative a decree was passed in the following terms: "Whereas T.
                        Quinctius and the Romans have committed to the good faith and protection of
                        the Achaeans the villages and forts on the coast of Laconia, and whereas the
                        village of Las has been attacked by the Lacedaemonians who were bound by
                        treaty not to interfere with them, and blood has been shed there, we decree
                        that unless the authors and abettors of this outrage are surrendered to the
                        Achaeans, the treaty shall be held to be broken." <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> A mission was at once despatched to Lacedaemon to
                        insist on this demand. So arbitrary and arrogant did it appear in the eyes
                        of the Lacedaemonians that if that city had been in the position it once
                        held they would undoubtedly have taken up arms. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> What they feared most of all was that if they submitted
                        to the yoke so far as to comply with this initial demand, Philopoemen would
                        carry out the policy he had long contemplated of handing Lacedaemon to the
                        exiles. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In a frenzy of anger they put to
                        death thirty men who belonged to the party who were in league with
                        Philopoemen and the exiles, and then passed a decree denouncing the alliance
                        with the Achaeans and ordering the immediate despatch of a mission to
                        Cephallania to make a formal surrender of Lacedaemon to the consul and to
                        Rome, begging him to come to <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> the
                        Peloponnesus and receive their city into the protection and suzerainty of
                        the people of Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When these proceedings were reported to
                        the Achaeans, all the States of the League with one consent proclaimed war
                        against the Lacedaemonians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Winter
                        prevented any immediate operations on a large scale, but their territories
                        were devastated by bodies of raiders both by land and sea, more in the
                        fashion of brigandage than of regular warfare. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> It was this disturbance that brought the consul to the
                        Peloponnesus, and by his orders a council was summoned to Elis and the
                        Lacedaemonians were invited to state their case. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The discussion soon became a heated quarrel, which the
                        consul put an end to. He was anxious to befriend both sides and after giving
                        a reply which committed him to nothing, warned them both to abstain from
                        hostilities until their representatives had appeared before the Senate. Both
                        sides sent delegates to Rome; the Lacedaemonian exiles entrusted their cause
                        to the Achaeans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The leaders of the
                        Achaean embassy were Diophanes and Lycortas, both natives of Megalopolis.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They were opposed to one another in
                        their political views and the speeches they delivered showed a similar
                        divergence. Diophanes was for leaving the decision on every point to the
                        Senate as they would settle <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> the matters
                        in dispute between the Achaeans and the Lacedaemonians in the best possible
                        way. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Lycortas, acting on instructions from
                        Philopoemen, claimed the right of the Achaeans to execute their decree in
                        accordance with the treaty and their laws, and pleaded that as the Senate
                        had been the instrument of their freedom, so they should preserve that
                        freedom for them undiminished and unimpaired. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> At that time the Achaeans stood high in Roman esteem;
                        it was, however, decided that the position of the Lacedaemonians should be
                        in no way changed. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The reply of the
                        senate was so ambiguous that while the Achaeans assumed that they had a free
                        hand with regard to Lacedaemon, the Lacedaemonians interpreted it to mean
                        that the Achaeans had not gained all they asked for. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Achaeans made a most unscrupulous use
                        of the permission which they considered to have been granted them.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Philopoemen was still in office and in
                        the first days of spring he called out the army and fixed his camp on
                        Lacedaemonian territory. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then he sent to
                        demand the authors of the revolt, and promised that if the city would
                        surrender them it should remain at peace, and the men themselves should
                        suffer no injury until their case had been heard. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Fear kept the rest silent; those who had been named
                        declared their willingness to go, as they had received from Philopoemen's
                        emissaries a guarantee that they would be safe from violence until they had
                        pleaded their cause. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Others, men of high
                        position, went with them to support their friends and also because they
                        considered their cause to be the cause of the State. Never before had the
                        Achaeans brought the exiles with them on to Lacedaemonian soil, because they
                        thought that nothing would do more to estrange their fellow-countrymen from
                        them, but now they were almost in the forefront of the whole army.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the Lacedaemonians came to the
                        gate of the camp the exiles met them in a body. At first they assailed them
                        with insults; then passions became heated on both sides, and the more
                        ferocious of the exiles made an attack upon the Lacedaemonians. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Whilst these were appealing to the gods and the
                        pledged word of Philopoemen's emissaries, and he and his emissaries were
                        keeping back the crowd and protecting the <milestone n="8??" unit="section"
                        /> Lacedaemonians and preventing some from actually manacling them, a large
                        crowd collected and the disturbance increased. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The Achaeans ran up to see what was going on, and the
                        exiles, protesting loudly about the sufferings they had endured, implored
                        their help and told them if they let this opportunity slip they would never
                        again have such a favourable one. "The treaty which had been solemnly
                        published in the Capitol at Olympia and in the citadel at Athens had been
                        set at nought by these men, and before we are bound by another treaty the
                        guilty must be punished." <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This language
                        excited the crowd, and one man shouted out "Kill them." On this they flung
                        stones at them, and seventeen men who had been thrown into chains during the
                        tumult were killed. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On the following day
                        sixty-three were arrested whom Philopoemen had protected from violence, not
                        that he was concerned for their safety, but because he did not want them to
                        perish before the day of trial. Victims to the fury of the mob, they spoke
                        but little and that to deaf ears. All were found guilty and handed over for
                        punishment. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Having thus terrorised the Lacedaemonians,
                        they sent them peremptory orders: first, that they must destroy their walls;
                        secondly, that all the foreign mercenaries who had served under the tyrants
                        must depart from the land of Laconia; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        thirdly, that all the slaves whom the tyrants had set free, and of whom
                        there was a large number, must leave by a certain day; any who remained the
                        Achaeans would have the right to carry off and sell; <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> lastly, they must abrogate the laws and customs of
                        Lycurgus and accustom themselves to the laws and institutions of the
                        Achaeans, as in this way they would form one body and unite more easily in a
                        common policy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> With none of these demands
                        did they comply more readily than with that demanding the destruction of
                        their walls, and none roused such bitter feeling as that demanding the
                        restoration of the exiles. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A decree for
                        their restoration was passed in the Council of the Achaeans at Tegea, and it
                        was stated that the foreign mercenaries had been disbanded, and that the
                        "naturalised Lacedaemonians," for so they designated the slaves set free by
                        the tyrants, had left the city and dispersed into the surrounding country.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On receiving this intelligence it was
                        decided that before the army was demobilised the captain-general should go
                        with a light force and arrest those people and sell them as lawfully
                        acquired booty. Many were thus caught and sold. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> With the money thus raised the colonnade at
                        Megalopolis, which the Lacedaemonians had destroyed, was at the suggestion
                        of the Achaeans restored. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This city also
                        won back the territory of Belbina, which the tyrants of Lacedaemon had
                        wrongfully taken possession of; this was in pursuance of an old decree made
                        by the Achaeans during the reign of Philip the son of Amyntas. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Through these measures the city of Lacedaemon
                        lost the sinews of her strength, and was for a long time at the mercy of the
                        Achaeans. No loss, however, affected her more deeply than the loss of the
                        discipline of Lycurgus, which they had maintained for 800 years. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the meeting of the Council in which
                        the dispute between the Achaeans and the Lacedaemonians took place before
                        the consul, M. Fulvius returned to Rome for the purpose of conducting the
                        elections, as the year was now drawing to a close. M. Aemilius Lepidus, one
                        of the candidates, was a personal enemy of his, and he refused to allow any
                        votes to be cast for him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The consuls
                        elected were M. Valerius Messala and C. Livius Salinator. The praetors
                        elected were Q. Marcius Philippus, M. Claudius Marcellus, C. Stertinius, C.
                        Atinius, P. Claudius Pulcher and L. Manlius Acidinus. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> When the elections were over it was decided that M.
                        Fulvius should return to his army and command, and an extension of office
                        was granted to him and to his colleague Cn. Manlius. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> This year P. Cornelius, as directed by the Keepers of
                        the Sacred Books, placed a statue of Hercules and a chariot with six horses,
                        all gilded, in the Capitol. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                        inscription stated that it had been given by a consul. Twelve gilt shields
                        were also hung there by the curule aediles P. Claudius Pulcher and Servius
                        Sulpicius Gallus out of the fines levied on corn factors who had been
                        holding back their grain. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Another had been
                        convicted at the instance of the plebeian aedile, on two separate charges,
                        and with this fine he provided two gilt statues. His colleague A. Caecilius
                        had not prosecuted any one. The Roman Games were exhibited three times, the
                        Plebeian Games five times. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Immediately on
                        entering into office on the Ides of March the new consuls consulted the
                        senate on the policy to be pursued in the provinces and the armies.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> No change was made with regard to
                        Aetolia or Asia. Pisa and Liguria were assigned to one consul, Gaul to the
                        other. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They were instructed to come to a
                        mutual arrangement, or failing that to ballot, as to which province each
                        should take, and each was to raise afresh army of two Roman legions and
                        15,000 foot and 1200 cavalry from the Italian allies. Liguria fell to
                        Messala; Gaul to Salinator. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then the
                        praetors balloted for their commands. The City jurisdiction fell to M.
                        Claudius; the alien to P. Claudius; Sicily to Q. Marcius; Sardinia to C.
                        Stertinius; Hither Spain to L. Manlius; and Further Spain to C. Atinius.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the case of the armies abroad it was
                        settled that the legions in Gaul which had been under C. Laelius should be
                        transferred to the propraetor M. Tuccius for service in Bruttium. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The army in Sicily was to be disbanded, and the
                        fleet lying there M. Sempronius the propraetor was to bring back to Rome.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was decreed that the legion
                        stationed in each of the two Spanish provinces should remain there, and the
                        praetors were each to take with them 3000 infantry and 200 cavalry drawn
                        from the allies as reinforcements. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Before
                        the new magistrates left for their provinces, special intercessions for
                        three days were ordered on the authority of the Keepers of the Sacred Books
                        to be offered at all the cross-roads owing to a darkness which came over in
                        broad daylight between the third and fourth hours. Sacrifices were also
                        enjoined for nine days in consequence of a shower of stones on the Aventine.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Campanians had been obliged by a
                        decree of the senate passed the year before to have their census taken in
                        Rome as it had previously been uncertain where they ought to be enrolled.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They now requested that they might be
                        allowed to marry women who were Roman citizenesses, and that any who had
                        already done so might hold themselves to be lawfully married, and that
                        children already born might be regarded as legitimate and capable of
                        inheriting property. Both requests were granted. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> One of the tribunes of the plebs, C. Valerius Tappo,
                        brought forward a proposal granting the full franchise to the citizens of
                        the municipal boroughs of Formiae, Fundi and Arpinum. They had hitherto
                        enjoyed the citizenship without the power of voting. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> This motion was opposed by four of the tribunes on the
                        ground that it had not received the sanction of the senate, but on being
                        informed that it rested with the people and not the senate to confer the
                        franchise on whom they chose, they abandoned their opposition. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> The citizens of Formiae and Fundi were authorised
                        to vote in the Aemilian tribe, and those of Arpinum in the Cornelian. In
                        these tribes, therefore, they were for the first time enrolled by virtue of
                        the plebiscite, passed on the motion of Valerius. The censor M. Claudius
                        Marcellus, to whom the ballot gave precedence over T. Quinctius, closed the
                        lustrum. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The census gave the number of
                        citizens as 258,318. After these matters were settled the consuls left for
                        their provinces. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During this winter Cn. Manlius, who was
                        passing the season in Asia first as consul and then as proconsul, was
                        visited by deputations from all the cities and nationalities west of the
                        Taurus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Whilst the Romans regarded their
                        victory over Antiochus as a more notable one than their subsequent victory
                        over the Gauls, their Asiatic allies rejoiced more over the latter than the
                        former. Subjection to the king was a much easier thing to bear than the
                        ferocity of the ruthless barbarians and the <milestone n="3??"
                            unit="section"/> terror which haunted them from one day to another, for
                        they never knew in what direction that ferocity might sweep them like a
                        storm upon plundering and devastating raids. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> They had regained their liberty through the repulse of Antiochus and
                        their peace through the subjugation of the Gauls, and now they brought to
                        the consul not only their congratulations and thanks but also golden crowns,
                        each according to their ability. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Delegates
                        came, too, from Antiochus and even from the Gauls themselves to learn the
                        conditions of peace. Ariarathes also sent envoys from Cappadocia to sue for
                        forgiveness and offer a pecuniary atonement for his offence in assisting
                        Antiochus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He was ordered to pay 600
                        talents of silver and the Gauls were told that when Eumenes arrived they
                        would have the conditions of peace given to them. The delegations from the
                        various cities were dismissed with gracious replies and went away even
                        happier than they had come. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Those from
                        Antiochus received instructions to convey money and corn into Pamphylia, as
                        agreed with L. Scipio, as the consul was going there with his army. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At the beginning of spring, therefore,
                        after performing the lustrations on behalf of his army, he commenced his
                        march, and after eight days reached Apamea. Here he remained encamped for
                        three days, and then advanced into Pamphylia where he had ordered the king's
                        envoys to deposit the money and the corn. He received 1500 talents of silver
                        which were taken to Apamea; the corn was distributed amongst the soldiers.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> From there he advanced to Perga, the
                        only city in that country which was held by a garrison of the king's troops.
                        On his approach he was met by the commandant who asked for a respite of
                        thirty days that he might consult Antiochus about surrendering the city.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He was allowed the interval and on
                        the thirtieth day the garrison evacuated the place. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst the consul was at Perga he sent his brother L.
                        Manlius with a force of 4000 men to Oroanda to exact the rest of the money
                        which, according to the stipulation, was to be paid. On learning that
                        Eumenes and the ten commissioners from Rome had arrived at Ephesus, he led
                        his army back to Apamea and ordered the envoys from Antiochus to follow him.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Here the treaty as settled by the ten
                        commissioners was drawn up. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The substance
                        of it was as follows: "There shall be peace and amity between King Antiochus
                        and the Roman people on these terms and conditions: The king shall not
                        suffer any army purposing to levy war on the Roman people or their allies to
                        pass through the borders of his kingdom or of any subject to him, nor shall
                        he assist it with provisions or in any other way whatever. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The Romans and their allies shall act in like manner
                        towards Antiochus and those under his sway. Antiochus shall have no right to
                        levy war upon those who dwell in the islands, or to sail across to Europe.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He shall withdraw from all the cities,
                        lands, villages and forts west of the Taurus as far as the Halys and
                        extending from the lowlands of the Taurus up to the range which stretches
                        towards Lycaonia. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He shall not carry any
                        arms from the aforesaid towns and lands and forts from which he withdraws;
                        if he has carried any away he shall duly restore them to whatever place they
                        belong. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He shall not reclaim any soldier
                        or any other person whatever from the kingdom of Eumenes. If any citizens
                        belonging to the cities which are passing from under his rule are with
                        Antiochus or within the boundaries of his realm, they shall all return to
                        Apamea by a certain day; if any of Antiochus' subjects are with the Romans
                        and their allies they shall be at liberty to depart or to remain. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> He shall restore to the Romans and their allies
                        the slaves, whether fugitives or prisoners of war, or any free man who has
                        been taken captive or is a deserter. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He
                        shall give up his elephants and not procure any more. He shall likewise make
                        over his ships of war and all their tackle, nor shall he possess more than
                        ten light decked ships, none of which may be propelled by more than thirty
                        oars, and no smaller ones for use in any war which he may undertake.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He shall not take his ships west of
                        the headlands of the Calycadnus or the Sorpedon, save only such ships as
                        shall carry money or tribute or envoys or hostages. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Antiochus shall not have the right to hire mercenary
                        troops from those nations which shall be under the suzerainty of Rome nor to
                        accept them even as volunteers. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Such
                        houses and buildings as belonged to the Rhodians and their allies within the
                        dominions of Antiochus shall be held by them on the same right as before the
                        war. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If any moneys are due to them they
                        shall have the same right to exact them, if aught has been taken from them,
                        they shall have the right of search and recovery. Whatever cities amongst
                        those that are to be surrendered they hold as a gift from Antiochus; he
                        shall withdraw the garrisons from them and provide for their due surrender.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He shall pay 12,000 Attic talents of
                        sterling silver in equal instalments over twelve years-the talent shall
                        weigh not less than 80 Roman pounds-and 540,000 modii of wheat. To King
                        Eumenes he shall pay 350 talents within five years, and in place of corn its
                        value in money, 127 talents. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He shall
                        give twenty hostages to the Romans and exchange them for others in three
                        years, that none may be less than eighteen or more than forty-five years of
                        age. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> If any of the allies of Rome shall
                        wantonly and without provocation make war on Antiochus, he shall have the
                        right to repel them <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> by force of arms,
                        always providing that he shall not hold any city by right of war or receive
                        it into friendship and amity. Disputes shall be determined before a judicial
                        tribunal, or if both parties shall so will it, by war." <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> There was an additional clause dealing with the
                        surrender of Hannibal, Thoas and Mnasilochus, <milestone n="18??"
                            unit="section"/> as well as Eubulidas and Philo of Chalcidaea, and also
                        a proviso that if it should afterwards be decided to add to, or repeal, or
                        alter any of the articles, that should be done without impairing the
                        validity of the treaty. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul took the oath to observe the
                        treaty, and Q. Minucius Thermus and L. Manlius who happened to have just
                        returned from Oroanda went to demand the oath from the king. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The consul also sent written instructions to Q.
                        Fabius Labeo, who was in command of the fleet, to proceed forthwith to
                        Patara and break up or burn all the king's ships which were stationed there.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Fifty decked ships were thus either
                        broken up or burnt. During this voyage he retook Telmessus, where the
                        inhabitants had been greatly alarmed at the sudden appearance of the fleet.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Leaving Lycia he continued his voyage,
                        and sailing through the Archipelago he landed in Greece, and stayed a few
                        days at Athens, waiting for the ships which he had ordered to follow him
                        from Ephesus. As soon as they entered the Peiraeus he returned with the
                        entire fleet to Italy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Amongst the things
                        which were to be taken from Antiochus were his elephants, and these Cn.
                        Manlius presented to Eumenes. He then commenced an investigation into the
                        circumstances of the different cities, many of which were in a state of
                        confusion owing to the political changes. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Ariarathes had about this time betrothed his daughter to Eumenes, and owing
                        to the latter's good offices half the indemnity demanded from him was
                        remitted. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the investigation into the
                        circumstances and position of the different cities was completed, the ten
                        commissioners decided each case upon its merits. Those which had been
                        tributary to Antiochus but whose sympathies had been with Rome were granted
                        immunity from all tribute. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Those who had
                        sided with Antiochus or paid tribute to Attalus were all ordered to pay
                        tribute to Eumenes. The natives of Colophon who were living at Notium,
                        together with the inhabitants of Cymae and Mylasa, were also specially named
                        as receiving immunity. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> To Clazomenae was
                        given the island of Drymussa, as well as immunity. They restored to the
                        Milesians the so-called "sacred ground," and the inhabitants of <milestone
                            n="10??" unit="section"/> Ilium received Rhoeteum and Gergithus as
                        additions to their territory not so much on account of services recently
                        rendered as in recognition of its being the original home, and for the same
                        reason Dardanus was granted its liberty. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        Chios, Zmyrna and Erythrae in return for their conspicuous loyalty in the
                        war received a grant of territory and were treated with especial honour.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The territory which the Phoceans had
                        held before the war was restored to them, and they were allowed to enjoy
                        their old constitution. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The grants made
                        to Rhodes under a former decree were confirmed; these included Lycia and
                        Caria as far as the Maeander, with the exception of Telmessus. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> The dominions of Eumenes were enlarged by the
                        addition of the European Chersonesus and Lysimachia, the forts, villages and
                        territory within the limits of Antiochus' rule; <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> in Asia the two Phrygias, the one on the Hellespont,
                        the other called "Greater Phrygia"; Mysia which Prusias had taken from him
                        was restored as well as Lycaonia, Milyas and Lydia, and the cities of
                        Tralles, Ephesus and Telmessus, which were specially named. <milestone
                            n="16" unit="section"/> With regard to Pamphylia a difficulty arose
                        between Eumenes and the envoys of Antiochus, as part of <milestone n="17??"
                            unit="section"/> it lies on one side the Taurus and part on the other,
                        and the matter was referred to the senate. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After these articles of peace had been
                        finally settled and accepted, Manlius proceeded to the Hellespont with the
                        ten commissioners and the whole of his army. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> Here he summoned the Gaulish chiefs to meet him and informed them of the
                        terms upon which they were to keep the peace with Eumenes, and warned them
                        that they must put a stop to their custom of making armed forays and confine
                        themselves to the limits of their own territories. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He then collected his ships from the whole extent of
                        the coast, and with the addition of Eumenes' fleet, which was brought up by
                        his brother Athenaeus, the consul was able to transport the whole of his
                        force to Europe. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The army was heavily
                        weighted with spoils of every description and its advance consequently
                        through the Chersonese was at a moderate pace till they reached Lysimachia.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Here they rested for some time in
                        order that their draught cattle might be as strong and fresh as possible
                        before they entered Thrace, as they generally dreaded the march through that
                        country. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The same day on which he left
                        Lysimachia the consul reached Melas, and the next day he arrived at Cypsela.
                        From Cypsela a ten miles' march over broken ground shut in by forests
                        awaited them. In view of the difficulties of the route the army was formed
                        into two divisions. One was ordered to march in advance, the other, at a
                        considerable distance, to bring up the rear. The baggage was placed between
                        them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This included the wagons carrying
                        the State money and other valuable booty. Whilst marching through a pass in
                        this order a body of Thracians drawn from the four tribes of Astii, Caeni,
                        Maduateni and Coreli, not more than 10,000 in number, occupied each side of
                        the road at its narrowest part. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was
                        generally thought that this was due to treachery on Philip's part, that he
                        knew the Romans would return through Thrace and was also aware of the amount
                        of money they were carrying. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The general was with the first division
                        and the broken and difficult ground made him anxious. As long as the armed
                        troops were passing through, the Thracians did not stir, but when they saw
                        that the vanguard had <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> cleared the
                        narrowest part of the pass and those behind were nowhere near, they attacked
                        the baggage and the pack animals, and killing the escort began to loot the
                        wagons, while others led off the horses with their packs. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The cries and shouts were first heard by those behind
                        who had already entered the pass; then they reached the leading division.
                        From both directions a rush was made to the centre, and irregular fighting
                        began at several points. The booty itself exposed the Thracians to
                        slaughter, hampered as they were by the loads they were carrying, and most
                        of them without arms that they might have their hands free for pillage.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The unfavourable ground on the other
                        hand exposed the Romans to the barbarians, who ran up through paths they
                        were familiar with or concealed themselves in the recesses of the rocks.
                        Even the packs and wagons obstructed the combatants and interfered with the
                        movements of one side or the other just as it chanced. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Here a plunderer fell; there, one trying to recover the
                        plunder. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The fortunes of the battle
                        changed as first one side and then the other was on favourable or
                        unfavourable ground; as the courage of each rose or fell; as the numbers
                        preponderated on either side, some engaged with larger, others with smaller
                        bodies than their own. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Many fell on both
                        sides and night was already coming on when the Thracians drew off from the
                        fight, not to escape wounds and death, but because they had as much plunder
                        as they wanted. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When they had got clear of the pass, the
                        first division of the Roman army encamped on open ground near the temple of
                        Bendis. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The second remained in the pass to
                        protect the baggage train which they enclosed with a double rampart. The
                        next day after reconnoitring the pass, they joined the front division.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The fighting had practically extended
                        the whole length of the pass, a portion of the pack animals and camp
                        servants had fallen and a considerable number of soldiers. But the most
                        serious loss was that of the gallant and energetic Q. Minucius Thermus.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In the course of the day they reached
                        the Hebrus, and from there they marched past a temple to the Zerynthian
                        Apollo, as the natives call him, into the country of the Aenians. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Another defile near Tempyra had to be crossed,
                        not less precipitous than the one already surmounted, but as there was no
                        wooded country around it, it afforded no concealment for an ambush.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Another Thracian tribe, the Thrausi,
                        had assembled here, quite as greedy of plunder, but their movements, as they
                        tried to block the pass, were visible from afar owing to the bareness of the
                        landscape. The Romans were very little perturbed as though the ground was
                        ill-adapted for maneuvering, they saw that they could fight on a proper
                        front in a regular action. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Charging in
                        close order and raising their battle-cry they drove the enemy from his
                        ground and then put him to flight. The narrowness of the pass crowded the
                        fugitives together, and there was much slaughter. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The victorious Romans encamped at a
                        village belonging to Maronia called Sale. The following day, marching
                        through open country, they entered the plain of Priantae. Here they
                        remained, taking in corn partly from the country people, who brought it in
                        from their fields, and partly from the ships of <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> the fleet which were loaded with all sorts of stores
                        and were following their movements. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> A
                        day's march brought them to Apollonia and from here, through the district of
                        Abdera, they arrived at Neapolis. The whole of this march through the Greek
                        colonies was unmolested, but the other part through the heart of Thrace,
                        though not actually opposed, demanded caution both by day and night.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When this army traversed the same
                        route under Scipio they found the Thracians less aggressive; the only reason
                        for this being that there was less chance of plunder, plunder being their
                        one object. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> We are, however, told by
                        Claudius that a body of Thracians, amounting to some 15,000, sought to
                        oppose Muttines the Numidian, who was reconnoitring in advance of the main
                        army. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> There were 400 Numidian cavalry and
                        a few elephants; the son of Muttines, with 150 picked troopers, rode through
                        the middle of the enemy, and after Muttines with his elephants in the centre
                        and his cavalry on the flanks had engaged the enemy, his <milestone n="14??"
                            unit="section"/> son attacked their rear and created such disorder
                        amongst them that they never got near the main body of infantry. Passing
                        through Macedonia, Cn. Manlius led his army into Thessaly and finally
                        reached Apollonia. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Here he remained for
                        the winter, as the dangers of a winter voyage were not yet so contemptible
                        that he could venture to cross. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was almost at the close of the year
                        that the consul M. Valerius came from Liguria to elect new magistrates. He
                        had done nothing worth mentioning in his province, and this might have been
                        the reason why he had come at a later date <milestone n="2??" unit="section"
                        /> than usual to conduct the elections. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        The consular elections were held on February 18; the new consuls were M.
                        Aemilius Lepidus and C. Flaminius. The praetors elected on the following day
                        were Ap. Claudius Pulcher, Ser. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Sulpicius
                        Galba, Q. Terentius Culleo, L. Terentius Massiliota, Q. Fulvius Flaccus, and
                        M. Furius Crassipes. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the elections
                        were over the consuls asked the senate to settle what provinces were to be
                        assigned to the praetors. They decreed that there should be two in Rome for
                        the administration of justice; two outside Italy, namely Sicily and
                        Sardinia; two in Italy itself, namely Tarentum and Gaul; and the praetors
                        were ordered to ballot at once for these before they took office. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> The civic jurisdiction fell to Ser. Sulpicius,
                        the alien to Q. Terentius, Sicily went to L. Terentius, Sardinia to Q.
                        Fulvius, Tarentum to Ap. Claudius, and Gaul to M. Furius. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> During the year L. Minucius Myrtilus and L. Manlius
                        were charged with having beaten the Carthaginian ambassadors. They were
                        handed over to them by the fetials and carried off to Carthage. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There were rumours of a warlike movement
                        on a large scale in Liguria, which was every day growing more serious. In
                        consequence of this the senate decreed that both the consuls should have
                        Liguria as their province. The consul Lepidus opposed this resolution and
                        protested against both consuls being confined to the valleys of Liguria.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> M. Fulvius, he said, and Cn. Manlius
                        had now for two years been acting like kings, the one in Europe, the other
                        in Asia, as though they had replaced Philip and Antiochus on their thrones.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If it was the pleasure of the senate
                        that there should be armies in those countries it was more fitting that
                        consuls should command them than unofficial citizens. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> They were visiting with all the horrors of war nations
                        against whom no war had been proclaimed, and selling peace to them at a
                        price. If it was necessary that armies should occupy those provinces, then
                        C. Livius and M. Valerius as consuls ought to succeed Fulvius and Manlius,
                        just as L. Scipio, when consul, succeeded Manius Acilias, and M. Fulvius and
                        Cn. Manlius, when they became consuls, succeeded L. Scipio. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> Now, at all events, seeing that the war in
                        Aetolia was at an end, Asia taken from Antiochus, and the Gauls subjugated,
                        either consuls ought to be sent to command consular armies, or the legions
                        brought home and restored to the republic. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                        /> After listening to this speech the senate adhered to their decision that
                        Liguria should be the province of both consuls, and Manlius and Fulvius were
                        to resign their provinces, bring their armies away and return to Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> M. Fulvius and M. Aemilius were on bad
                        terms with one another, the main cause being Aemilius' suspicion that it was
                        owing to Fulvius that he had been made consul two years later than he ought
                        to have been. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In order to stir up odium
                        against him, he introduced into the senate some delegates from Ambracia who
                        had been suborned to bring charges against him. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> They asserted that while they were at peace and had
                        done all that the former consuls had required of them and were prepared to
                        show the same obedience to M. Fulvius, war was declared against them, their
                        fields were ravaged, the terror created by the bloodshed and pillage reached
                        their city and compelled them to close their gates. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Then they were besieged, their city carried by storm,
                        and all the horrors of war, fire and slaughter, wreaked upon them, their
                        homes demolished, their city completely sacked, their wives and children
                        dragged <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> off into slavery, their goods
                        carried away, and what they felt most bitterly of all, the temples in the
                        city stripped of their adornments, the statues of their gods, or rather the
                        gods themselves, torn from their shrines and carried away. All that was left
                        to the Ambracians were the naked walls and the columns to receive their
                        worship or hear their supplications and prayers. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst they were stating these grievances the consul,
                        as previously arranged, questioned them as to other charges, and elicited
                        answers made with apparent reluctance. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The House was impressed by these
                        statements and the other consul took up the cause of Fulvius. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> He pointed out that the Ambracians had taken an
                        old and outworn course; just in the same way had M. Marcellus been accused
                        by the Syracusans, and Q. Fulvius by the Campanians. Why might not the
                        senate allow charges to be brought on similar grounds against T. Quinctius
                        by Philip, against Manius Acilius and L. Scipio by Antiochus, against Cn.
                        Manlius by the Gauls, against M. Fulvius himself by the Aetolians and
                        Cephallanians? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> "Ambracia," he went on to
                        say, "has been taken by storm, the statues and temple ornaments have been
                        carried away, and everything has happened which usually does happen at the
                        capture of cities. Do you think, senators, that either I, speaking for
                        Fulvius, or M. Fulvius himself, will deny this? <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> He is going to demand a triumph just because he has
                        done all this, and will carry in front of his chariot and fasten on the
                        pillars of his house the captured Ambracia and the statues which he is
                        alleged to have criminally removed. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> There
                        is nothing to separate the case of the Ambracians from that of the
                        Aetolians, the cause of the one is the cause of the other. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> My colleague must display his enmity in some other case
                        or if he prefers the present one, he must keep his Ambracians till Fulvius
                        returns. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> I will not allow any decree to
                        be passed in respect of either the Ambracians or the Aetolians in M.
                        Fulvius' absence." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Aemilius continued to attack his enemy and
                        declared that his cunning and malice were notorious, and that Fulvius would
                        manage to delay matters so as not to come to Rome while his adversary was
                        consul. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Two days were thus wasted in the
                        quarrel between the consuls. It was clear that while Faminius was present no
                        decision could be arrived at. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Owing to
                        Flaminius' absence through illness, Aemilius seized the opportunity to move
                        a resolution which the senate adopted. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Its
                        purport was that the Ambracians should have all their property restored to
                        them; they should be free to live under their own laws; they should impose
                        such harbour dues and other imposts by land and sea as they desired,
                        provided that the Romans and their Italian allies were exempt. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> With regard to the statues and ornaments which
                        they said had been taken from their temples, it was decided that after
                        Fulvius' return their ultimate disposal should be referred to the pontifical
                        college, and what they deemed right would be done. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The consul was not content with this; subsequently in a
                        thinly attended House he got a clause added to the effect that there was no
                        evidence that Ambracia had been taken by storm. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> In consequence of a serious epidemic which ravaged City
                        and country alike, the Keepers of the Sacred Books decreed that special
                        sacrifices and intercessions should be offered for three days. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> Then came the Latin Festival. When the consuls
                        were free from these religious duties and had raised what men they
                        required-they both preferred to employ fresh troops-they left for their
                        province and disbanded all the old troops. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        After their departure Cneius Manlius arrived at Rome, and the praetor S.
                        Servilius convened a meeting of the senate to grant an audience. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> After giving a report of what he had done, he
                        asked that in recognition of these services, honours should be paid to the
                        immortal gods and permission given to him to enter the City in triumph.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The majority of the ten commissioners
                        who had been with him opposed this demand, especially L. Furius Purpurio and
                        L. Aemilius Paulus. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They had been appointed, they said, to act
                        as commissioners with Cn. Manlius for the purpose of concluding peace with
                        Antiochus and finally settling the terms of the treaty which had been
                        outlined by L. Scipio. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Cn. Manlius did his
                        utmost to upset the negotiations and, if he got the chance, to inveigle the
                        king into his power. When the king became aware of the consul's designs,
                        though he was frequently invited to a personal interview, he avoided not
                        only meeting him but even the very sight of him. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> When the consul was bent upon crossing the Taurus
                        range, it was with the utmost difficulty that he was prevented from doing so
                        by the commissioners, who warned him against tempting the doom foretold in
                        the Sibylline Books for every one who overpassed the limits fixed by Fate.
                        Nevertheless, he marched his army up and encamped almost on the summit where
                        the mountain streams flow opposite ways. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        When he found that the king's subjects remained perfectly quiet and that
                        there was nothing to justify hostilities, he led his troops round against
                        the Gallograeci, <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> a nation against whom
                        no declaration of war had been made either by the authority of the senate or
                        the order of the people. Who else would have ever dared to do such a thing?
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The wars with Antiochus, Philip,
                        Hannibal and Carthage were fresh in all men's memories; in every one of
                        these the senate issued its decree and the people their mandate; envoys had
                        been sent beforehand frequently to demand satisfaction, and as a final step
                        to declare war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> "Which of these
                        preliminaries," the speaker continued, "has been so observed by you, Cn.
                        Manlius, as to make us regard that war as waged by the people of Rome and
                        not simply as a marauding expedition of your own? <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> But were you ever content with that? Did you march your
                        army straight against those whom you had elected to regard as your enemies?
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Did you not on the contrary make a
                        roundabout march through winding roads, halting at all the cross-roads in
                        order that in whatever direction Eumenes' brother Attalus should direct his
                        march, you might follow him like a mercenary captain, you, a consul with a
                        Roman army? Did you not visit every hole and corner of Pisidia, Lycaonia,
                        and Phrygia, collecting money from the tyrants and their officers scattered
                        through the land? What business had you, pray, to interfere with Oroanda or
                        with other equally unoffending communities? But about this war, on the
                        strength of which you are seeking a triumph, in what way did you conduct it?
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Did you fight on favourable ground,
                        at a time of your own choosing? You are certainly right in claiming that
                        honours should be paid to the immortal gods. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> For in the first place they would not let the army pay
                        the penalty of its commander's recklessness in making an aggressive war in
                        defiance of the law of nations, and in the second place they brought against
                        us wild animals not men. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="46" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Do not suppose, senators, that it is only
                        in their name that the Gallograeci are a mixed race; it is much more their
                        bodies and minds that have become mixed and corrupted. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> If they had been real Gauls like those with whom we
                        have fought numberless doubtful battles in Italy, would a single man, so far
                        as our general is concerned, have returned to tell the story? <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> He fought with them twice. On both occasions he
                        advanced against them at a disadvantage, and from his lower ground almost
                        placed his line under the enemy's feet, so that, without discharging their
                        weapons from above, by simply hurling their naked bodies upon us, they could
                        have overwhelmed us. What, then, occurred to prevent this? <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Great is the Fortune of the Roman people, great and
                        terrible its name! The recent downfall of Hannibal, of Philip, of Antiochus,
                        had almost stunned the Gauls. With all their huge bulk they were put to
                        flight by slings and arrows, not a sword in the army was stained by the
                        blood of a Gaul, they fled away like flocks of birds at the first whirr of
                        our missiles. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Yes, but Fortune also warned
                        us what would have happened to us then, if we had had a real enemy.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On our return march we fell amongst
                        Thracian brigands, and were killed, put to flight, and stripped of our
                        baggage. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Q. Minucius Thermus fell,
                        together with many brave men, and his loss was much more serious than that
                        of Cn. Manlius would have been, through whose foolhardiness the disaster
                        occurred. The army which was bringing home the spoil taken from Antiochus
                        was dispersed in three sections, the van in one place, the rear in another,
                        and the baggage in another, and they lay down one night amongst thickets and
                        lairs of wild beasts. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Is it for these
                        exploits that a triumph is asked for? Supposing no ignominious defeat had
                        been sustained in Thrace, over what enemy would you seek triumph? <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Over those, I presume, whom the senate or the
                        people of Rome had assigned to you as your enemy. On these terms a triumph
                        was granted to L. Scipio, to Manius Acilius over Antiochus, to T. Quinctius,
                        a little earlier, over Philip, to P. Africanus over Hannibal and Carthage
                        and Syphax. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And even when the senate has
                        voted for war, certain minor questions have had to be answered-as to whom
                        the declaration of war ought to be made, whether in any case to the kings
                        themselves, or whether it would be sufficient to proclaim it at one of his
                        frontier garrisons. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Do you then,
                        senators, want all these formalities to be treated with scorn, the solemn
                        procedure of the fetials to be abolished, and the fetials themselves to be
                        done away with? Suppose all religious scruples-the gods forgive me for
                        saying it! <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> were cast to the winds and
                        forgetfulness of the gods took possession of your hearts, should you still
                        think it right that the senate should not be consulted as to war, or the
                        question referred to the people whether it was their will and order that war
                        should be waged with the Gauls? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Recently,
                        at all events, when the consuls wanted to have Greece and Asia as their
                        provinces, you held to your resolution to decree Liguria as their province,
                        and they submitted to your authority. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        Deservedly, therefore, will they ask for a triumph, after their successes,
                        from you under whose authority they will have achieved them." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="47" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This was the substance of what Furius and
                        Aemilius said. I understand that Manlius spoke to the following effect:
                        "Formerly, senators, it was the tribunes of the plebs who usually opposed
                        those who claimed a triumph. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> I am grateful
                        to them for having conceded this much to me, either personally or in
                        acknowledgment of the greatness of my services, that they not only showed by
                        their silence their approval of my being thus honoured, but were even ready,
                        if necessary, to recommend it to the senate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> It is amongst the ten commissioners that I find my opponents, those whom
                        our ancestors assigned to their commanders for the purpose of gathering the
                        fruits of their victories and enhancing their glory. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> L. Furius and L. Aemilius forbid me to enter the
                        triumphal chariot; they snatch the victor's wreath from my brow; these very
                        men whom I was going to call as witnesses to what I have done, had the
                        tribunes opposed my triumph. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I envy no man
                        his honours, senators. Only the other day when the tribunes of the plebs
                        were trying to prevent the triumph of Q. Fabius Labeo, strong and determined
                        as they were, you overawed them by your authority. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> His enemies laid it to his charge, not that he had
                        fought an unjust war, but that he had never even seen an enemy. Still he
                        enjoyed his triumph. I, who have fought so many pitched battles with 100,000
                        of our fiercest enemies, who have killed or taken prisoners 40,000, who have
                        stormed two of their camps, who have left all the country this side the
                        Taurus more peaceable than the land of Italy-I am not only being defrauded
                        of my triumph, but actually have to defend myself <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> before you against the accusations of my commissioners. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> "You have noticed, senators, that they
                        bring a double charge against me; that I ought not to have made war on the
                        Gauls, and that I conducted it in a rash and imprudent way. 'The Gauls,'
                        they say, 'were not hostile to us, but you wantonly attacked them while they
                        were quietly carrying out your orders.' <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> I
                        am not going to ask you, senators, to judge the Gauls who inhabit those
                        countries from what you know of the savagery common to the race, and their
                        deadly hatred to the name of Rome. Keep out of sight the infamous and
                        hateful character of the race as a whole and judge those men by themselves.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> I wish Eumenes, I wish all the cities
                        of Asia were here, and that you were hearing their complaints rather than
                        the charges I am bringing. Send commissioners to visit all the cities of
                        Asia and find out which has delivered them from the heavier thraldom, the
                        removal of Antiochus beyond the Taurus or the subjugation of the Gauls.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Let them bring back word how often
                        the fields of those people have been devastated, how often they and all
                        their property have been <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> carried off,
                        with hardly a chance of ransoming the captives, and knowing that human
                        victims were being sacrificed and their children immolated. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> Let me tell you that your allies paid tribute to
                        the Gauls, and would have been paying it now, though freed from the rule of
                        Antiochus, if it had not been put a stop to by me. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="48" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "The greater the distance to which
                        Antiochus was removed, the more tyrannically did the Gauls lord it over
                        Asia; by his removal you added whatever lands lie on this side the Taurus to
                        their dominion, not your own. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But you say,
                        'Assuming this to be true, the Gauls once despoiled Delphi, but though it
                        was the one oracle common to all mankind, and the central spot in the whole
                        world, the Romans did not on that account declare or commence war against
                        them.' <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> I should certainly have thought
                        that there was a considerable difference between the conditions existing
                        when Greece and Asia had not yet passed under your suzerainty, as far as
                        regards your interest and concern in their affairs, and the conditions
                        prevailing now; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> when you have fixed the
                        Taurus as the frontier of your dominion; when you are giving to the cities
                        liberty and immunity from tribute; when you are enlarging the territories of
                        some and depriving others of their land by way of punishment or imposing
                        tribute: when you are extending, diminishing, giving, taking away kingdoms,
                        and making it your one care that they shall keep the peace both on land and
                        sea. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Would you consider that the liberty
                        of Asia would not have been secure had not Antiochus withdrawn his
                        garrisons, which were remaining quietly in their quarters, and do you
                        suppose that your gifts to Eumenes would be safe or the cities retain their
                        freedom as <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> long as the armies of the
                        Gauls were roaming far and wide? </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> "But why do I use these arguments, as
                        though I had made the Gauls into enemies and had not found them such
                        already? I appeal to you, L. Scipio, whose valour and good fortune alike I
                        prayed to the immortal gods-and not in vain-to grant me, when I succeeded to
                        your command; I appeal to you, P. Scipio, who though subordinate to your
                        brother the consul, still possessed both with him and the army all the
                        authority of a colleague; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and I ask you
                        whether you know that there were legions of Gauls in the army of Antiochus;
                        whether you saw that they were posted at either end of his line, for there
                        his main strength seemed to be; whether you fought with them as regular
                        enemies, and killed them and brought their spoils home. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> And yet the war which the senate had decreed and the
                        people ordered was a war against Antiochus, not against the Gauls.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Yes, but I hold that the decree and
                        order included those who had formed part of his army, and amongst these-with
                        the exception of Antiochus with whom Scipio had concluded peace and with
                        whom you ordered a special treaty to be made-all who bore arms on his behalf
                        were our enemies. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Gauls above all
                        supported his cause, as did also some petty kings and tyrants. With the
                        others, however, I made peace and compelled them to make an expiation for
                        their misdoings proportionate to the dignity of your empire, and I tried to
                        influence the Gauls, if haply their innate ferocity could be mitigated. When
                        I saw that they remained untameable and implacable, I thought they ought to
                        be coerced by force of arms. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> "Now that I have cleared myself of the
                        charge of wanton aggression, I have to account for my conduct of the war.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> On this topic I should feel perfect
                        confidence in my case, even if I were pleading not before the Romans but
                        before the Carthaginian senate, where it is said that their generals are
                        crucified, even when successful, if their strategy has been faulty.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> But this State has recourse to the
                        gods at the commencement and during the conduct of all its business, because
                        it will not have those matters which the gods have approved of open to any
                        man's censure, and when it decrees special thanksgivings or a triumph,
                        employs the solemn formula: 'Whereas he has managed the affairs of the
                        Republic with success and good fortune.' <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        If, then, renouncing all assertion of my own merits as arrogant and
                        presumptuous, I were to demand on behalf of my own good fortune and that of
                        my army, in having crushed so powerful a nation without any loss, that
                        honours should be paid to the immortal gods, and that <milestone n="16??"
                            unit="section"/> I, myself, should go up in triumph to the Capitol, from
                        whence I started after my vows and prayers had been duly offered, would you
                        refuse this to me and to the immortal gods as well? </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="49" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "But, they say, I fought on unfavourable
                        ground. Then tell me where I could have fought at less disadvantage. The
                        enemy had occupied the mountain, they kept themselves within their lines;
                        surely if I was to win the battle it was necessary for me to advance against
                        them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> How would it have been if they had
                        been holding a city there and keeping within its walls? Of course, they must
                        have been attacked. Why, did not Manius Acilius engage Antiochus on
                        unfavourable ground at Thermopylae? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Did
                        not T. Quinctius under similar conditions dislodge Philip when he was
                        holding the heights above the Aous? So far I am unable to make out what sort
                        of an enemy they are picturing to themselves, or in what light they wish you
                        to regard him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If they say that he has
                        degenerated and become enervated by the attractions and luxuries of Asia,
                        what risk did we run in attacking him even when we were in a bad position?
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If they regard him as formidable,
                        owing to ferocity and physical strength, do you refuse a triumph for so
                        great a victory? Envy, senators, is blind and knows no other method than
                        that of disparaging merit and soiling its honours and rewards. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> I crave your indulgence, senators, if the
                        necessity of defending myself against accusations, and not a desire to sound
                        my praises, has made my speech somewhat long. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Was it in my power when marching through Thrace to make
                        the narrow passes into open country, the broken road into level ground, the
                        forests into open fields? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Could I have
                        made such dispositions as to prevent the Thracian banditti from concealing
                        themselves in lurking-places with which they were perfectly familiar, or any
                        of our baggage from being stolen, or any pack animal from being carried off
                        from so long a column, or a single man from being wounded, or that gallant
                        soldier, Q. Minucius, from dying of his wounds? <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> They make a great point of that sad misfortune,
                        involving as it did the loss of so good a citizen. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> But the fact of our two divisions at the front and rear
                        of the column having hemmed in the barbarians when busy in looting our
                        baggage, after attacking in a difficult pass on ground wholly against us;
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> the fact that those two divisions
                        killed or took prisoners many thousands of the enemy on that day and many
                        more a few days later-if they have been silent as to these facts, are they
                        not aware that you will know them when the whole army can testify to what I
                        say? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If I had never drawn the sword in
                        Asia, or seen an enemy there, I should still have deserved a triumph for
                        those two battles in Thrace. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But I have
                        said enough and would only ask for and, I hope, receive your indulgence for
                        having wearied you by speaking at greater length than I wished." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="50" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The attack would that day have prevailed
                        over the defence had they not protracted the debate to a late hour. When the
                        House rose, the general opinion was that it would in all likelihood refuse
                        the triumph. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The next day the friends and
                        relatives of Cn. Manlius exerted their utmost efforts, and the authority of
                        the older senators prevailed. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They said
                        that there was no instance on record of a commander who had brought back his
                        army, after subjugating a dangerous enemy and reducing his province to
                        order, entering the city in an unofficial and private capacity without the
                        chariot and laurels of triumph. The sense of the indignity of such a
                        proceeding was too strong for the aspersions of his enemies, and a full
                        senate decreed to him a triumph. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> All
                        discussion and even recollection of this dispute were lost in the outbreak
                        of a more serious controversy with a greater and more distinguished man.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> We are told on the authority of
                        Valerius Antias that the two Petillii instituted proceedings against P.
                        Scipio Africanus. Men put different interpretations on this according to
                        their various dispositions. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Some blamed,
                        not the tribunes only, but the whole body of citizens, for letting such a
                        thing be possible; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> the two greatest cities
                        in the world, they said, had proved themselves, almost at the same time,
                        ungrateful to their foremost men. Rome was the more ungrateful of the two,
                        for whilst Carthage after her defeat drove the defeated Hannibal into exile,
                        Rome would banish the victorious Scipio in the hour of her victory.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Others again took the ground that no
                        single citizen should stand on such an eminence that he could not be
                        required to answer according to law. Nothing contributed more towards
                        maintaining liberty for all than the power of putting the most powerful
                        citizen on his trial. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> What business, it
                        was asked-not to mention the supreme interests of the State-could be
                        entrusted to any man, if he had not to render an account for it? If a man
                        cannot submit to laws which are the same for all, no force which may be
                        employed against him is unlawful. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> So the
                        matter was discussed until the day of trial came. Never before had anyone,
                        even Scipio himself when he was consul or censor, been surrounded by a
                        greater concourse of people of all sorts and conditions than on the day when
                        he was conducted into the Forum to make his defence. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> When he was called upon to plead, he made no allusion
                        whatever to the charges brought against him, but spoke of the services he
                        had rendered in such a lofty tone that it was universally felt that no man
                        had ever deserved higher or truer praise. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        He described his actions in the spirit and temper in which he had performed
                        them, and he was listened to without any impatience because they were
                        recounted not in self-glorification but in self-defence. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="51" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In order to support the charges they were
                        bringing against him, the tribunes brought up the old story of his luxurious
                        living in his winter quarters in Syracuse and the disturbance created by
                        Pleminius at Locri. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They then went on to
                        accuse him of having received bribes, more on grounds of suspicion than by
                        direct proof; they alleged that his son who was taken prisoner was restored
                        to him without ransom; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> that Antiochus had
                        in every way tried to ingratiate himself with Scipio as though peace and war
                        with Rome were solely in his hands; that Scipio had behaved towards the
                        consul in his province as dictator rather than subordinate; that he had gone
                        out with no other object than to make clear to Greece and Asia and all the
                        kings and nationalities in the East what had long been the settled
                        conviction of Spain and Gaul and Sicily and Africa, that he alone was the
                        head and mainstay of Roman sovereignty; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        that under Scipio's shadow the mistress city of the world lay sheltered and
                        that his nod took the place of the decrees of the senate and the orders of
                        the people. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> No stigma of disgrace could be
                        fastened upon him, so they did their utmost to excite popular odium against
                        him. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As the speeches went on till night,
                        the proceedings were adjourned. When the next day for the hearing came, the
                        tribunes took their seats on the Rostra at daybreak. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The defendant was summoned, and passing through the
                        middle of the Assembly accompanied by a large body of friends and clients,
                        stood before the Rostra. Silence having been called he spoke as follows: </p>
                    <p> "Tribunes of the plebs, and you, Quirites, this is the anniversary of the
                        day on which I fought with success and good fortune a pitched battle against
                        Hannibal and the Carthaginians. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It is
                        therefore only right and fitting that on this day all pleas and actions
                        should be suspended. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> I am going at once to
                        the Capitol and the Citadel to make my devotions to Jupiter Optimus Maximus,
                        and Juno and Minerva and all the other tutelar deities of the Capitol and
                        the Citadel, and to offer up thanksgivings to them for having given me as on
                        this day the wisdom and the strength to do the Republic exceptional service.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Those of you, Quirites, who are at
                        liberty to do so, come with me. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> You have
                        always from my seventeenth year down to this period of my old age advanced
                        me to honours before I was of the age for them, and I have always
                        forestalled your honours by my services; then pray now to the gods that you
                        may always have leaders like me." <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> From
                        the Rostra he went straight up to the Capitol, and the whole Assembly
                        turning their backs on the tribunes followed him; even the secretaries and
                        apparitors left the tribunes; there was no one with them except their
                        attendant slaves and the usher who used to stand at the Rostra and call the
                        defendants. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Scipio not only went up to
                        the Capitol; he visited all the temples throughout the City, accompanied by
                        the Roman people. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The enthusiasm of the
                        citizens and their recognition of his real greatness made that day almost a
                        more glorious one for him than when he entered the City in triumph after his
                        victories over Syphax and the Carthaginians. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="52" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This splendid day was the last day of
                        brightness for Scipio. He saw before him envious attacks and contests with
                        the tribunes, and so after a somewhat lengthy adjournment had been agreed
                        upon, he retired to Liternum, firmly resolved not to appear in his defence.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> His spirit was too high, his mind too
                        great; he had all through held a position too lofty to allow him to accept
                        the position of a defendant or submit to the humiliation of having to plead
                        his cause. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When the day arrived and his
                        name was called, L. Scipio apologised for his absence on the ground of
                        ill-health. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The prosecuting tribunes did
                        not accept the excuse and gave out that his refusal to appear was dictated
                        by the same spirit of pride and arrogance in which he had left the seat of
                        judgment and the tribunes and the Assembly. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> Surrounded by the very men whom he had deprived of the right and liberty
                        of passing sentence upon him, and dragging them after him like prisoners of
                        war, he had celebrated a triumph over the people of Rome and had made a
                        secession on that day from the tribunes to the Capitol. "So now," they
                        continued, "you have the due reward of your folly; the man at whose
                        instigation and under whose leadership you deserted us, has now deserted
                        you. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> So low is our courage falling day by
                        day, that the man whom <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> seventeen years
                        ago we dared to send tribunes to Sicily to apprehend, whilst he had an army
                        and a fleet at his command, that man we dare not now, though he is only a
                        private citizen, fetch from his country-house to stand his trial." L. Scipio
                        appealed to the tribunes of the plebs as a body, and they passed the
                        following resolution: "If illness be pleaded as an excuse, it is our
                        pleasure that this excuse be accepted, and our colleagues must again adjourn
                        the day of trial." <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Tiberius Sempronius
                        Gracchus was one of the tribunes. He was a political opponent of Scipio, and
                        had forbidden his colleagues to add his name to their resolution. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> It was generally expected that he would give a
                        more severe sentence, but he drew up a resolution in the following terms:
                        "Since L. Scipio has pleaded illness as the reason for his brother's
                        absence, I hold that to be sufficient excuse, and will not allow P. Scipio
                        to be put on his trial before his return to Rome; <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> even then, if he appeals to me, I will support him in
                        any effort to avoid a trial. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Scipio has
                        by the common consent of gods and men attained such a lofty position through
                        his own acts and the honours which the Roman people have conferred upon him,
                        that for him to stand beneath the Rostra as a defendant, and have to listen
                        to the insults of young men, would be a greater ignominy for the people of
                        Rome than for him." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="53" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He followed this up by an indignant
                        speech: Is Scipio, the conqueror of Africa, to stand at your feet, tribunes?
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Was it for this that he broke and
                        routed four armies in Spain under the most famous generals that Carthage
                        possessed? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Was it for this that he
                        captured Syphax and crushed Hannibal, made Carthage tributary to us, removed
                        Antiochus beyond the Taurus-for his brother Lucius allowed him to share his
                        glory-was it simply that he might succumb to the two Petillii, and that you
                        might claim the palm of victory over Publius Africanus. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Will you allow the claim, citizens? Will illustrious
                        men never either through their own merits or the honours you confer, reach a
                        safe, and if I may say so, a sacred asylum where their old age may rest, if
                        not venerated, at least inviolate?" <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> His
                        resolution and the speech which followed it had their effect upon the other
                        tribunes, even upon the prosecutors, who said that they would deliberate as
                        to what their right and duty demanded. After the Assembly broke up, a
                        meeting of the senate was held. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Here a
                        most hearty vote of thanks to Tiberius Gracchus was passed by the whole
                        order, especially the men of consular rank and the elder senators, for
                        having placed the interests of the State before his own private feelings,
                        and the Petillii were taunted with wanting to shine by darkening another's
                        reputation and enrich themselves by a triumph over Africanus. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> After this nothing more was said about
                        proceedings against Scipio. He passed his life at Liternum without any wish
                        to return to the City, and it is said <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                        that on his death-bed he gave orders that he should be buried and his
                        monument set up there, so that there might be no funeral rites performed for
                        him by his ungrateful country. He was an extraordinary man, more
                        distinguished, however in the arts of war than in those of peace. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> The earlier part of his life was more brilliant
                        than the later; as a young man he was constantly engaged in war; with
                        advancing years the glory of his achievements faded, and there was nothing
                        to call forth his genius. What additional lustre did his second consulship
                        confer as compared with his first, or even his censorship? <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> What further distinction did he gain during his
                        subordinate command in Asia, rendered useless through bad health and
                        saddened by the misfortune which overtook his son? Then, again, after his
                        return he was under the necessity of either standing his trial or of
                        absenting himself from his native city. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        Still, he alone won the unique glory of bringing the war with Carthage to a
                        close, the greatest and most serious war that the Romans have ever waged.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="54" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With the death of Africanus the courage of
                        his enemies rose. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The foremost of these
                        was M. Porcius Cato, who even during Scipio's lifetime was constantly
                        belittling his greatness, and it was at his instigation, it was thought,
                        that the Petillii attacked him whilst he was alive. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> After his death they introduced into the Assembly the
                        following motion: "Touching the money which was seized, confiscated and
                        exacted from Antiochus and his subjects, is it your will and pleasure,
                        Quirites, that in respect of such money as has not been accounted for to the
                        State, the City praetor Servius Sulpicius shall consult the senate as to
                        which of the acting praetors it shall appoint to investigate the matter?"
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The two Mummii, Quintus and Lucius,
                        interposed their veto to this proposal; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        they considered that where money had not been accounted for to the State, it
                        was only right and proper that the senate should conduct such investigation
                        as it always had done previously. The Petillii accused the nobility and the
                        despotic power which the Scipios possessed over the senate. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> L. Furius Purpurio, a man of consular rank, one of the
                        ten commissioners, thought that the inquiry ought to go further. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> By way of damaging his enemy Cn. Manlius, he
                        suggested that it ought to include not only the amount taken from Antiochus,
                        but all that had been taken from other kings and nations. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> L. Scipio, who it was evident would speak more in his
                        own defence than against the proposal, came forward to oppose it. He
                        protested strongly against this question being raised after the death of his
                        brother P. Africanus, of all men the bravest and most illustrious.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> No public eulogium had been made over
                        him when he died, but that was not enough, now accusations must be levelled
                        at him. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Even the Carthaginians were
                        content with banishing Hannibal; the Roman people were not satisfied with
                        the death of Africanus, but his reputation must be torn to pieces over his
                        tomb, and as an aggravation of malice, his brother also must be sacrificed.
                        M. Cato supported the motion; his speech, "Concerning the money of King
                        Antiochus," is still extant. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The weight
                        of his authority deterred the Mummii from opposing it, and as these withdrew
                        their veto, the proposal was earned by <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/>
                        the unanimous vote of the Tribes. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="55" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Ser. Sulpicius next consulted the senate
                        as to who was to conduct the inquiry, and they fixed upon Q. Terentius
                        Culleo. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There are some writers who assert
                        that this praetor was so attached to the family of the Cornelii that at the
                        funeral-they say he died and was buried in Rome-he preceded the bier wearing
                        a cap of liberty just as though he were marching in a triumphal procession,
                        and at the Porta Capena he distributed wine sweetened with honey to those
                        who followed the body, because amongst the other captives in Africa he had
                        been delivered by Scipio. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Another account
                        is that he was hostile to the family; that, knowing this, the party opposed
                        to the Scipios selected him as the one man to conduct the inquiry.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> However this may be, it was before
                        this praetor, whether biassed in favour of or against the defendant, that L.
                        Scipio was at once put on his trial. The names of his divisional commanders,
                        Aulus and Lucius Hostilius Cato, were also given in to the praetor, and
                        entered by him, as well as that of the quaestor C. Furius Aculeo; <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> and that his whole staff might appear to be
                        associated in the embezzlement, his two secretaries and his marshal were
                        also included. Lucius Hostilius, the secretaries and the marshal were all
                        acquitted before Scipio's case was heard. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        He, together with A. Hostilius and C. Furius, were found guilty-Scipio, of
                        having received 6000 pounds of gold and 480 of silver over and above what he
                        had brought into the treasury; and Hostilius was convicted of having
                        similarly embezzled 80 pounds of gold and 403 of silver; <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> the quaestor was found guilty of having received 130
                        pounds of gold and 200 of silver. These are the amounts I find as stated by
                        Antias. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In the case of L. Scipio, I should
                        prefer to regard these figures as a mistake on the part of the copyist,
                        rather than a false assertion of the author, for the weight of the silver
                        was in all probability greater than that of the gold, and the <milestone
                            n="9??" unit="section"/> fine was more likely to be fixed at 400,000
                        than at 2,400,000 sesterces, especially as it is stated that this was the
                        sum for which Publius Scipio was asked to account in the senate. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> It is also recorded that when he had told his
                        brother Lucius to fetch his account-book, he tore it up with his own hands
                            <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> while the senate was looking on,
                        and indignantly protested against an account for 400,000 <milestone n="12??"
                            unit="section"/> sesterces being demanded of him after he had brought
                        into the treasury 2,000,000. He is further stated to have shown the same
                        self-confidence in demanding the keys of the treasury, when the quaestors
                        did <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> not venture to bring the money out
                        as against the law, and declaring that as it was through him it was shut, so
                        he would open it. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="56" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There are many other details in which
                        writers differ, especially as regards his closing years, his impeachment,
                        his death, his funeral, and his tomb, so that I cannot decide what
                        traditions or documents to follow. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There
                        is no agreement as to the prosecutors. . Some say that M. Naevius, others
                        that the Petillii, initiated the proceedings; nor as to the date when they
                        began, nor the year in which he died, nor where he was buried. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Some say that he died and was buried in Rome;
                        others say in Liternum. In both places his monument and statues are shown.
                        At Liternum there was a monument surmounted by a statue which we have seen
                        lately, and which was overthrown by a storm. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> At Rome there are three statues above the monument of the Scipios; two
                        are said to be those of Publius and Lucius; the third that of the poet Q.
                        Ennius. Nor is it only the chroniclers who differ; even the speeches, if
                        they are really those of the men whose they are said to be, viz., <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> P. Scipio and Tiberius Gracchus, cannot be
                        brought into agreement. The title of Scipio's speech gives the prosecutor's
                        name as M. Naevius; in the speech itself the name does not appear; sometimes
                        he describes him as a knave, sometimes as a trifler. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Even the speech of Gracchus makes no mention of the
                        Petillii as the prosecutors of Africanus, nor of the actual proceedings.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Quite another story will have to be
                        put together to fit this speech of Gracchus, and we shall have to follow
                        those authorities who aver that at the time when Lucius Scipio was tried and
                        convicted of having taken bribes from the king, Africanus was serving in a
                        subordinate command in Etruria and, on hearing of the misfortune which had
                        befallen his brother, hurried back to Rome. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> On learning that his brother was being taken to prison, he went straight
                        to the Forum, drove off the officer who had charge of him and, his affection
                        for his brother getting the better of his citizenship, even used violence
                        towards the tribunes who tried to hold him back. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Gracchus himself complains that in this
                        instance the authority of the tribunes was successfully defied by a private
                        citizen, and at the end of his speech where he promises to support Scipio,
                        he adds that it would form a better precedent were it to appear that the
                        tribunitian and State authority had been overborne by a tribune of the plebs
                        rather than by a private citizen. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But
                        while he reproaches him bitterly for losing his self-control in this one
                        outbreak of lawlessness, and censures him for having fallen so far below
                        himself, he makes up for his censures in recalling the high esteem in which
                        Scipio was held in the old days for his equable and self-disciplined
                        character. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He reminded his hearers how
                        severely Scipio rebuked the people for wishing to make him perpetual consul
                        and dictator; how he had prevented them from raising statues to him in the
                        Comitium, the Rostra, the senate house, and in the shrine of Jupiter on the
                        Capitol, and how he had prevented a decree from being passed authorising his
                        image decked in triumphal garb to be borne in procession from the temple of
                        Jupiter Optimus Maximus. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> These things,
                        even if inserted in a public eulogium, would still be a proof of his
                        greatness of soul in keeping his honours within the limits of ordinary civic
                        life; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> how much more so when they are the
                        admissions of an enemy. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="57" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It is generally understood that the
                        younger of his two daughters was married to this same Gracchus, and the
                        elder one was certainly disposed of by her father to P. Cornelius Nasica,
                        but whether it was after her father's death is uncertain. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> It is equally uncertain whether the current belief in
                        the following story is well founded. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        story goes that when Gracchus saw that L. Scipio was on the point of being
                        carried off to prison and that none of his fellow-tribunes interfered on his
                        behalf, he swore that though his enmity towards the Scipios was as strong as
                        ever, and he would do nothing to <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> win his
                        favour, yet he would not look on whilst the brother of Africanus was being
                        taken to a dungeon into which he had seen Africanus himself taking kings and
                        commanders. The senate happened to be dining that day in the Capitol, and
                        rising in a body they begged Scipio to betroth his daughter to Gracchus
                        there and then. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The betrothal having been
                        formally completed in the presence of the whole gathering, Scipio went home.
                        On meeting his wife, he told her that he had betrothed their youngest
                        daughter. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> She was naturally hurt and
                        indignant at not having been consulted in the disposal of their child, and
                        observed that even if he were giving her to Tiberius Gracchus, her mother
                        ought to have had a voice in the matter. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Scipio was delighted to find that they were of one accord, and told her that
                        it was to that man that she was betrothed. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        It is right that in the case of so great a man the various opinions and the
                        different historical statements as to these details should be noted. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="58" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the praetor Q. Terentius had brought
                        the proceedings to a close, Hostilius and Furius, who had been convicted,
                        gave the required sureties to the City quaestors. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Scipio, who stoutly maintained that the whole of the
                        money he had received was in the treasury, and that he had none which
                        belonged to the State, was ordered off to prison. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> P. Scipio Nasica formally appealed to the tribunes in a
                        speech full of just and true encomiums on the house of the Cornelii and
                        particularly on his own family. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He pointed
                        out that the two distinguished men, Cn. and P. Scipio, were the fathers
                        respectively of himself, and of P. and L. Scipio, who was now being led to
                        prison. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These two men had for many years
                        fought in Spain against numerous armies of Carthaginians and Spaniards, and
                        had not only added to the glory of Rome, but after presenting to those two
                        nations an example of <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> Roman moderation
                        and good faith, had at last given their lives for the commonwealth. It would
                        have been enough had their glory been kept untarnished for posterity, but
                            <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> P. Africanus had so far surpassed
                        his father's renown that men believed him to be sprung from no human
                        parents, but to be of divine origin. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As to
                        Lucius Scipio, whose case was before them, he would pass over all that he
                        had done as his brother's lieutenant in Spain and Africa, and would remind
                        them that when he was consul the senate thought him worthy of being
                        entrusted with Asia and the war with Antiochus as his province, without
                        having recourse to the ballot. His brother, too, though he had been censor
                        and twice consul, and graced with a triumph, went to him to serve as his
                        lieutenant in Asia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Whilst he was there,
                        as though to prevent the greatness and splendour of the lieutenant from
                        eclipsing the fame of the consul, it so happened that on the day when Lucius
                        Scipio completely defeated Antiochus in the great battle of Magnesia,
                        Publius Scipio was several days' journey away, lying ill at Elaea.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The army that Lucius engaged was not
                        less than that which Hannibal commanded at the battle in Africa. Hannibal
                        who had commanded all through the Punic war was also among the generals with
                        Antiochus. The conduct of the war was such that no one could charge even
                        Fortune with caprice. It is in respect of the peace that the charges are
                        made; the peace is said to have been sold. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                        /> If so, the ten commissioners are also involved in the charge; it was on
                        their advice that the peace was granted. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        And though out of those ten men some came forward to accuse Cn. Manlius, not
                        only did they fail to prove their charge, they were not even able to delay
                        his triumph. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="59" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But in Scipio's case the very terms of the
                        peace formed the grounds of suspicion as being too favourable to Antiochus.
                        "His kingdom," they say, "has been left to him in its entirety; after his
                        defeat he remained in possession of all that had belonged to him before the
                        war. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Though he had a large amount of gold
                        and silver, none of it has been brought into the treasury; it has all passed
                        into private hands." <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Was not the amount of
                        gold and silver borne before all men's eyes in Lucius Scipio's triumph
                        greater than in any other ten triumphs if it were all collected together?
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> What am I to say about the limits of
                        the king's dominions? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Antiochus held all
                        Asia and the adjacent parts of Europe; how great a part of the world that
                        is, stretching from the Taurus to the Aegean, you all know. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> This tract of country, more than thirty days' march in
                        length and, measured from sea to sea, ten days' march in breadth, extending
                        right up to the Taurus, has been taken from Antiochus. He has been banished
                        to the most remote corner of the world. What more, pray, could have been
                        taken from him, even if peace had been granted without any conditions?
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After Philip's defeat, Macedonia was
                        left to him as Lacedaemon was to Nabis, and yet no criminal inquiry was
                        instituted against Quinctius. He had not Africanus for his brother, whose
                        great reputation ought to have helped Lucius instead of injuring him by the
                        jealousy it aroused. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was stated in the
                        trial that the amount of gold and silver brought into Lucius Scipio's house
                        was greater than could have been realised by the sale of the whole of his
                        property. Where, then, is that gold and silver and all the benefactions he
                        has received? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Surely this access of
                        fortune must have been in evidence in a house which is not wasted with
                        extravagance. Yes, but what cannot be got out of his property, his enemies
                        will get out of his person by insult and torture, in order that a man so
                        illustrious may be shut up with burglars and highwaymen in the <milestone
                            n="10??" unit="section"/> inmost dungeon and breathe out his life in
                        darkness, and his naked body flung out of the prison doors. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> That would not bring a deeper disgrace upon the
                        house of the Cornelii than upon the whole City of Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="60" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Terentius, in reply, read the resolution
                        carried by the Petillii, the decision of the senate and the sentence passed
                        upon L. Scipio. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He declared that unless
                        the sum stated in the judgment were restored to the treasury, there was no
                        other course open to him but to order him to be arrested and taken to
                        prison. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The tribunes retired for
                        consultation and shortly afterwards C. Fannius, in the name of all his
                        colleagues except Gracchus, declared that they would not intervene to
                        prevent the praetor from exercising his authority. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> T. Gracchus gave his decision thus: He would not oppose
                        the action of the praetor in recovering the sum in question from the sale of
                        Lucius Scipio's property, but that as to L. Scipio himself, a man who had
                        conquered the most prosperous and wealthy monarch in the world; <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> who had carried the dominion of Rome to the
                        utmost limits of the world; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> who had bound
                        King Eumenes, the Rhodians, and so many other cities in Asia under
                        obligations to Rome; who had led first in triumph, and then to prison, so
                        many enemy commanders-this man he would not allow to lie in prison and in
                        chains amongst the enemies of Rome. He then ordered him to be released.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> His decision was greeted with such
                        enthusiasm by those who heard it, and there was such general delight at the
                        news of Scipio's release, that it seemed hardly possible that these were the
                        same people before whom the sentence against him had lately been pronounced.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The praetor then sent the quaestors to
                        seize L. Scipio's property in the name of the government. Not only was there
                        not a vestige of the king's gold to be seen, but the amount realised was
                        nowhere near the sum named in the judgment. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> The relatives and friends and clients of L. Scipio's contributed a sum
                        sufficient, if he accepted it, to make him even richer than before. He
                        refused to accept any of it. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Everything
                        necessary for him was supplied by his nearest relations. The ill-will and
                        popular odium against the Scipios had now turned against the praetor and his
                        assessors and the prosecution. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
