<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Inst." type="work">Institutio Oratoria, books 7-9 - 8</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Quint.">Quintilian</author>
                <editor n="Butler" role="editor">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Quintilian</author>
                        <title>With An English Translation</title>
                        <editor n="Butler" role="editor">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1922</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="Section"
                    matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+).(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2']/tei:div[@n='$3'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book and Chapter and Section</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern n="Chapter"
                    matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book and Chapter</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern n="Book"
                    matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="page"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><change who="GRC" when="2006">tagging</change><!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        --><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
            <change who="Zach Himes" when="2015-11-16">Edited teiHeader, converted to TEI P5 and EpiDoc</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="p.177"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" subtype="book" type="translation">
                <head>Book VIII</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="pr" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    THE observations contained in the preceding five
books approximately cover the method of invention
and the arrangement of the material thus provided.
It is absolutely necessary to acquire a thorough
knowledge of this method in all its details, if we
desire to become accomplished orators, but a simpler
and briefer course of instruction is more suitable for
beginners.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    For they tend either to be deterred from
study by the difficulties of so detailed and complicated
a course, or lose heart at having to attempt tasks of
such difficulty just at the very period when their
minds need special nourishment and a more attractive form of diet, or think that when they have
learned this much and no more, they are fully
equipped for the tasks of eloquence, or finally, regarding themselves as fettered by certain fixed laws
of oratory, shrink from making any effort on their
own initiative.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently, it has been held that
those who have exercised the greatest care in
writing text-books of rhetoric have been the furthest
removed from genuine eloquence. Still, it is absolutely necessary to point out to beginners the road
which they should follow, though this road must be
smooth and easy not merely to enter, but to indicate.
Consequently, our skilful instructor should select all
                    <pb xml:id="p.179"/>
                    that is best in the various writers on the subject
and content himself for the moment with imparting
those precepts of which he approves, without wasting
time over the refutation of those which he does not
approve. For thus your pupils will follow where you
lead.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Later, as they acquire strength in speaking,
their learning will grow in proportion. To begin
with, they may be allowed to think that there is no
other road than that on which we have set their
feet, and it may be left to time to teach them what
is actually the best. It is true that writers on
rhetoric have, by the pertinacity with which they
have defended their opinions, made the principles
of the science which they profess somewhat complicated; but these principles are in reality neither
obscure nor hard to understand.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently, if
we regard the treatment of the art as a whole, it is
harder to decide what we should teach than to teach
it, once the decision has been made. Above all, in
the two departments which I have mentioned, the
necessary rules are but few in number, and if the
pupil gives them ready acceptance, he will find that
the path to further accomplishment presents no
difficulty.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    I have, it is true, already expended much labour
on this portion of my task; for I desired to make
it clear that rhetoric is the science of speaking well,
that it is useful, and further, that it is an art and a
virtue. I wished also to show that its subject matter
consists of everything on which an orator may be
called to speak, and is, as a rule, to be found in three
classes of oratory, demonstrative, deliberative, and
forensic; that every speech is composed of matter
and words, and that as regards matter we must
                    <pb xml:id="p.181"/>
                    study invention, as regards words, style, and as
regards both, arrangement, all of which it is the
task of memory to retain and delivery to render
attractive.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    I attempted to show that the duty of
the orator is composed of instructing, moving and
delighting his hearers, statement of facts and argument falling under the head of instruction, while
emotional appeals are concerned with moving the
audience and, although they may be employed
throughout the case, are most effective at the beginning and end. As to the element of charm, I
pointed out that, though it may reside both in facts
and words, its special sphere is that of style.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    I
observed that there are two kinds of questions, the
one indefinite, the other definite, and involving the
consideration of persons and circumstances of time
and place; further, that whatever our subject matter, there are three questions which we must ask,
                    <hi rend="italic">is it? what is it?</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">of what kind is it?</hi>
                    To this I
added that demonstrative oratory consists of praise
and denunciation, and that in this connexion we
must consider not merely the acts actually performed by the person of whom we were speaking,
but what happened after his death. This task I
showed to be concerned solely with what is honourable or expedient.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    I remarked that in deliberative
oratory there is a third department as well which
depends on conjecture, for we have to consider
whether the subject of deliberation is possible or
likely to happen. At this point I emphasised the
importance of considering who it is that is speaking,
before whom he is speaking, and what he says. As
regards forensic cases, I demonstrated that some
turn on one point of dispute, others on several, and
                    <pb xml:id="p.183"/>
                    that whereas in some cases it is the attack, in others
in is the defence that determines the
                    <hi rend="italic">basis;</hi>
                    that
every defence rests on denial, which is of two kinds,
since we may either deny that the act was committed or that its nature was that alleged, while it
further consists of justification and technical pleas
to show that the action cannot stand.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    I proceeded
to show that questions must turn either on something written or something done: in the latter
case we have to consider the truth of the facts
together with their special character and quality;
in the former we consider the meaning or the
intention of the words, with reference to which we
usually examine the nature of all cases, criminal or
civil, which fall under the heads of the
                    <hi rend="italic">letter</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">intention,</hi>
                    the
                    <hi rend="italic">syllogism, ambiguity</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italic">contrary lairs.</hi>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    I went on to point out that in all forensic cases the
speech consists of five parts, the
                    <hi rend="italic">exordium</hi>
                    designed
to conciliate the audience, the
                    <hi rend="italic">statement of facts</hi>
                    designed to instruct him, the
                    <hi rend="italic">proof</hi>
                    which confirms
our own propositions, the
                    <hi rend="italic">refutation</hi>
                    which overthrows
the arguments of our opponents, and the
                    <hi rend="italic">peroration</hi>
                    which either refreshes the memory of our hearers
or plays upon their emotions.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    I then dealt with the
sources of arguments and emotion, and indicated
the means by which the judges should be excited,
placated, or amused. Finally I demonstrated the
method of division. But I would ask that the
student who is really desirous of learning should
believe that there are also a variety of subjects with
regard to which nature itself should provide much
of the requisite knowledge without any assistance
from formal teaching, so that the precepts of which
I have spoken may be regarded not so much as
                    <pb xml:id="p.185"/>
                    having been discovered by the professors of rhetoric
as having been noted by them when they presented
themselves.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    The points which follow require greater care and
industry. For I have now to discuss the theory of
style, a subject which, as all orators agree, presents
the greatest difficulty. For Marcus Antonius, whom
I mentioned above, states that lie has seen many
good, but no really eloquent speakers, and holds
that, while to be a good speaker it is sufficient to
say what is necessary, only the really eloquent
speaker can do this in ornate and appropriate language.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                        xxi. 94.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    And if this excellence was to be found in
no orator up to his own day, and not even in himself
or Lucius Crassus, we may regard it as certain that
the reason why they and their predecessors lacked
this gift was its extreme difficulty of acquisition.
Again, Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Cic.
                        <hi rend="italic">Or.</hi>
                        xiv. 44;
                    </note>
                    holds that, while invention and
arrangement are within the reach of any man of
good sense, eloquence belongs to the orator alone,
and consequently it was on the rules for the cultivation of eloquence that he expended the greatest
care.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    That he was justified in so doing is shown
clearly by the actual name of the art of which I am
speaking. For the verb
                    <hi rend="italic">eloqui</hi>
                    means the production
and communication to the audience of all that the
speaker has conceived in his mind, and without this
power all the preliminary accomplishments of oratory
are as useless as a sword that is kept permanently
concealed within its sheath.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Therefore it is on this
that teachers of rhetoric concentrate their attention, since it cannot possibly be acquired without
the assistance of the rules of artit is this which
is the chief object of our study, the goal of all
                    <pb xml:id="p.187"/>
                    our exercises and all our efforts at imitation, and it
is to this that we devote the energies of a lifetime;
it is this that makes one orator surpass his rivals,
this that makes one style of speaking preferable to
another.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    The failure of the orators of the Asiatic
and other decadent schools did not lie in their
inability to grasp or arrange the facts on which
they had to speak, nor, on the other hand, were
those who professed what we call the dry style of
oratory either fools or incapable of understanding
the cases in which they were engaged. No, the
fault of the former was that they lacked taste and
restraint in speaking, while the latter lacked power,
whence it is clear that it is here that the real faults
and virtues of oratory are to be found.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    This does not, however, mean that we should
devote ourselves to the study of words alone. For
I am compelled to offer the most prompt and determined resistance to those who would at the very
portals of this enquiry lay hold of the admissions
I have just made and, disregarding the subject
matter which, after all, is the backbone of any
speech, devote themselves to the futile and crippling
study of words in a vain desire to acquire the gift of
elegance, a gift which I myself regard as the fairest
of all the glories of oratory, but only when it is
natural and unaffected.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    Healthy bodies, enjoying
a good circulation and strengthened by exercise,
acquire grace from the same source that gives them
strength, for they have a healthy complexion, firm
flesh and shapely thews. But, on the other hand,
the man who attempts to enhance these physical
graces by the effeminate use of depilatories and cosmetics, succeeds merely in defacing them by the
                    <pb xml:id="p.189"/>
                    very care which he bestows on them.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    Again, a
tasteful and magnificent dress, as the Greek poet
tells us, lends added dignity to its wearer: but
effeminate and luxurious apparel fails to adorn the
body and merely reveals the foulness of the mind.
Similarly, a translucent and iridescent style merely
serves to emasculate the subject which it arrays with
such pomp of words. Therefore I would have the
orator, while careful in his choice of words, be even
more concerned about his subject matter.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    For, as a
rule, the best words are essentially suggested by the
subject matter and are discovered by their own
intrinsic light. But to-day we hunt for these words
as though they were always hiding themselves and
striving to elude our grasp. And thus we fail to
realise that they are to be found in the subject of
our speech, and seek them elsewhere, and, when we
have found them, force them to suit their context.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    It is with a more virile spirit that we should pursue
eloquence, who, if only her whole body be sound,
will never think it her duty to polish her nails and
tire her hair.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The usual result of over-attention to the niceties
of style is the deterioration of our eloquence.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    The
main reason for this is that those words are best
which are least far-fetched and give the impression
of simplicity and reality. For those words which are
obviously the result of careful search and even seem to
parade their self-conscious art, fail to attain the grace
at which they aim and lose all appearance of sincerity
because they darken the sense and choke the good
seed by their own luxuriant overgrowth.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    For in
our passion for words we paraphrase what might be
said in plain language, repeat what we have already
                    <pb xml:id="p.191"/>
                    said at sufficient length, pile up a number of words
where one would suffice, and regard allusion as
better than directness of speech. So, too, all
directness of speech is at a discount, and we think no
phrase eloquent that another could conceivably have
used.
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    We borrow figures and metaphors from the
most decadent poets, and regard it as a real sign
of genius that it should require a genius to understand our meaning. And yet Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        I. iii. 12.
                    </note>
                    long since
laid down this rule in the clearest of language, that
the worst fault in speaking is to adopt a style inconsistent with the idiom of ordinary speech and
contrary to the common feeling of mankind.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    But
nowadays our rhetoricians regard Cicero as lacking
both polish and learning; we are far superior, for
we look upon everything that is dictated by nature
as beneath our notice, and seek not for the true
ornaments of speech, but for meretricious finery, as
though there were any real virtue in words save in
their power to represent facts. And if we have to
spend all our life in the laborious effort to discover
words which will at once be brilliant, appropriate
and lucid, and to arrange them with exact precision,
we lose all the fruit of our studies.
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    And yet we see
the majority of modern speakers wasting their time
over the discovery of single words and over the
elaborate weighing and measurement of such words
when once discovered. Even if the special aim of
such a practice were always to secure the best words,
such an ill-starred form of industry would be much
to be deprecated, since it checks tile natural current
of our speech and extinguishes the warmth of
imagination by the delay and loss of self-confidence
which it occasions.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    For the orator who cannot
                    <pb xml:id="p.193"/>
                    endure to lose a single word is like a man plunged
in griping poverty. On the other hand, if he will
only first form a true conception of the principles of
eloquence, accumulate a copious supply of words by
wide and suitable reading, apply the art of arrangement to the words thus acquired, and finally, by
continual exercise, develop strength to use his
acquisitions so that every word is ready at hand
and lies under his very eyes, he will never lose a
single word.
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    For the man who follows these instructions will find that facts and words appropriate
to their expression will present themselves spontaneously. But it must be remembered that a long
course of preliminary study is necessary and that
the requisite ability must not merely be acquired,
but carefully stored for use; for the anxiety devoted
to the search for words, to the exercise of the
critical faculty and the power of comparison is in its
place while we are learning, but not when we are
speaking. Otherwise, the orator who has not given
sufficient attention to preliminary study will be like
a man who, having no fortune, lives from hand to
mouth.
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    If, on the other hand, the powers of speech
have been carefully cultivated beforehand, words
will yield us ready service, not merely turning up
when we search for them, but dwelling in our
thoughts and following them as the shadow follows
the body.
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    There are, however, limits even to this
form of study; for when our words are good Latin,
full of meaning, elegant and aptly arranged, why
should we labour further? And yet there are some
who are never weary of morbid self-criticism, who
throw themselves into an agony of mind almost
over separate syllables, and even when they have
                    <pb xml:id="p.195"/>
                    discovered the best words for their purpose look for
some word that is older, less familiar, and less
obvious, since they cannot bring themselves to
realise that when a speech is praised for its words,
it implies that its sense is inadequate.
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    While, then,
style calls for the utmost attention, we must always
bear in mind that nothing should be done for the
sake of words only, since words were invented
merely to give expression to things: and those
words are the most satisfactory which give the best
expression to the thoughts of our mind and produce
the effect which we desire upon the minds of the
judges.
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    Such words will assuredly be productive
of a style that will both give pleasure and awaken
admiration; and the admiration will be of a kind
far other than that which we bestow on portents,
while the pleasure evoked by the charm will have
nothing morbid about it, but will be praiseworthy
and dignified.
                </p>
                <p>
                    I. What the Greeks call
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">fra/sin</foreign>
                    we in Latin call
                    <hi rend="italic">elocuio</hi>
                    or style. Style is revealed both in individual
words and in groups of words. As regards the
former, we must see that they are Latin, clear, elegant
and well-adapted to produce the desired effect. As
regards the latter, they must be correct, aptly placed
and adorned with suitable figures.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    I have already,
in the portions of the first book dealing with the
subject of grammar, said all that is necessary on
the way to acquire idiomatic and correct speech.
But there my remarks were restricted to the prevention of positive faults, and it is well that I should
now point out that our words should have nothing
provincial or foreign about them. For you will find
                    <pb xml:id="p.197"/>
                    that there are a number of writers by no means
deficient in style whose language is precious rather
than idiomatic. As an illustration of my meaning
I would remind you of the story of the old woman
at Athens, who, when Theophrastus, a man of no
mean eloquence, used one solitary word in an
affected way, immediately said that he was a
foreigner, and on being asked how she detected it,
replied that his language was too Attic for Athens.
Again Asinius Pollio held that Livy,
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    for all his
astounding eloquence, showed traces of the idiom
of Padua. Therefore, if possible, our voice and all
our words should be such as to reveal the native of
this city, so that our speech may seem to be of
genuine Roman origin, and not merely to have
been presented with Roman citizenship.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Clearness results above all from
                    <hi rend="italic">propriety</hi>
                    in
the use of words. But
                    <hi rend="italic">propriety</hi>
                    is capable of more
than one interpretation. In its primary sense it
means calling things by their right names, and is
consequently sometimes to be avoided, for our
language must not be obscene, unseemly or mean.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Language may be described as mean when it is
beneath the dignity of the subject or the rank of
the speaker. Some orators fall into serious error
in their eagerness to avoid this fault, and are afraid
of all words that are in ordinary use, even although
they may be absolutely necessary for their purpose.
There was, for example, the man who in the course
of a speech spoke of
                    <quote>Iberian grass,</quote>
                    a meaningless
phrase intelligible only to himself. Cassius Severus,
however, by way of deriding his affectation, explained
that he meant Spanish broom.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Nor do I see why
a certain distinguished orator thought
                    <quote>
                        fishes
                        <pb xml:id="p.199"/>
                        conserved in brine
                    </quote>
                    a more elegant phrase than the
word which he avoided.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Probably salsamenta.</note>
                    But while there is no
special merit in the form of
                    <hi rend="italic">propriety</hi>
                    which consists
in calling things by their real names, it is a fault
to fly to the opposite extreme. This fault we call
                    <hi rend="italic">impropriety,</hi>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    while the Greeks call it
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)/kuron</foreign>
                    As
examples I may cite the Virgilian,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                        IV. 419.
                    </note>
                    <quote>Never could I have hoped for such great woe,</quote>
                    or the phrase,
which I noted had been corrected by Cicero in a
speech of Dolabella's,
                    <quote>To bring death,</quote>
                    or again,
phrases of a kind that win praise from some of
our contemporaries, such as,
                    <quote>His words fell from the cross.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Presumably in the sense,
                        <quote>He spoke like one in bodily pain.</quote>
                    </note>
                    On the other hand, everything that
lacks appropriateness will not necessarily suffer from
the fault of positive
                    <hi rend="italic">impropriety,</hi>
                    because there are, in
the first place, many things which have no proper
term either in Greek or Latin.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    For example, the
verb
                    <hi rend="italic">iaculari</hi>
                    is specially used in the sense of
                    <quote>to throw a javelin,</quote>
                    whereas there is no special verb
appropriated to the throwing of a ball or a stake.
So, too, while
                    <hi rend="italic">lapidare</hi>
                    has the obvious meaning of
                    <quote>to stone,</quote>
                    there is no special word to describe
the throwing of clods or potsherds.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Hence abuse or
                    <hi rend="italic">catachresis</hi>
                    of words becomes necessary, while metaphor, also, which is the supreme ornament of oratory,
applies words to things with which they have
strictly no connexion. Consequently
                    <hi rend="italic">propriety</hi>
                    turns
not on the actual term, but on the meaning of the
term, and must be tested by the touchstone of the
understanding, not of the ear.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The second sense
in which the word
                    <hi rend="italic">propriety</hi>
                    is used occurs when
there are a number of things all called by the same
name: in this case the original term from which
the others are derived is styled the
                    <hi rend="italic">proper</hi>
                    term.
                    <pb xml:id="p.201"/>
                    For example, the word
                    <hi rend="italic">vertex</hi>
                    means a whirl of
water, or of anything else that is whirled in a like
manner: then, owing to the fashion of coiling the
hair, it comes to mean the top of the head, while
finally, from this sense it derives the meaning of
the highest point of a mountain. All these things
may correctly be called
                    <hi rend="italic">vertices,</hi>
                    but the
                    <hi rend="italic">proper</hi>
                    use
of the term is the first. So, too,
                    <hi rend="italic">solea</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">tuidus</hi>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    are employed as names of fish, to mention no other
cases.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Lit. i. e. in the
                        <hi rend="italic">proper</hi>
                        sense
                        <hi rend="italic">the sole of the foot and a thrush.</hi>
                    </note>
                    The third kind of
                    <hi rend="italic">propriety</hi>
                    is found in
the case where a thing which serves a number
of purposes has a special name in some one particular context; for example, the proper term for
a funeral
                    <hi rend="italic">song</hi>
                    is
                    <hi rend="italic">naenia,</hi>
                    and for the general's
                    <hi rend="italic">tent augurale.</hi>
                    Again, a term which is common to a
number of things may be applied in a
                    <hi rend="italic">proper</hi>
                    or
special sense to some one of them. Thus we use
                    <hi rend="italic">urbs</hi>
                    in the special sense of Rome,
                    <hi rend="italic">venales</hi>
                    in the
special sense of newly-purchased slaves, and
                    <hi rend="italic">Corinthia</hi>
                    in the special sense of bronzes, although
there are other cities besides Rome, and many
other things which may be styled
                    <hi rend="italic">venales</hi>
                    besides
slaves, and gold and silver are found at Corinth
as well as bronze. But the use of such terms
implies no special excellence in an orator.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    There
is, however, a form of
                    <hi rend="italic">propriety</hi>
                    of speech which
deserves the highest praise, that is to say, the
employment of words with the maximum of significance, as, for instance, when Cato
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Suet. Caes.</hi>
                        53.
                    </note>
                    said that
                    <quote>Caesar was thoroughly sober when he undertook the task of overthrowing the constitution,</quote>
                    or as
Virgil
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ecl.</hi>
                        vi. 5.
                    </note>
                    spoke of a
                    <quote>thin-drawn strain,</quote>
                    and Horace
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Odes</hi>
                        I. xii. 1, and III. vi. 36.
                    </note>
                    of the
                    <quote>shrill pipe,</quote>
                    and
                    <quote>dread Hannibal.</quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Some
also include under this head that form of
                    <hi rend="italic">propriety</hi>
                    <pb xml:id="p.203"/>
                    which is derived from characteristic epithets,
such as in the Virgilian
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Georg.</hi>
                        i. 295 and
                        <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                        xi. 681.
                    </note>
                    phrases,
                    <quote>sweet unfermented wine,</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>with white teeth.</quote>
                    But of
this sort of propriety I shall have to speak elsewhere.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">SC.</hi>
                        ch. vi.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Propriety is</hi>
                    also made to include the appropriate use of words in metaphor, while at times the
salient characteristic of an individual comes to be
attached to him as a
                    <hi rend="italic">proper</hi>
                    name: thus Fabius was
called
                    <quote>Cunctator,</quote>
                    the Delayer, on account of the
most remarkable of his many military virtues. Some,
perhaps, may think that words which mean more
than they actually say deserve mention in connexion
with clearness, since they assist the understanding.
I, however, prefer to place
                    <hi rend="italic">emphasis</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See IX. ii. 64.</note>
                    among the
ornaments of oratory, since it does not make a thing
intelligible, but merely more intelligible.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Obscurity, on the other hand, results from the
employment of obsolete words, as, for instance, if
an author should search the records of the priests,
the earliest treaties and the works of long-forgotten
writers with the deliberate design of collecting
words that no man living understands. For there
are persons who seek to gain a reputation for erudition by such means as this, in order that they
may be regarded as the sole depositories of certain
forms of knowledge.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Obscurity may also be produced by the use of words which are more familiar
in certain districts than in others, or which are
of a technical character, such as the wind called
                    <quote>Atabalus,</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        An Apulian term for the Scirocco. What is the peculiarity of a
                        <hi rend="italic">sack-ship</hi>
                        is unknown. It is possible that with
Haupt we should read
                        <hi rend="italic">stlataria,</hi>
                        "a broad-beamed merchant-vessel.
                    </note>
                    or a
                    <quote>sack-ship,</quote>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italic">in malo cosanum.</hi>
                    Such expressions should be avoided if we are pleading before a judge who is ignorant of their meaning,
or, if used, should be explained, as may have to be
done in the case of what are called homonyms. For
                    <pb xml:id="p.205"/>
                    example, the word
                    <hi rend="italic">taurus</hi>
                    may be unintelligible unless we make it clear whether we are speaking of
a bull, or a mountain, or a constellation, or the name
of a man, or the root of a tree.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Reference unknown.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    A greater source of obscurity is, however, to be
found in the construction and combination of words,
and the ways in which this may occur are still more
numerous. Therefore, a sentence should never be
so long that it is impossible to follow its drift, nor
should its conclusion be unduly postponed by transposition or an excessive use of
                    <hi rend="italic">hyperbaton.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See viii. vi. 62.</note>
                    Still
worse is the result when the order of the words is
confused as in the line
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                        i. 109. The awkwardness of the order cannot be
brought out in English.
                    </note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="F">In the midmost sea</l>
                            <l part="N">Rocks are there by Italians altars called.</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    Again,
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    parenthesis, so often employed by orators
and historians, and consisting in the insertion of one
sentence in the midst of another, may seriously
hinder the understanding of a passage, unless the
insertion is short. For example, in the passage
where Vergil
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Georg.</hi>
                        iii. 79–83.
                    </note>
                    describes a colt, the words
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">Nor fears he empty noises,</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    are followed by a number of remarks of a totally
different form, and it is only four lines later that
the poet returns to the point and says,
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">Then, if tile sound of arms be heard afar,</l>
                            <l part="N">How to stand still he knows not.</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    Above all, ambiguity must be avoided,
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    and by
ambiguity I mean not merely the kind of which
I have already spoken, where the sense is uncertain,
as in the clause
                    <hi rend="italic">Chremetem audivi percussisse Demean,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See VII. ix. 10.</note>
                    <pb xml:id="p.207"/>
                    but also that form of ambiguity which, although
it does not actually result in obscuring the sense,
falls into the same verbal error as if a man should say
                    <hi rend="italic">visum a se hominem librum scribentem</hi>
                    (that he had
seen a man writing a book). For although it is
clear that the book was being written by the man,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>
                        and not the man by the book!
                    </note>
                    the sentence is badly put together, and its author
has made it as ambiguous as he could.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    Again, some writers introduce a whole host of
useless words; for, in their eagerness to avoid
ordinary methods of expression, and allured by
false ideals of beauty they wrap up everything in a
multitude of words simply and solely because they
are unwilling to make a direct and simple statement of the facts: and then they link up and
involve one of those long-winded clauses with others
like it, and extend their periods to a length beyond
the compass of mortal breath.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    Some even expend
an infinity of toil to acquire this vice, which, by the
way, is nothing new: for I learn from the pages of
Livy
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Perhaps in his letter to his son, for which see II. v. 20.
                    </note>
                    that there was one, a teacher, who instructed
his pupils to make all they said obscure, using the
Greek word
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">sko/tison</foreign>
                    (
                    <quote>darken it.</quote>
                    ) It was this
same habit that gave rise to the famous words of
praise,
                    <quote>So much the better: even I could not understand you.</quote>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    Others are consumed with a
passion for brevity and omit words which are
actually necessary to the sense, regarding it as a
matter of complete indifference whether their meaning is intelligible to others, so long as they know
what they mean themselves. For my own part, I
regard as useless words which make such a demand
upon the ingenuity of the hearer. Others, again,
succeed in committing the same fault by a
                    <pb xml:id="p.209"/>
                    perverse misuse of figures.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    Worst of all are the
phrases which the Greeks call
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)diano/hta,</foreign>
                    that is to
say, expressions which, though their meaning is
obvious enough on the surface, have a secret meaning, as for example in the phrase
                    <hi rend="italic">cum ductus est caecus secundam viam stare,</hi>
                    or where the man, who
is supposed in the scholastic theme to have torn his
own limbs with his teeth, is said to have
                    <hi rend="italic">lain upon himself</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Like a wild beast devouring his prey.</note>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    Such expressions are regarded as ingenious,
daring and eloquent, simply because of their ambiguity, and quite a number of persons have become
infected by the belief that a passage which requires
a commentator must for that very reason be a
masterpiece of elegance. Nay, there is even a class
of hearer who find a special pleasure in such passages; for the fact that they can provide an answer
to the riddle fills them with an ecstasy of self-congratulation, as if they had not merely heard the
phrase, but invented it.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    For my own part, I regard clearness as the first
essential of a good style: there must be propriety
in our words, their order must be straightforward,
the conclusion of the period must not be long postponed, there must be nothing lacking and nothing
superfluous. Thus our language will be approved
by the learned and clear to the uneducated. I am
speaking solely of clearness in style, as I have
already dealt with clearness in the presentation
of facts in the rules I laid down for the
                    <hi rend="italic">statement of the case.</hi>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    But the general method is the same
in both. For if what we say is not less nor more
than is required, and is clear and systematically
arranged, the whole matter will be plain and obvious
even to a not too attentive audience. For we must
                    <pb xml:id="p.211"/>
                    never forget that the attention of the judge is not
always so keen that he will dispel obscurities without assistance, and bring the light of his intelligence
to bear on the dark places of our speech. On the
contrary, lie will have many other thoughts to distract him unless what we say is so clear that our
words will thrust themselves into his mind even
when he is not giving us his attention, just as the
sunlight forces itself upon the eyes.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    Therefore
our aim must be not to put him in a position
to understand our argument, but to force him to
understand it. Consequently we shall frequently
repeat anything which we think the judge has
failed to take in as he should. We shall say, for
example,
                    <quote>
                        I fear that this portion of our case has
been somewhat obscurely stated: the fault is mine,
and I will therefore re-state it in plainer and simpler
language
                    </quote>
                    ; for the pretended admission of a fault
on our part creates an excellent impression.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    I now come to the subject of ornament, in
which, more than in any other department, the orator
undoubtedly allows himself the greatest indulgence.
For a speaker wins but trifling praise if he does no
more than speak with correctness and lucidity; in
fact his speech seems rather to be free from blemish
than to have any positive merit.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Even the untrained often possess the gift of invention, and no
great learning need be assumed for the satisfactory
arrangement of our matter, while if any more
recondite art is required, it is generally concealed,
since unconcealed it would cease to be an art, while
all these qualities are employed solely to serve the
interests of the actual case. On the other hand, by
the employment of skilful ornament the orator
                    <pb xml:id="p.213"/>
                    commends himself at the same time, and whereas his
other accomplishments appeal to the considered
judgment of the learned, this gift appeals to the
enthusiastic approval of the world at large, and the
speaker who possesses it fights not merely with
effective, but with flashing weapons.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    If in his defence
of Cornelius Cicero had confined himself merely to
instructing the judge and speaking in clear and idiomatic Latin without a thought beyond the interests
of his case, would he ever have compelled the Roman
people to proclaim their admiration not merely by
acclamation, but by thunders of applause? No, it
was the sublimity and splendour, the brilliance and
the weight of his eloquence that evoked such clamorous enthusiasm.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Nor, again, would his words have
been greeted with such extraordinary approbation if
his speech had been like the ordinary speeches of
every day. In my opinion the audience did not know
what they were doing, their applause sprang neither
from their judgment nor their will; they were seized
with a kind of frenzy and, unconscious of the place in
which they stood, burst forth spontaneously into a
perfect ecstasy of delight.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    But rhetorical ornament contributes not a little to
the furtherance of our case as well. For when our
audience find it a pleasure to listen, their attention
and their readiness to believe what they hear are
both alike increased, while they are generally filled
with delight, and sometimes even transported by
admiration. The flash of the sword in itself strikes
something of terror to the eye, and we should be
less alarmed by the thunderbolt if we feared its
violence alone, and not its flash as well.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Cicero
was right when, in one of his letters to Brutus, he
                    <pb xml:id="p.215"/>
                    wrote,
                    <quote>Eloquence which evokes no admiration is, in my opinion, unworthy of the name.</quote>
                    Aristotle
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Rhet.</hi>
                        III. ii. 5.
                    </note>
                    likewise thinks that the excitement of admiration
should be one of our first aims.
                </p>
                <p>
                    But such ornament must, as I have already said,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">In the introduction to this book, 19.</note>
                    be bold, manly and chaste, free from all effeminate
smoothness and the false hues derived from artificial
dyes, and must glow with health and vigour.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    So true
is this, that although, where ornament is concerned,
vice and virtue are never far apart, those who employ
a vicious style of embellishment disguise their vices
with the name of virtue. Therefore let none of our
decadents accuse me of being an enemy to those
who speak with grace and finish. I do not deny the
existence of such a virtue, I merely deny that they
possess it.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Shall I regard a farm as a model of good
cultivation because its owner shows me lilies and
violets and anemones and fountains of living water
in place of rich crops and vines bowed beneath their
clusters? Shall I prefer the barren plane and myrtles
trimly clipped, to the fruitful olive and the elm that
weds the vine? No, let such luxuries delight the rich:
but where would their wealth be if they had nought
save these?
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Again, is beauty an object of no consideration in the planting of fruit trees? Certainly
not! For my trees must be planted in due order
and at fixed intervals. What fairer sight is there
than rows of trees planted in échelon
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Quincunx.</hi>
                        The formation may be thus represented
                    </note>
                    which present
straight lines to the eye from whatever angle they be
viewed? But it has an additional advantage, since
this form of plantation enables every tree to derive
an equal share of moisture from the soil.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    When the
tops of my olive trees rise too high, I lop them away,
with the result that their growth expands laterally
                    <pb xml:id="p.217"/>
                    in a manner that is at once more pleasing to the eye
and enables them to bear more fruit owing to the
increase in the number of branches. A horse whose
flanks are compact is not only better to look upon,
but swifter in speed. The athlete whose muscles
have been formed by exercise is a joy to the eye, but
he is also better fitted for the contests in which he
must engage.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    In fact true beauty and usefulness
always go hand in hand.
                </p>
                <p>
                    It does not, however, require any special ability to
discern the truth of this. It is more important to
note that such seemly ornament must be varied to
suit the nature of the material to which it is applied.
To begin with the primary classification of oratory,
the same form of ornament will not suit demonstrative, deliberative and forensic speeches. For the
oratory of display aims solely at delighting the
audience, and therefore develops all the resources of
eloquence and deploys all its ornament, since it seeks
not to steal its way into the mind nor to wrest the
victory from its opponent, but aims solely at honour
and glory.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently the orator, like the hawker
who displays his wares, will set forth before his
audience for their inspection, nay, almost for their
handling, all his most attractive reflexions, all the
brilliance that language and the charm that figures
can supply, together with all the magnificence of
metaphor and the elaborate art of composition that
is at his disposal. For his success concerns himself,
and not his cause.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    But when it is a question of facts,
and he is confronted by the hard realities of battle,
his last thought will be for his personal glory. Nay,
it is even unseemly to trouble overmuch about words
when the greatest interests are at stake. I would
                    <pb xml:id="p.219"/>
                    not assert that such themes afford no scope for
ornament, but such ornament as is employed must
be of a more severe, restrained and less obvious
character; above all, it must be adapted to the
matter in hand.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    For whereas in deliberative oratory
the senate demand a certain loftiness and the people
a certain impetuosity of eloquence, the public cases
of the courts and those involving capital punishment
demand a more exact style. On the other hand, in
private deliberations and lawsuits about trifling sums
of money (and there are not a few of these) it is more
appropriate to employ simple and apparently unstudied language. For we should be ashamed to
demand the repayment of a loan in rolling periods, or
to display poignant emotion in a case concerned with
water-droppings, or to work ourselves into a perspiration over the return of a slave to the vendor.
But I am wandering from the point.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Since rhetorical ornament, like clearness, may
reside either in individual words or groups of words,
we must consider the requirements of both cases.
For although tile canon, that clearness mainly
requires propriety of language and ornament the
skilful use of metaphor, is perfectly sound, it is
desirable that we should realise that without propriety ornament is impossible.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    But as several words
may often have the same meaning (they are called
synonyms), some will be more distinguished, sublime, brilliant, attractive or euphonious than others.
For as those syllables are the most pleasing to the
ear which are composed of the more euphonious
letters, thus words composed of such syllables will
sound better than others, and the more vowel sounds
they contain the more attractive they will be to hear.
                    <pb xml:id="p.221"/>
                    The same principle governs the linking of word with
word; some arrangements will sound better than
others.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    But words require to be used in different
ways. For example, horrible things are best described by words that are actually harsh to the
ear. But as a general rule it may be laid down
that the best words, considered individually, are
those which are fullest or most agreeable in sound.
Again, elegant words are always to be preferred
to those which are coarse, and there is no room
for low words in the speech of a cultivated man.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    The choice of striking or sublime words will be
determined by the matter in hand; for a word that
in one context is magnificent may be turgid in
another, and words which are all too mean to
describe great things may be suitable enough when
applied to subjects of less importance. And just as
a mean word embedded in a brilliant passage
attracts special attention, like a spot on a bright
surface, so if our style be of a plain character,
sublime and brilliant words will seem incongruous
and tasteless excrescences on a flat surface.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    In
some cases instinct, and not reason, must supply
the touchstone, as, for example, in the line:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                        viii. 641.
                    </note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">A sow was slain to ratify their pacts.</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    Here the poet, by inventing the word
                    <hi rend="italic">porca,</hi>
                    succeeded in producing an elegant impression, whereas
if lie had used the masculine
                    <hi rend="italic">porcuis,</hi>
                    the very reverse
would have been the case. In some cases, however,
the incongruity is obvious enough. It was only the
other day that we laughed with good reason at the
poet who wrote:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">The youngling mice had gnawed</l>
                            <l part="N">Within its chest the purple-bordered gown.</l>
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                                Camillus originally means a
                                <quote>young boy.</quote>
                            </note>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb xml:id="p.223"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, we admire Virgil
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Georg. i.</hi>
                        181.
                    </note>
                    when he
says:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">
                            <quote>Oft hath the tiny mouse,</quote>
                            etc.
                        </l>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    For here the epithet is appropriate and prevents
our expecting too much, while the use of the singular
instead of the plural, and the unusual monosyllabic
conclusion of the line, both add to the pleasing effect.
Horace
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">A. P.</hi>
                        139.
                    </note>
                    accordingly imitated Virgil in both these
points, when he wrote,
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">The fruit shall be a paltry mouse.</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    Again, our style need not always dwell on the
heights: at times it is desirable that it should sink.
For there are occasions when the very meanness of
the words employed adds force to what we say.
When Cicero, in his denunciation of Piso,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Fr.</hi>
                        100.
                    </note>
                    says,
                    <quote>When your whole family rolls up in a dray,</quote>
                    do
you think that his use of the word
                    <hi rend="italic">dray</hi>
                    was accidental,
and was not designedly used to increase his audience's
contempt for the man he wished to bring to ruin?
The same is true when he says elsewhere,
                    <quote>You put down your head and butt him.</quote>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    This device may also
serve to carry off a jest, as in the passage of Cicero
where he talks of the
                    <quote>little sprat of a boy who slept with his elder sister,</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro. Cael.</hi>
                        xv. 36.
                    </note>
                    or where he speaks of
                    <quote>Flavius, who put out the eyes of crows,</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Mil.</hi>
                        xi. 25. Our equivalent is
                        <quote>catch a weasel asleep.</quote>
                    </note>
                    or, again, in the
                    <hi rend="italic">pro Milone,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Mil.</hi>
                        xxii. 60.
                        <hi rend="italic">Rufio,</hi>
                        a slave name = red head.
                    </note>
                    cries,
                    <quote>Hi, there! Rufio!</quote>
                    and talks of
                    <quote>Erucius Antoniaster.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        From the lost
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Vareno.</hi>
                        <quote>Erucius, Antonius' ape.</quote>
                    </note>
                    On the other hand, this
practice becomes more obtrusive when employed in
the schools, like the phrase that was so much
praised in my boyhood,
                    <quote>Give your father bread,</quote>
                    or
in the same declamation,
                    <quote>You feed even your dog.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        A declamation turning on the law that sons must support
their parents.
                    </note>
                    But such tricks do not always come off,
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    especially in
                    <pb xml:id="p.225"/>
                    the schools, and often turn the laugh against the
speaker, particularly in the present day, when declamation has become so far removed from reality
and labours under such an extravagant fastidiousness
in the choice of words that it has excluded a good
half of the language from its vocabulary.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    Words are
                    <hi rend="italic">proper, newly-coined or metaphorical.</hi>
                    In
the case of
                    <hi rend="italic">proper</hi>
                    words there is a special dignity
conferred by antiquity, since old words, which not
everyone would think of using, give our style a
venerable and majestic air: this is a form of ornament
of which Virgil, with his perfect taste, has made
unique use.
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    For his employment of words such as
                    <hi rend="italic">olli,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Archaic for
                        <hi rend="italic">illi.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <hi rend="italic">quianam,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Because.</note>
                    <hi rend="italic">moerus,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Archaic for
                        <hi rend="italic">murus (Aen.</hi>
                        x. 24.).
                    </note>
                    <hi rend="italic">pone</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Behind.</note>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">pellacia</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Deceitfulness (
                        <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                        ii. 90).
                    </note>
                    gives his
work that impressive air of antiquity which is so
attractive in pictures, but which no art of man can
counterfeit. But we must not overdo it, and such
words must not be dragged out from the deepest
darkness of the past.
                    <hi rend="italic">Quaeso</hi>
                    is old enough: what
need for us to say
                    <hi rend="italic">quaiso?</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">quaeso</hi>
                        = pray,
                        <hi rend="italic">oppido</hi>
                        quite, exactly.
                    </note>
                    <hi rend="italic">Oppido</hi>
                    was still used by
my older contemporaries, but I fear that no one
would tolerate it now. At any rate,
                    <hi rend="italic">antegerio,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Quite, very.</note>
                    which
means the same, would certainly never be used by
anyone who was not possessed with a passion for
notoriety.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    What need have we of
                    <hi rend="italic">acrumnosum?</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Wretched.</note>
                    It
is surely enough to call a thing
                    <hi rend="italic">horridum. Reor may</hi>
                    be tolerated,
                    <hi rend="italic">autumo</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Assert.</note>
                    smacks of tragedy,
                    <hi rend="italic">proles</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Offspring.</note>
                    has
become a rarity, while
                    <hi rend="italic">prosapia</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Stock, family.</note>
                    stamps the man
who uses it as lacking taste. Need I say more
Almost the whole language has changed.
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    But there
are still some old words that are endeared to us by
                    <pb xml:id="p.227"/>
                    their antique sheen, while there are others that we
cannot avoid using occasionally, such, for example, as
                    <hi rend="italic">nuncupare</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">fari:</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Name, speak.</note>
                    there are yet others which it
requires some daring to use, but which may still be
employed so long as we avoid all appearance of that
affectation which Virgil
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Catal.</hi>
                        ii.
                    </note>
                    has derided so cleverly:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">
                                Britain's Thucydides,
                                <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                                whose mad Attic brain
                            </l>
                            <l part="N">Loved word-amalgams like Corinthian bronze,</l>
                            <l part="N">First made a horrid blend of words from Gaul,</l>
                            <l part="N">Tau, al, min, sil and God knows how much else,</l>
                            <l part="N">Then mixed them in a potion for his brother!</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    This was a certain Cimber who killed his brother,
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    a fact which Cicero recorded in the words,
                    <quote>Cimber has killed his brother German.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Phil.</hi>
                        XI. vi. 14. A pun on the two meanings of
                        <hi rend="italic">gemanus,</hi>
                        brother and German.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    The epigram against Sallust is scarcely less well
known:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">Crispus, you, too, Jugurtha's fall who told,</l>
                            <l part="N">And filched such store of words from Cato old.</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    It is a tiresome kind of affectation; any one can
practise it, and it is made all the worse by the fact
that the man who catches the infection will not
choose his words to suit his facts, but will drag in
irrelevant facts to provide an opportunity for the use
of such words.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The coining of new words is, as I stated in the
first book,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">I. v. 70</note>
                    more permissible in Greek, for the
Greeks did not hesitate to coin nouns to represent
certain sounds and emotions, and in truth they were
taking no greater liberty than was taken by the
first men when they gave names to things.
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    Our
own writers have ventured on a few attempts at
composition and derivation, but have not met with
                    <pb xml:id="p.229"/>
                    much success. I remember in my young days there
was a dispute between Pomponius and Seneca which
even found its way into the prefaces of their works,
as to whether
                    <hi rend="italic">gradus eliminate</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Sc.
                        <quote>moves his steps beyond the threshold.</quote>
                    </note>
                    was a phrase which
ought to have been allowed in tragedy. But the
ancients had no hesitation about using even
                    <hi rend="italic">expectorate</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <quote>banishes from his heart.</quote>
                    </note>
                    and, after all, it presents exactly the same formation
as
                    <hi rend="italic">exanimat.</hi>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    Of the coining of words by expansion
and inflexion we have examples, such as the Ciceronian
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">De Nat. D.</hi>
                        I. xxxiv. 95.
                    </note>
                    <hi rend="italic">beatitas</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">beatitudo,</hi>
                    forms which he feels to
be somewhat harsh, though he thinks they may be
softened by use. Derivatives may even be fashioned
from proper names, quite apart from ordinary words,
witness
                    <hi rend="italic">Sullaturit</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">a Att.</hi>
                        IX. x. 6.
                        <quote>Desires to be a second Sulla.</quote>
                    </note>
                    in Cicero and
                    <hi rend="italic">Fimbriatus</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">Figulatus</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Metamorphosed into Figulus. Presumably refers to
Clusinius Figulus, see VII. ii. 26.
                    </note>
                    in Asinius.
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    Many new words have been
coined in imitation of the Greeks,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See II. xiv. 2.</note>
                    more especially
by Verginius Flavus, some of which, such as
                    <hi rend="italic">queens</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">essentia,</hi>
                    are regarded as unduly harsh. But I see no
reason why we should treat them with such contempt,
except, perhaps, that we are highly self-critical and
suffer in consequence from the poverty of our
language. Some new formations do, however, succeed
in establishing themselves.
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    For words which now
are old, once were new, and there are some words in
use which are of quite recent origin, such as
                    <hi rend="italic">reatus,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The condition of an accused person.</note>
                    invented by Messala, and
                    <hi rend="italic">munerarius,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The giver of a gladiatorial show.</note>
                    invented by
Augustus. So, too, my own teachers still persisted
in banning the use of words, such as
                    <hi rend="italic">piratica, musica</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">fabrica,</hi>
                    while Cicero regards
                    <hi rend="italic">favor</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">urbanus</hi>
                    as but newly introduced into the language. For in
a letter to Brutus he says,
                    <hi rend="italic">eum amorer et eum, ut hoc</hi>
                    <pb xml:id="p.231"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">verbo utar, favored in consilium advocabo,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        This letter is lost:
                        <quote>I will call that love and that favour, if I may use the word, to be my counsellors.</quote>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    while to
Appius Pulcher he writes,
                    <hi rend="italic">le hominem non solum sapientem, verum etiam, ut nunc loquimur, urbanum.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">ad Fam.</hi>
                        III. viii. 3.
                        <quote>You who are not merely wise, but, as we say nowadays, urbane.</quote>
                    </note>
                    He
also thinks that Terence was the first to use the
word
                    <hi rend="italic">obsequium,</hi>
                    while Caecilius asserts that Sisenna
was the first to use the phrase
                    <hi rend="italic">albente caelo.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <quote>When the sky grew white (at dawn).</quote>
                    </note>
                    Hortensius seems to have been the first to use
                    <hi rend="italic">cervix</hi>
                    in
the singular, since the ancients confined themselves
to the plural. We must not then be cowards, for I
cannot agree with Celsus when he forbids orators to
coin new words.
                    <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                    For some words, as Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Part Or.</hi>
                        v. 16.
                    </note>
                    says,
are native, that is to say, are used in their original
meaning, while others are derivative, that is to say,
formed from the native. Granted then that we
are not justified in coining entirely new words
having no resemblance to the words invented by
primitive man, I must still ask at what date we were
first forbidden to form derivatives and to modify
and compound words, processes which were undoubtedly permitted to later generations of mankind.
If, however,
                    <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                    one of our inventions seems a little
risky, we must take certain measures in advance to
save it from censure, prefacing it by phrases such as
                    <quote>so to speak,</quote>
                    <quote>if I may say so,</quote>
                    <quote>in a certain sense,</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>if you will allow me to make use of such a word.</quote>
                    The same practice may be followed in the
case of bold metaphors, and it is not too much to
say that almost anything can be said with safety
provided we show by the very fact of our anxiety
that the word or phrase in question is not due to an
error of judgment. The Greeks have a neat saying
on this subject, advising us to be the first to blame
our own hyperbole.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ar. Rhet.</hi>
                        III. vii. 9.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                    The metaphorical use of words cannot be
                    <pb xml:id="p.233"/>
                    recommended except in connected discourse. Enough has
now been said on the subject of single words, which,
as I have pointed out elsewhere,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">I. v. 3.</note>
                    have no intrinsic
value of their own. On the other hand, there is no
word which is intrinsically ugly unless it be beneath
the dignity of the subject on which we have to
speak, excepting always such words as are nakedly
obscene.
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
                    I would commend this remark to those
who do not think it necessary to avoid obscenity on
the ground that no word is indecent in itself and
that, if a thing
                    <hi rend="italic">is</hi>
                    revolting, its unpleasantness will
be realised clearly enough by whatever name it is
called. Accordingly, I shall content myself with
following the good old rules of Roman modesty and,
as I have already replied to such persons, shall
vindicate the cause of decency by saying no more on
this unpleasant subject.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
                    Let us now pass to consider connected discourse.
Its adornment may be effected, primarily, in two
ways; that is to say, we must consider first our ideal
of style, and secondly how we shall express this ideal
in actual words. The first essential is to realise
clearly what we wish to enhance or attenuate, to
express with vigour or calm, in luxuriant or austere
language, at length or with conciseness, with gentleness or asperity, magnificence or subtlety, gravity or
wit.
                    <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>
                    The next essential is to decide by what kind of
metaphor, figures, reflexions, methods and arrangement we may best produce the effect which we
desire.
                </p>
                <p>
                    But, before I discuss ornament, I must first touch
upon its opposite, since the first of all virtues is the
avoidance of faults.
                    <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>
                    Therefore we must not expect
any speech to be ornate that is not, in the first place,
                    <pb xml:id="p.235"/>
                    acceptable. An acceptable style is defined by
Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Part. Or.,</hi>
                        vi. 19.
                    </note>
                    as one which is not over-elegant: not that
our style does not require elegance and polish,
which are essential parts of ornament, but that excess
is always a vice.
                    <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
                    He desires, therefore, that our
words should have a certain weight about them, and
that our thoughts should be of a serious cast or, at
any rate, adapted to the opinions and character of
mankind. These points once secured, we may
proceed to employ those expressions which he
regards as conferring distinction on style, that is to
say, specially selected words and phrases, metaphor,
hyperbole, appropriate epithets, repetitions, synonyms and all such language as may suit our case and
provide an adequate representation of the facts.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="44" unit="section"/>
                    But since my first task is to point out the faults to
be avoided, I will begin by calling attention to the
fault known as
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">kake/mfaton,</foreign>
                    a term applied to the
employment of language to which perverted usage
has given an obscene meaning: take, for example,
phrases such as
                    <hi rend="italic">ductare exercitus and patrare bellum,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">ductare</hi>
                        might mean
                        <hi rend="italic">ad libidinem abducere. patrare bellum</hi>
                        might mean
                        <hi rend="italic">paedicare formosum.</hi>
                    </note>
                    which were employed by Sallust in their old and
irreproachable sense, but, I regret to say, cause
amusement in certain quarters to-day. This, however, is not, in my opinion, the fault of the writer, but
of his readers;
                    <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>
                    still it is one to be avoided, for we
have perverted the purity of language by our own
corruption, and there is no course left to us but to
give ground before the victorious advance of vice.
The same term is also applied in the cases where an
unfortunate collocation of words produces an obscene
suggestion. For example, in the phrase
                    <hi rend="italic">cum hominibus notis loqui,</hi>
                    unless
                    <hi rend="italic">hominibus</hi>
                    is placed between
                    <hi rend="italic">cum</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">notis,</hi>
                    we shall commit ourselves to a phrase
                    <pb xml:id="p.237"/>
                    which will require some apology, since the final letter
of the first syllable, which cannot be pronounced
without closing the lips, will force us either to pause
in a most unbecoming manner, or by assimilation to
the
                    <hi rend="italic">n</hi>
                    which follows
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>
                        pronouncing
                        <hi rend="italic">cunnotis.</hi>
                    </note>
                    will produce a most objectionable suggestion.
                    <milestone n="46" unit="section"/>
                    I might quote other collocations
of words which are liable to the same objection, but
to discuss them in detail would be to fall into that
very fault which I have just said should be avoided.
A similar offence against modesty may be caused by
the division of words, as, for example, by the use of
the nominative of
                    <hi rend="italic">intercapedinis.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">interccapedo,</hi>
                        of which the last two syllables might give
rise to unseemly laughter;
                        <hi rend="italic">pedo =</hi>
                        <quote>break wind.</quote>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="47" unit="section"/>
                    And it is not
merely in writing that this may occur, but you will
find, unless you exercise the greatest care, that there
are a number of persons who take pleasure in putting
an indecent interpretation on words, thinking, as
Ovid
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Met.</hi>
                        i. 502.
                    </note>
                    says:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">that whatsoe'er is hid is best of all.</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    Nay, an obscene meaning may be extracted even
from words which are as far removed from indecency
as possible. Celsus, for example, detects an instance
of
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">kake/mfaton</foreign>
                    in the Virgilian
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Georg.</hi>
                        i. 357.
                    </note>
                    phrase:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">incipiunt agitata tumescere;</l>
                    </quote>
                    but if this point of view be accepted, it will be risky
to say anything at all.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="48" unit="section"/>
                    Next to indecency of expression comes meanness,
styled
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">tapei/nwsis,</foreign>
                    when the grandeur or dignity of
anything is diminished by the words used, as in the
line:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">
                            <quote>There is a rocky wart upon the mountain's brow.</quote>
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">From an unknown tragedian.</note>
                        </l>
                    </quote>
                    The opposite fault, which is no less serious, consists
                    <pb xml:id="p.239"/>
                    in calling small things by extravagant names, though
such a practice is permissible when deliberately
designed to raise a laugh. Consequently we must
not call a parricide a scamp, nor a man who keeps a
harlot a villain, since the first epithet is too weak
and the second too strong.
                    <milestone n="49" unit="section"/>
                    This fault will result in
making our language dull, or coarse, jejune, heavy,
unpleasing or slovenly, all of which faults are best
realised by reference to the virtues which are their
opposites, that is, point, polish, richness, liveliness,
charm, and finish.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="50" unit="section"/>
                    We must also avoid
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">mei/wsis</foreign>
                    a term applied to
meagreness and inadequacy of expression, although
it is a fault which characterises an obscure style rather
than one which lacks ornament. But
                    <hi rend="italic">meiosis</hi>
                    may be
deliberately employed, and is then called a figure,
as also is
                    <hi rend="italic">tautology,</hi>
                    which means the repetition of a
word or phrase.
                    <milestone n="51" unit="section"/>
                    The latter, though not avoided
with special care even by the best authors, may
sometimes be regarded as a fault: it is, in fact, a
blemish into which Cicero not infrequently falls
through indifference to such minor details: take, for
example, the following passage,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Cluent.</hi>
                        xxxv. 96. To bring out the effect criticised
by Cicero,
                        <hi rend="italic">iudicium</hi>
                        must he translated
                        <quote>judgment.</quote>
                        But
                        <quote>trial</quote>
                        is required to give the correct sense.
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)pana/lhyis</foreign>
                        = repetition.
                    </note>
                    <quote>Judges, this judgment was not merely unlike a judgment.</quote>
                    It is sometimes given another name,
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)pana/lhyis,</foreign>
                    under
which appellation it is ranked among figures, of
which I shall give examples when I come to the
discussion of stylistic virtues.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">IX. ii.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="52" unit="section"/>
                    A worse fault is
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">o(moei/deia,</foreign>
                    or sameness, a term
applied to a style which has no variety to relieve
its tedium, and which presents a uniform monotony
of hue. This is one of the surest signs of lack of art,
and produces a uniquely unpleasing effect, not merely
on the mind, but on the ear, on account of its
                    <pb xml:id="p.241"/>
                    sameness of thought, the uniformity of its figures, and
the monotony of its structure.
                    <milestone n="53" unit="section"/>
                    We must also avoid
                    <hi rend="italic">macrology,</hi>
                    that is, the employment of more words
than are necessary, as, for instance, in the sentence
of Livy,
                    <quote>The ambassadors, having failed to obtain peace, went back home, whence they had come.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Fr.</hi>
                        62,
                        <hi rend="italic">Hertz.</hi>
                    </note>
                    On the other hand,
                    <hi rend="italic">periphrasis,</hi>
                    which is akin to this
blemish, is regarded as a virtue. Another fault is
                    <hi rend="italic">pleonasm,</hi>
                    when we overload our style with a superfluity of words, as in the phrase,
                    <quote>I saw it with my eyes,</quote>
                    where
                    <quote>I saw it</quote>
                    would have been
sufficient.
                    <milestone n="54" unit="section"/>
                    Cicero passed a witty comment on a
fault of this kind in a declamation of Hirtius when
he said that a child had been carried for ten months
in his mother's womb.
                    <quote>Oh,</quote>
                    he said,
                    <quote>I suppose other women carry them in their bags.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">perulra</hi>
                        means
                        <quote>a small wallet.</quote>
                        But it is noteworthy
that in Apul.
                        <hi rend="italic">Met.</hi>
                        V. xiv. it is used
                        <hi rend="italic">= uterus,</hi>
                        and the
                        <hi rend="italic">doubleentendre</hi>
                        was probably current in Cicero's time.
                    </note>
                    Sometimes, however, the form of pleonasm, of which I
have just given an example, may have a pleasing
effect when employed for the sake of emphasis, as
in the Virgilian phrase
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                        iv- 359.
                    </note>
                    :
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">With mine own ears his voice I heard.</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    But whenever the addition is not deliberate,
                    <milestone n="55" unit="section"/>
                    but
merely tame and redundant, it must be regarded as
a fault. There is also a fault entitled
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">periergi/a,</foreign>
                    which
I may perhaps translate by superfluous elaboration,
which differs from its corresponding virtue much as
fussiness differs from industry, and superstition from
religion. Finally, every word which neither helps
the sense nor the style may be regarded as faulty.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="56" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Cacozelia,</hi>
                    or perverse affectation, is a fault in every
kind of style: for it includes all that is turgid,
trivial, luscious, redundant, far-fetched or extravagant, while the same name is also applied to virtues
                    <pb xml:id="p.243"/>
                    carried to excess, when the mind loses its critical
sense and is misled by the false appearance of
beauty, the worst of all offences against style, since
other faults are due to carelessness, but this is
deliberate.
                    <milestone n="57" unit="section"/>
                    This form of affectation, however, affects
style alone. For the employment of arguments which
might equally well be advanced by the other side,
or are foolish, inconsistent or superfluous, are all
faults of matter, whereas corruption of style is
revealed in the employment of improper or redundant
words, in obscurity of meaning, effeminacy of rhythm,
or in the childish search for similar or ambiguous
expressions.
                    <milestone n="58" unit="section"/>
                    Further, it always involves insincerity,
even though all insincerity does not imply affectation.
For it consists in saying something in an unnatural
or unbecoming or superfluous manner. Style may,
however, be corrupted in precisely the same number
of ways that it may be adorned. But I have discussed this subject at greater length in another
work,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The lost
                        <hi rend="italic">De causis corruptae eloquentiae.</hi>
                    </note>
                    and have frequently called attention to it in
this, while I shall have occasion to mention it continually in the remaining books. For in dealing with
ornament, I shall occasionally speak of faults which
have to be avoided, but which are hard to distinguish
from virtues.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="59" unit="section"/>
                    To these blemishes may be added faulty arrangement or
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)noikono/mhton,</foreign>
                    the faulty use of figures or
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)sxhma/tiston,</foreign>
                    and the faulty collocation of words
or
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">kakosu/nqeton.</foreign>
                    But, as I have already discussed
arrangement, I will confine myself to the consideration of figures and structure. There is also a fault
known as
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">*sardismo\s,</foreign>
                    which consists in the indiscriminate use of several different dialects, as, for
instance, would result from mixing Doric, Ionic, and
                    <pb xml:id="p.245"/>
                    even Aeolic words with Attic.
                    <milestone n="60" unit="section"/>
                    A similar fault is
found amongst ourselves, consisting in the indiscriminate mixture of grand words with mean, old
with new, and poetic with colloquial, the result
being a monstrous medley like that described by
Horace in the opening portion of his
                    <hi rend="italic">Ars poetica,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">A. P. I.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="F">If a painter choose</l>
                            <l part="N">To place a man's head on a horse's neck,</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    and, be proceeds to say, should add other limbs from
different animals.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="61" unit="section"/>
                    The ornate is something that goes beyond what
is merely lucid and acceptable. It consists firstly
in forming a clear conception of what we wish to
say, secondly in giving this adequate expression,
and thirdly in lending it additional brilliance, a
process which may correctly be termed embellishment. Consequently we must place among ornaments
that
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)na/rgeia</foreign>
                    which I mentioned in the rules which
I laid down for the statement of facts,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                        ii. 63.
                    </note>
                    because vivid
illustration, or, as some prefer to call it, representation, is something more than mere clearness, since
the latter merely lets itself be seen, whereas the
former thrusts itself upon our notice.
                    <milestone n="62" unit="section"/>
                    It is a great
gift to be able to set forth the facts on which
we are speaking clearly and vividly. For oratory
fails of its full effect, and does not assert itself
as it should, if its appeal is merely to the hearing,
and if the judge merely feels that the facts
on which he has to give his decision are being
narrated to him, and not displayed in their living
truth to the eyes of the mind.
                    <milestone n="63" unit="section"/>
                    But since different
views have been held with regard to this art of
representation, I shall not attempt to divide it into
                    <pb xml:id="p.247"/>
                    all its different departments, whose number is
ostentatiously multiplied by certain writers, but
shall content myself with touching on those which
appear to me to be absolutely necessary. There is,
then, to begin with, one form of vividness which consists in giving an actual word-picture of a scene, as
in the passage beginning,
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">
                                Forthwith each hero tiptoe stood erect.
                                <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                    v. 426.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    Other details follow which give us such a picture
of the two boxers confronting each other for the
fight, that it could not have been clearer had we
been actual spectators.
                    <milestone n="64" unit="section"/>
                    Cicero is supreme in this
department, as in others. Is there anybody so incapable of forming a mental picture of a scene that,
when he reads the following passage from the
Verrines,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">v. xxxiii. 86.</note>
                    he does not seem not merely to see the
actors in the scene, the place itself and their very
dress, but even to imagine to himself other details
that the orator does not describe?
                    <quote>
                        There on the
shore stood the praetor, the representative of the
Roman people, with slippered feet, robed in a purple
cloak, a tunic streaming to his heels, and leaning on
the arm of this worthless woman.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="65" unit="section"/>
                    For my own
part, I seem to see before my eyes his face, his eyes,
the unseemly blandishments of himself and his paramour, the silent loathing and frightened shame of
those who viewed the scene.
                    <milestone n="66" unit="section"/>
                    At times, again, the
picture which we endeavour to present is fuller in
detail, as, for example, in the following description
of a luxurious banquet, which is also from Cicero,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        From the lost
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Gallio.</hi>
                    </note>
                    since he by himself is capable of supplying admirable
examples of every kind of oratorical ornament:
                    <quote>
                        I
seemed to see some entering, some leaving the room,
                        <pb xml:id="p.249"/>
                        some reeling under the influence of the wine, others
yawning with yesterday's potations. The floor was
foul with wine-smears, covered with wreaths half-withered and littered with fishbones.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="67" unit="section"/>
                    What more
would any man have seen who had actually entered
the room? So, too, we may move our hearers to
tears by the picture of a captured town. For the
mere statement that the town was stormed, while
no doubt it embraces all that such a calamity involves, has all the curtness of a dispatch, and fails
to penetrate to the emotions of the hearer.
                    <milestone n="68" unit="section"/>
                    But if
we expand all that the one word
                    <quote>stormed</quote>
                    includes,
we shall see the flames pouring from house and
temple, and hear the crash of falling roofs and one
confused clamour blent of many cries: we shall
behold some in doubt whither to fly, others clinging
to their nearest and dearest in one last embrace,
while the wailing of women and children and the
laments of old men that the cruelty of fate should
have spared them to see that day will strike upon
our ears.
                    <milestone n="69" unit="section"/>
                    Then will come the pillage of treasure
sacred and profane, the hurrying to and fro of the
plunderers as they carry off their booty or return to
seek for more, the prisoners driven each before his
own inhuman captor, the mother struggling to keep
her child, and the victors fighting over the richest
of the spoil. For though, as I have already said,
the sack of a city includes all these things, it is less
effective to tell the whole news at once than to
recount it detail by detail.
                    <milestone n="70" unit="section"/>
                    And we shall secure
the vividness we seek, if only our descriptions give
the impression of truth, nay, we may even add
fictitious incidents of the type which commonly
occur. The same vivid impression may be produced
                    <pb xml:id="p.251"/>
                    also by the mention of the
                    <hi rend="italic">accidents</hi>
                    of each
situation:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="F">Chill shudderings shake my limbs</l>
                                <l part="N">And all my blood is curdled cold with fear;</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                iii. 29
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    or
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="F">And trembling mothers clasped</l>
                                <l part="N">Their children to their breast.</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                vii. 518.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    Though the attainment of such effects is,
                    <milestone n="71" unit="section"/>
                    in my
opinion, the highest of all oratorical gifts, it is far
from difficult of attainment. Fix your eyes on nature
and follow her. All eloquence is concerned with
the activities of life, while every man applies to
himself what he hears from others, and the mind
is always readiest to accept what it recognises to
be true to nature.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="72" unit="section"/>
                    The invention of
                    <hi rend="italic">similes</hi>
                    has also provided an
admirable means of illuminating our descriptions.
Some of these are designed for insertion among
our arguments to help our proof, while others are
devised to make our pictures yet more vivid; it is
with this latter class of simile that I am now specially
concerned. The following are good examples:—
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Thence like fierce wolves beneath the cloud of night,</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">Aen. ii. 355.</bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    or
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="M">Like the bird that flies</l>
                                <l part="N">Around the shore and the fish-haunted reef,</l>
                                <l part="N">Skimming the deep.</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">Aen. iv. 254.</bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="73" unit="section"/>
                    In employing this form of ornament we must be
especially careful that the subject chosen for our
simile is neither obscure nor unfamiliar: for anything that is selected for the purpose of illuminating
                    <pb xml:id="p.253"/>
                    something else must itself be clearer than that which
it is designed to illustrate. Therefore while we may
permit poets to employ such similes as:—
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">As when Apollo wintry Lycia leaves,</l>
                                <l part="N">And Xanthus' streams, or visits Delos' isle,</l>
                                <l part="N">His mother's home,</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                iv. 143.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    it would be quite unsuitable for an orator to illustrate
something quite plain by such obscure allusions.
                    <milestone n="74" unit="section"/>
                    But even the type of simile which I discussed in
connexion with arguments
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                        xi. 22.
                    </note>
                    is an ornament to oratory,
and serves to make it sublime, rich, attractive or
striking, as the case may be. For the more remote
the simile is from the subject to which it is applied,
the greater will be the impression of novelty and the
unexpected which it produces.
                    <milestone n="75" unit="section"/>
                    The following type
may be regarded as commonplace and useful only as
helping to create an impression of sincerity:
                    <quote>
                        As
the soil is improved and rendered more fertile by
culture, so is the mind by education,
                    </quote>
                    or
                    <quote>
                        As
physicians amputate mortified limbs, so must we
lop away foul and dangerous criminals, even though
they be bound to us by ties of blood.
                    </quote>
                    Far finer is
the following from Cicero's
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Arch.</hi>
                        viii. 19.
                    </note>
                    defence of Archias:
                    <quote>
                        Rock and deserts reply to the voice of man, savage
beasts are oft-times tamed by the power of music
and stay their onslaught,
                    </quote>
                    and the rest.
                    <milestone n="76" unit="section"/>
                    This type
of simile has, however, sadly degenerated in the
hands of some of our declaimers owing to the license
of the schools. For they adopt false comparisons,
and even then do not apply them as they should
to the subjects to which they wish them to provide
a parallel. Both these faults are exemplified in
two similes which were on the lips of everyone
                    <pb xml:id="p.255"/>
                    when I was a young man,
                    <quote>Even the sources of mighty rivers are navigable,</quote>
                    and
                    <quote>The generous tree bears fruit while it is yet a sapling.</quote>
                    <milestone n="77" unit="section"/>
                    In every
comparison the simile either precedes or follows the
subject which it illustrates. But sometimes it is
free and detached, and sometimes, a far better
arrangement, is attached to the subject which it
illustrates, the correspondence between the resemblances being exact, an effect produced by
                    <hi rend="italic">reciprocal representation,</hi>
                    which the Greeks style
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)ntapo/dosis.</foreign>
                    For example, the simile already quoted,
                    <milestone n="78" unit="section"/>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">
                                    Thence like fierce wolves beneath the cloud of
                                    <lb/>
                                    night,
                                </l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                ii. 355.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    precedes its subject. On the other hand, an example
of the simile following its subject is to be found in
the first
                    <hi rend="italic">Georgic,</hi>
                    where, after the long lamentation
over the wars civil and foreign that have afflicted
Rome, there come the lines:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">As when, their barriers down, the chariots speed</l>
                                <l part="N">Lap after lap; in vain the charioteer</l>
                                <l part="N">Tightens the curb: his steeds ungovernable</l>
                                <l part="N">Sweep him away nor heeds the car the rein.</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Georg. i.</hi>
                                512.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    There is, however, no
                    <hi rend="italic">antapodosis</hi>
                    in these similes.
                    <milestone n="79" unit="section"/>
                    Such
                    <hi rend="italic">reciprocal representation</hi>
                    places both subjects of
comparison before our very eyes, displaying them
side by side. Virgil provides many remarkable examples, but it will be better for me to quote from
oratory. In the
                    <hi rend="italic">pro Murena</hi>
                    Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Mur.</hi>
                        xiii. 29.
                    </note>
                    says,
                    <quote>
                        As among
Greek musicians (for so they say), only those turn
flute-players that cannot play the lyre, so here at
Rome we see that those who cannot acquire the art
of oratory betake themselves to the study of the
                        <pb xml:id="p.257"/>
                        law.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="80" unit="section"/>
                    There is also another simile in the same
speech,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Mur.</hi>
                        xvii. 36.
                    </note>
                    which is almost worthy of a poet, but in
virtue of its
                    <hi rend="italic">reciprocal representation</hi>
                    is better adapted
for ornament:
                    <quote>
                        For as tempests are generally preceded by some premonitory signs in the heaven, but
often, on the other hand, break forth for some obscure
reason without any warning whatsoever, so in the
tempests which sway the people at our Roman
elections we are not seldom in a position to discern
their origin, and yet, on the other hand, it is frequently so obscure that the storm seems to have
burst without any apparent cause.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="81" unit="section"/>
                    We find also
shorter similes, such as
                    <quote>Wandering like wild beasts through the woods,</quote>
                    or the passage from Cicero's
speech against Clodius:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Now lost.</note>
                    <quote>He fled from the court like a man escaping naked from a fire.</quote>
                    Similar
examples from everyday speech will occur to
everyone.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Such comparisons reveal the gift not merely of
placing a thing vividly before the eye, but of doing
so with rapidity and without waste of detail.
                    <milestone n="82" unit="section"/>
                    The
praise awarded to perfect brevity is well-deserved;
but, on the other hand,
                    <hi rend="italic">brachylogy,</hi>
                    which I shall
deal with when I come to speak of figures, that is
to say, the brevity that says nothing more than what
is absolutely necessary, is less effective, although it
may be employed with admirable results when it
expresses a great deal in a very few words, as in
Sallust's description of Mithridates as
                    <quote>huge of stature, and armed to match.</quote>
                    But unsuccessful
attempts to imitate this form of terseness result
merely in obscurity.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="83" unit="section"/>
                    A virtue which closely resembles the last, but
is on a grander scale, is
                    <hi rend="italic">emphasis,</hi>
                    which succeeds
                    <pb xml:id="p.259"/>
                    in revealing a deeper meaning than is actually
expressed by the words. There are two kinds of
                    <hi rend="italic">emphasis:</hi>
                    the one means more than it says, the
other often means something which it does not
actually say.
                    <milestone n="84" unit="section"/>
                    An example of the former is found
in Homer,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Od.</hi>
                        xi. 523.
                    </note>
                    where he makes Menelaus say that the
Greeks
                    <hi rend="italic">descended</hi>
                    into the Wooden Horse, indicating
its size by a single verb. Or again, there is the
following example by Virgil:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                        ii. 262.
                    </note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">Descending by a rope let down,</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    a phrase which in a similar manner indicates the
height of the horse. The same poet,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                        iii. 631.
                    </note>
                    when he says
that the Cyclops lay stretched
                    <quote>throughout the cave,</quote>
                    by taking the room occupied as the standard
of measure, gives an impression of the giant's
immense bulk.
                    <milestone n="85" unit="section"/>
                    The second kind of
                    <hi rend="italic">emphasis</hi>
                    consists either in the complete suppression of a word
or in the deliberate omission to utter it. As an
example of complete suppression I may quote the
following passage from the
                    <hi rend="italic">pro Ligario,</hi>
                    4 where
Cicero says:
                    <quote>
                        But if your exalted position were
not matched by your goodness of heart, a quality
which is all your own, your very own—I know
well enough what I am saying——
                    </quote>
                    Here he suppresses the fact, which is none the less clear enough
to us, that he does not lack counsellors who would
incite him to cruelty. The omission of a word is produced by
                    <hi rend="italic">aposiopesis,</hi>
                    which, however, being a figure,
shall be dealt with in its proper place.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        v. 15: The passage goes on,
                        <quote>
                            Then your victory
would have brought bitter grief in its train. For how many
of the victors would have wished you to be cruel!
                        </quote>
                        Where
then is the
                        <hi rend="italic">suppression?</hi>
                        Quintilian is probably quoting from
memory and has forgotten the context.
ix. ii. 54; iii. 60.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="86" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Emphasis is</hi>
                    also found in the phrases of every day, such as
                    <quote>Be a man!</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>He is but mortal,</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>We must live!</quote>
                    So like, as a rule, is nature to art.
                </p>
                <p>
                    It is not, however, sufficient for eloquence to set
                    <pb xml:id="p.261"/>
                    forth its theme in brilliant and vivid language:
there are many different ways of embellishing our
style.
                    <milestone n="87" unit="section"/>
                    For even that absolute and unaffected simplicity which the Greeks call
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)fe/leia</foreign>
                    has in it a
certain chaste ornateness such as we admire also in
women, while a minute accuracy in securing propriety and precision in our words likewise produces
an impression of neatness and delicacy. Again
copiousness may consist either in wealth of thought
or luxuriance of language.
                    <milestone n="88" unit="section"/>
                    Force, too, may be
shown in different ways; for there will always be
force in anything that is in its own way effective.
Its most important exhibitions are to be found in
the following:
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">dei/nwsis</foreign>
                    or a certain sublimity in the
exaggerated denunciation of unworthy conduct, to
mention no other topics;
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">fantasi/a</foreign>
                    or imagination,
which assists us to form mental pictures of things;
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)cergasi/a</foreign>
                    or finish, which produces completeness of
effect;
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)pecergasi/a</foreign>
                    an intensified form of the preceding, which reasserts our proofs and clinches the
argument by repetition;
                    <milestone n="89" unit="section"/>
                    and
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)ne/rgeia,</foreign>
                    or vigour, a
near relative of all these qualities, which derives
its name from action and finds its peculiar function
in securing that nothing that we say is tame.
Bitterness, which is generally employed in abuse,
may be of service as in the following passage.
from Cassius:
                    <quote>
                        What will you do when I invade
your special province, that is, when I show that,
as far as abuse is concerned, you are a mere
ignoramus?
                    </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Cassius Severus was famous for his powers of abuse.
His opponent was abusive. Cassius says that he will take a
leaf out of his book and show him what real abuse is.
                    </note>
                    Pungency also may be employed,
as in the following remark of Crassus:
                    <quote>Shall I regard you as a consul, when you refuse to regard me as a senator?</quote>
                    But the real power of
oratory lies in enhancing or attenuating the force
                    <pb xml:id="p.263"/>
                    of words. Each of these departments has the same
number of methods; I shall touch on the more important; those omitted will be of a like character,
while all are concerned either with words or things.
I have, however,
                    <milestone n="90" unit="section"/>
                    already dealt with the methods of
invention and arrangement, and shall therefore now
concern myself with the way in which style may
elevate or depress the subject in hand.
                </p>
                <p>
                    IV. The first method of
                    <hi rend="italic">amplification</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italic">attenuation</hi>
                    is to be found in the actual word employed to
describe a thing. For example, we may say that
a man who was
                    <hi rend="italic">beaten</hi>
                    was
                    <hi rend="italic">murdered,</hi>
                    or that a
                    <hi rend="italic">dishonest</hi>
                    fellow is a
                    <hi rend="italic">robber,</hi>
                    or, on the other hand, we
may say that one who
                    <hi rend="italic">struck</hi>
                    another merely
                    <hi rend="italic">touched</hi>
                    him, and that one who
                    <hi rend="italic">wounded</hi>
                    another merely
                    <hi rend="italic">hurt</hi>
                    him. The following passage from the
                    <hi rend="italic">pro Caelio,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">xvi. 38.</note>
                    provides examples of both:
                    <quote>
                        If a widow lives
                        <hi rend="italic">freely,</hi>
                        if being by nature bold she throws restraint
to the winds, makes wealth an excuse for luxury,
and strong passions for playing the harlot, would
this be a reason for my regarding a man who was
somewhat free in his method of saluting her to be
an adulterer?
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    For here he calls an immodest
woman a harlot, and says that one who had long
been her lover saluted her with a certain freedom.
This sort of
                    <hi rend="italic">amplification</hi>
                    may be strengthened
and made more striking by pointing the comparison between words of stronger meaning and
those for which we propose to substitute them, as
Cicero does in denouncing Verres
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Verr. I.</hi>
                        iii. 9.
                    </note>
                    :
                    <quote>
                        I have brought
before you, judges, not a thief, but a plunderer;
not an adulterer, but a ravisher; not a mere committer of sacrilege, but the enemy of all religious
observance and all holy things; not an assassin,
                        <pb xml:id="p.265"/>
                        but a bloodthirsty butcher who has slain our fellowcitizens and our allies.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    In this passage the
first epithets are bad enough, but are rendered
still worse by those which follow. I consider,
However, that there are four principal methods of
                    <hi rend="italic">implication: augmentation, comparison, reasoning</hi>
                    and
accumulation.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Of these,
                    <hi rend="italic">augmentation</hi>
                    is most impressive when it
ends grandeur even to comparative insignificance.
This may be effected either by one step or by
everal, and may be carried not merely to the
highest degree, but sometimes even beyond it.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    A single example from Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Verr.</hi>
                        v. lxvi. 170.
                    </note>
                    will suffice to
llustrate all these points.
                    <quote>
                        It is a sin to bind a
Roman citizen, a crime to scourge him, little short
if the most unnatural murder to put him to death;
chat then shall I call his crucifixion?
                    </quote>
                    If he had
merely been scourged, we should have had but one
tep, indicated by the description even of the lesser
offence as a
                    <hi rend="italic">sin,</hi>
                    while if he had merely been killed,
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    we should have had several more steps; but after
saying that it was
                    <quote>little short of the most unatural murder to put him to death,</quote>
                    and mentioning the worst of crimes, he adds,
                    <quote>What then shall call his crucifixion?</quote>
                    Consequently, since he had
ready exhausted his vocabulary of crime, words
must necessarily fail him to describe something still
orse.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    There is a second method of passing beond the highest degree, exemplified in Virgil's
description of Lausus:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                        vii. 649.
                    </note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">Than whom there was not one more fair</l>
                            <l part="I">Saving Laurentian Turnus.</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    or here the words
                    <quote>
                        than whom there was not
                        <pb xml:id="p.267"/>
                        one more fair
                    </quote>
                    give us the superlative, on which
the poet proceeds to superimpose a still higher
degree.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    There is also a third sort, which is not
attained by gradation, a height which is not a
degree beyond the superlative, but such that
nothing greater can be conceived.
                    <quote>You beat your mother. What more need I say? You beat your mother.</quote>
                    For to make a thing so great as
to be incapable of augmentation is in itself a kind
of augmentation.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    It is also possible to heighten
our style less obviously, but perhaps yet more effectively, by introducing a continuous and unbroken
series in which each word is stronger than the last,
as Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Phil.</hi>
                        I. xxv. 63.
                    </note>
                    does when he describes how Antony
vomited
                    <quote>
                        before an assembly of the Roman people,
while performing a public duty, while Master of the
Horse.
                    </quote>
                    Each phrase is more forcible than that
which went before. Vomiting is an ugly thing in
itself, even when there is no assembly to witness
it; it is ugly when there is such an assembly, even
though it be not an assembly of the people; ugly
even though it be an assembly of the people and
not the Roman people; ugly even though he were
engaged on no business at the time, even if his
business were not public business, even if lie were
not Master of the Horse.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Another might have
broken up the series and lingered over each step
in the ascending scale, but Cicero hastens to his
climax and reaches the height not by laborious
effort, but by the impetus of his speed.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Just as this form of
                    <hi rend="italic">amplification</hi>
                    rises to a climax,
so, too, the form which depends on
                    <hi rend="italic">comparison</hi>
                    seeks
to rise from the less to the greater, since by raising
what is below it must necessarily exalt that which
                    <pb xml:id="p.269"/>
                    is above, as, for example: in the following passage:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Phil. II.</hi>
                        xxv. 63.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        If this had befallen you at the dinner-table in
the midst of your amazing potations, who would
not have thought it unseemly? But it occurred at
an assembly of the Roman people.
                    </quote>
                    Or take this
passage from the speech against Catiline:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Phil.</hi>
                        I. vii. 17.
xi 32.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        In
truth, if my slaves feared me as all your fellowcitizens fear you, I should think it wise to leave my
house.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    At times, again, we may advance a parallel
to make something which we desire to exaggerate
seem greater than ever, as Cicero does in the
                    <hi rend="italic">pro Cluentio,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">cp.</hi>
                        v. xiii. 24.
                    </note>
                    where, after telling a story of a woman
of Miletus who took a bribe from the reversionary
heirs to prevent the birth of her expected child,
lie cries,
                    <quote>
                        How much greater is the punishment
deserved by Oppianicus for the same offence! For
that woman, by doing violence to her own body
did but torture herself, whereas he procured
the same result by applying violence and torture
to the body of another.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    I would not, however,
have anyone think that this method is identical
with that used in argument, where the greater is
inferred from the less, although there is a certain
resemblance between the two. For in the latter
case we are aiming at proof, in the former at
                    <hi rend="italic">amplification;</hi>
                    for example, in the passage just cited
about Oppianicus, the object of the comparison is
not to show that his action was a crime, but that
it was even worse than another crime. There is,
however, a certain affinity between the two methods,
and I will therefore repeata passage which I
quoted there, although my present purpose is
different.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    For what I have now to demonstrate is
that when amplification is our purpose we
                    <pb xml:id="p.271"/>
                    compare not merely whole with whole, but part with
part, as in the following passage:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cat.</hi>
                        i. i. 3.
                        <hi rend="italic">Phil.</hi>
                        ii. xxv. 63.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        Did that illustrious citizen, the pontifex maximus, Publius Scipio,
acting merely in his private capacity, kill Tiberius
Gracchus when he introduced but slight changes
for the worse that did not seriously impair the
constitution of the state, and shall we as consuls
suffer Catiline to live, whose aim was to lay waste
the whole world with fire and sword?
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Here
Catiline is compared to Gracchus, the constitution
of the state to the whole world, a slight change for
the worse to fire and sword and desolation, and a
private citizen to the consuls, all comparisons
affording ample opportunity for further individual
expansion, if anyone should desire so to do.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    With regard to the
                    <hi rend="italic">amplificalion</hi>
                    produced by
                    <hi rend="italic">reasoning,</hi>
                    we must consider whether
                    <hi rend="italic">reasoning</hi>
                    quite
expresses my meaning. I am not a stickler for
exact terminology, provided the sense is clear to
any serious student. My motive in using this term
was, however, this, that this form of amplification
produces its effect at a point other than that where
it is actually introduced. One thing is magnified
in order to effect a corresponding augmentation elsewhere, and it is by reasoning that our hearers are
then led on from the first point to the second which
we desire to emplasise.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Cicero, when he is about
to reproach Antony with his drunkenness and
vomiting, says,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cat.</hi>
                        i. i. 3.
                        <hi rend="italic">Phil.</hi>
                        ii. xxv. 63.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        You with such a throat, such
flanks, such burly strength in every limb of your
prize-fighter's body,
                    </quote>
                    etc. What have his throat
and flanks to do with his drunkenness? The
reference is far from pointless: for by looking at
them we are enabled to estimate the quantity of
                    <pb xml:id="p.273"/>
                    the wine which he drank at Hippias' wedding, and
was unable to carry or digest in spite of the fact
that his bodily strength was worthy of a prizefighter. Accordingly if, in such a case, one thing is
inferred from another, the term
                    <hi rend="italic">reasoning</hi>
                    is neither
improper nor extraordinary, since it has been
applied on similar grounds to one of the
                    <hi rend="italic">bases.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See III. vi. 43 sqq. VII. v. 2.</note>
                    So, again,
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    amplification results from subsequent
events, since the violence with which the wine
burst from him was such that the vomiting was
not accidental nor voluntary, but a matter of
necessity, at a moment when it was specially unseemly, while the food was not recently swallowed,
as is sometimes the case, but the residue of the revel
of the preceding day.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand,
                    <hi rend="italic">amplification</hi>
                    may equally result from antecedent circumstances; for example, when Juno made her request
to Aeolus, the latter
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                        i. 81.
                    </note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="M">"Turned his spear and smote</l>
                        <l part="N">The mountain's caverned side, and forth the winds</l>
                        <l part="I">Rushed in a throng,"</l>
                    </quote>
                    whereby the poet shows what a mighty tempest will
ensue.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    Again, when we have depicted some horrible
circumstance in such colours as to raise the detestation of our audience to its height, we then proceed
to make light of them in order that what is to follow
may seem still more horrible: consider the following
passage from Cicero:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Verr.</hi>
                        5, 44, 177.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        These are but trivial offences
for so great a criminal. The captain of a warship
from a famous city bought off' his threatened scourging for a price: a humane concession! Another
paid down a sum of money to save his head from
the axe:
                        <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                        a perfectly ordinary circumstance!
                    </quote>
                    Does
                    <pb xml:id="p.275"/>
                    not the orator employ a process of reasoning to
enable the audience to infer how great the implied
crime must be when such actions were but humane
and ordinary in comparison? So, again, one thing
may be magnified by allusion to another: the valour
of Scipio is magnified by extolling the fame of
Hannibal as a general, and we are asked to marvel
at the courage of the Germans and the Gauls in
order to enhance the glory of Gaius Caesar.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    There
is a similar form of
                    <hi rend="italic">amplification</hi>
                    which is effected by
reference to something which appears to have been
said with quite another purpose in view. The chiefs
of Troy
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Il.</hi>
                        iii. 156.
                    </note>
                    think it no discredit that Trojan and Greek
should endure so many woes for so many years all
for the sake of Helen's beauty. How wondrous,
then, must her beauty have been! For it is not
Paris, her ravisher, that says this; it is not some
youth or one of the common herd; no, it is the
elders, the wisest of their folk, the counsellors of
Priam.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    Nay, even the king himself, worn out by a
ten years' war, which had cost him the loss of so many
of his sons, and threatened to lay his kingdom in the
dust, the man who, above all, should have loathed
and detested her beauty, the source of all those
tears, hears these words, calls her his daughter, and
places her by his side, excuses her guilt, and denies
that she is the cause of his sorrows.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    Again, when
Plato in the Symposium
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">218B–219D.</note>
                    makes Alcibiades confess
how he had wished Socrates to treat him, he does
not, I think, record these facts with a view to
blaming Aleibiades, but rather to show the unconquerable self-control of Socrates, which would
not yield even to the charms which the greatest
beauty of his day so frankly placed at his disposal.
                    <pb xml:id="p.277"/>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    We are even given the means of realising the
extraordinary stature of the heroes of old by the
description of their weapons, such as the shield of
Ajax
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Il.</hi>
                        vii. 219.
                    </note>
                    and the spear-shaft of Achilles
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Il.</hi>
                        xvi. 140.
                    </note>
                    hewn in the
forests of Pelion. Virgil
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic"> Aen.</hi>
                        iii. 659.
                    </note>
                    also has made admirable
use of this device in his description of the Cyclops.
For what an image it gives us of the bulk of that
body
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">
                                Whose hand was propped by a branchless trunk of
                                <lb/>
                                pine.
                            </l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    So, too, what a giant must Demoleos
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                        v. 264.
                    </note>
                    have been,
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    Whose
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="M">corselet manifold</l>
                            <l part="N">Scarce two men on their shoulders could uphold</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    And yet the hero buckled it upon him and
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">Drave the scattering Trojans at full speed.</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    And again, Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Phil.</hi>
                        ii. 27.
                    </note>
                    could hardly even have conceived of such luxury in Antony himself as he
describes when he says,
                    <quote>
                        You might see beds in
the chambers of his slaves strewn with the purple
coverlets that had once been Pompey's own.
                    </quote>
                    Slaves
are using purple coverlets in their chambers, aye,
and coverlets that had once been Pompey's! No
more, surely, can be said than this, and yet it leaves
us to infer how infinitely greater was the luxury of
their master.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    This form of
                    <hi rend="italic">amplification</hi>
                    is near akin
to
                    <hi rend="italic">emphasis:</hi>
                    but emphasis derives its effect from
the actual words, while in this case the effect is
produced by inference from the facts, and is consequently far more impressive, inasmuch as facts are
more impressive than words.
                </p>
                <pb xml:id="p.279"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Accumulation</hi>
                    of words and sentences identical in
meaning may also be regarded under the head of
                    <hi rend="italic">amplification.</hi>
                    For although the climax is not in
this case reached by a series of steps, it is none the
less attained by the piling up of words. Take the
following example:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Lig.</hi>
                        iii. 9.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        What was that sword of yours
doing, Tubero, the sword you drew on the field of
Pharsalus? Against whose body did you aim its
point? What meant those arms you bore? Whither
were your thoughts, your eyes, your hand, your fiery
courage directed on that day? What passion, what
desires were yours?
                    </quote>
                    This passage recalls the figure
styled
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">sunaqroismo/s</foreign>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <quote>accumulation.</quote>
                    </note>
                    by the Greeks, but in that
figure it is a number of different things that are
accumulated, whereas in this passage all the accumulated details have but one reference. The
heightening of effect may also be produced by
making the words rise to a climax.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Verr.</hi>
                        xv. xlv. 118.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        There stood
the porter of the prison, the praetor's executioner,
the death and terror of the citizens and allies of
Rome, the lictor Sextius.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Attenuation</hi>
                    is effected by the same method, since
there are as many degrees of descent as ascent.
I shall therefore content myself with quoting but
one example, namely, the words used by Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Leg. Agr.</hi>
                        II. V. 13.
                    </note>
                    to
describe the speech of Rullus:
                    <quote>
                        A few, however, who
stood nearest to him suspected that he had intended
to say something about the agrarian law.
                    </quote>
                    This passage may be regarded as providing an example of
                    <hi rend="italic">attenuation</hi>
                    or of
                    <hi rend="italic">augmentation,</hi>
                    according as we consider its literal meaning or fix our attention on the
obscurity attributed to Rullus.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    I know that some may perhaps regard
                    <hi rend="italic">hyperbole</hi>
                    as a species of
                    <hi rend="italic">amplification,</hi>
                    since
                    <hi rend="italic">hyperbole</hi>
                    can be
                    <pb xml:id="p.281"/>
                    employed to create an effect in either direction.
But as the name is also applied to one of the
                    <hi rend="italic">tropes,</hi>
                    I must postpone its consideration for the present.
I would proceed to the immediate discussion of this
subject but for the fact that others have given
separate treatment to this form of artifice, [which
employs words not in their literal, but in a metaphorical sense
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See ch. vi.</note>
                    ]. I shall therefore at this point
indulge a desire now almost universal, and discuss
a form of ornament which many regard as the chief,
nay, almost the sole adornment of oratory.
                </p>
                <p>
                    V. When the ancients used the word
                    <hi rend="italic">sententia,</hi>
                    they meant a feeling, or opinion. The word is
frequently used in this sense by orators, and traces
of this meaning are still found even in the speech
of every day. For when we are going to take an
oath we use the phrase
                    <hi rend="italic">ex animi nostri sententia (in</hi>
                    accordance with what we hold is the solemn truth),
and when we offer congratulations, we say that we do
so
                    <hi rend="italic">ex sententia</hi>
                    (with all our heart). The ancients, indeed, often expressed the same meaning by saying
that they uttered their
                    <hi rend="italic">sensa;</hi>
                    for they regarded
                    <hi rend="italic">senses</hi>
                    as referring merely to the senses of the body.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    But modern usage applies
                    <hi rend="italic">sensus</hi>
                    to concepts of the
mind, while
                    <hi rend="italic">sentcntia</hi>
                    is applied to striking reflexions
such as are more especially introduced at the close
of our periods, a practice rare in earlier days, but
carried even to excess in our own. Accordingly, I
think that I ought to say something of the various
forms which such reflexions may tale and the manner
in which they should be used.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Although all the different forms are included
under the same name, the oldest type of
                    <hi rend="italic">sententia,</hi>
                    and that in which the term is most correctly applied,
                    <pb xml:id="p.283"/>
                    is the aphorism, called
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">gnw/mh</foreign>
                    by the Greeks. Both
the Greek and the Latin names are derived from
the fact that such utterances resemble the decrees
or resolutions of public bodies. The term, however,
is of wide application (indeed, such reflexions may
be deserving of praise even when they have no
reference to any special context), and is used in
various ways. Sometimes it refers merely to things,
as in the sentence:
                    <quote>
                        There is nothing that wins
the affections of the people more than goodness of
heart.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                            Cic.
                            <hi rend="italic">pro Lig.</hi>
                            xii. 37.
                        </note>
                    </quote>
                    Occasionally, again, they may have a
personal reference, as in the following utterance
of Domitius Afer:
                    <quote>The prince who would know all, must needs ignore much.</quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Some have called
this form of
                    <hi rend="italic">reflexion</hi>
                    a part of the
                    <hi rend="italic">enthymeme,</hi>
                    others
the major premise or conclusion of the
                    <hi rend="italic">epichireme,</hi>
                    as
it sometimes, though not invariably, is. More correct
is the statement that at times it is simple, as in the
example just quoted, while at other times a reason
for the statement may be added,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The premises of the enthymeme are simple, while those
of the epichireme are supported by a
                        <hi rend="italic">reason.</hi>
                        See v. xiv.
                    </note>
                    such as the following:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sall. Jug.</hi>
                        10.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        For in every struggle, the stronger seems not
to suffer wrong, even when this is actually the case,
but to inflict it, simply in virtue of his superior
power.
                    </quote>
                    Sometimes, again, it may be double, as in
the statement that
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Complaisance wins us friends, truth enmity.</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ter. Andr.</hi>
                                I. i. 41.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    There are some even who classify them under ten
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">##</note>
                    heads, though the principle on which they make
this division is such that it would justify a still
larger number: they class them as based on interrogation, comparison, denial, similarity, admiration,
and the like, for they can be treated under every
                    <pb xml:id="p.285"/>
                    kind of figure. A striking type is that which is
produced by opposition:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Death is not bitter, but the approach to death.</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">Author unknown.</bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    Others are cast in a form of a direct statement,
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    such as
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="F">The miser lacks</l>
                                <l part="N">
                                    That which he has no less than what he has
                                    <lb/>
                                    not.
                                </l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                Publil.
                                <hi rend="italic">Syr. Sent.</hi>
                                486.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    But they acquire greater force by a change in the
                    <hi rend="italic">figure</hi>
                    employed, as in the following:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Is it so bitter, then, to die?</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                xii. 646.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    For this is more vigorous than the simple statement,
                    <quote>Death is not bitter.</quote>
                    A similar effect may be produced by transference of' the statement from the
general to the particular. For example, although
the direct statement would be,
                    <quote>To hurt is easy, but to do good is hard.</quote>
                    Ovid
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">In his lost tragedy, the Medea.</note>
                    gives this reflexion
increased force when lie makes Medea say,
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">I had the power to save, and ask you then</l>
                            <l part="I">If I have power to ruin?</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">' Pro Lig.</hi>
                        xii. 38.
                    </note>
                    again gives the general statement a personal
turn when he says:
                    <quote>
                        Caesar, the splendour of your
present fortune confers on you nothing greater than
the power and nothing better than the will to save
as many of your fellow-citizens as possible.
                    </quote>
                    For
here he attributes to Caesar what was really attributable to the circumstances of his power. In
this class of
                    <hi rend="italic">reflexion</hi>
                    we must be careful, as always,
not to employ them too frequently, nor at random,
nor place them in the mouth of every kind of person,
                    <pb xml:id="p.287"/>
                    while we must make certain that they are not
untrue, as is so often the case with those speakers
who style them
                    <hi rend="italic">reflexions of universal application and</hi>
                    recklessly employ whatever seems to support their
case as though its truth were beyond question.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Such reflexions are best suited to those speakers
whose authority is such that their character itself
will lend weight to their words. For who would
tolerate a boy, or a youth, or even a man of low
birth who presumed to speak with all the authority
of a judge and to thrust his precepts down our throats?
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The term
                    <hi rend="italic">enthymeme</hi>
                    may be applied to any concept
of the mind, but in its strict sense means a
                    <hi rend="italic">reflexion</hi>
                    drawn from contraries. Consequently, it has a
supremacy among
                    <hi rend="italic">reflexions</hi>
                    which we may compare to that of Homer among poets and Rome
among cities.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    I have already said enough on this
topic in dealing with arguments.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See v. x. 2, and again, for greater detail, v. xiv. 1 (note
at end), where an example of this type of
                        <hi rend="italic">sententia</hi>
                        is given
from the
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Milone</hi>
                        (ch. 29)
                        <quote>
                            You are sitting to avenge the
death of one whom you would be unwilling to restore to life
even if you thought it was in your power to restore it!
                        </quote>
                    </note>
                    But the use of
the enthymeme is not confined to proof, it may sometimes be employed for the purpose of ornament, as
in the following instance:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Lig.</hi>
                        iv. 10.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        Caesar, shall the language of those whom it is your glory to have spared
goad you to imitate their own cruelty?
                    </quote>
                    Cicero's
motive in saying this is not that it introduces any
fresh reason for clemency, but because he has already
demonstrated by other arguments how unjust such
conduct would be,
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    while he adds it at the period's
close as an
                    <hi rend="italic">epiphonema,</hi>
                    not by way of proof, but as
a crowning insult to his opponents. For an
                    <hi rend="italic">epiphonema</hi>
                    is an exclamation attached to the close of a statement
or a proof by way of climax. Here are two examples:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Such toil it was to found the Roman race!</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                i. 33.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    and
                    <quote>
                        The virtuous youth preferred to risk his life
                        <pb xml:id="p.289"/>
                        by slaying him to suffering such dishonour.
                    </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Cic.
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Mil.</hi>
                        iv. 9,
                        <hi rend="italic">cp.</hi>
                        V. xi. 13.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    There
is also what our modern rhetoricians call the
                    <hi rend="italic">noema,</hi>
                    a term which may be taken to mean every kind of
                    <hi rend="italic">conception,</hi>
                    but is employed by them in the special
sense of things which they wish to be understood,
though they are not actually said, as in the declamation where the sister defends herself against the
brother whom she had often bought out from the
gladiatorial school, when he brought an action
against her demanding the infliction of a similar
mutilation because she had cut off his thumb while
he slept:
                    <quote>You deserved,</quote>
                    she cries,
                    <quote>to have all your fingers,</quote>
                    meaning thereby,
                    <quote>You deserved to be a gladiator all your days.</quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    There is also what
is called a
                    <hi rend="italic">clausula.</hi>
                    If this merely means a
                    <hi rend="italic">conclusion,</hi>
                    it is a perfectly correct and sometimes a
necessary device, as in the following case:
                    <quote>
                        You
must, therefore, first confess your own offence before
you accuse Ligarius of anything.
                    </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Lig. i. 2.</hi>
                        It is a conclusion in the logical sense.
But
                        <hi rend="italic">clausula</hi>
                        more commonly means
                        <quote>close, conclusion, cadence</quote>
                        of a period.
                        <hi rend="italic">Cp.</hi>
                        what follows.
                    </note>
                    But to-day
something more is meant, for our rhetoricians want
every passage, every sentence to strike the ear by
an impressive close.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    In fact, they think it a disgrace, nay, almost a crime, to pause to breathe
except at the end of a passage that is designed to
call forth applause. The result is a number of tiny
epigrams, affected, irrelevant and disjointed. For
there are not enough striking reflexions in the world
to provide a close to every period.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    The following forms of reflexion are even more
modern. There is the type which depends on surprise for its effect, as, for example, when Vibius
Crispus, in denouncing the man who wore a breastplate when strolling in the forum and alleged that
he did so because he feared for his life, cried,
                    <quote>
                        Who
                        <pb xml:id="p.291"/>
                        gave you leave to be such a coward?
                    </quote>
                    Another
instance is the striking remark made by Africanus
to Nero with reference to the death of Agrippina:
                    <quote>Caesar, your provinces of Gaul entreat you to bear your good fortune with courage.</quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Others are of
an allusive type: for example, Domitius Afer, in his
defence of Cloatilla, whom Claudius had pardoned
when she was accused of having buried her husband,
who had been one of the rebels, addressed her sons
in his peroration with the words:
                    <quote>Nonetheless, it is your duty, boys, to give your mother burial.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The point is uncertain. Possibly, as Gesner suggests,
the sons were accusing their mother.
                    </note>
                    Some, again,
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    depend on the fact that they are
transferred from one context to another Crispus,
in his defence of Spatale, whose lover had made her
his heir and then proceeded to die at the age
of eighteen, remarked:
                    <quote>What a marvellous fellow to gratify his passion thus!</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">sibi indulsit</hi>
                        would seen to mean his appointing S. his
heir and then being kind enough to die so soon! But the
point is uncertain.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    Another type of reflexion may be produced by the doubling of a phrase,
as in the letter written by Seneca for Nero to be sent
to the senate on the occasion of his mother's death,
with a view to creating the impression that he had
been in serious danger:—
                    <quote>As yet I cannot believe or rejoice that I am safe.</quote>
                    Better, however, is the
type which relies for its effect on contrast of opposites,
as
                    <quote>I know from whom to fly, but whom to follow I know not;</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Cic.
                        <hi rend="italic">ad Att.</hi>
                        VIII. vii. 2.
                    </note>
                    or,
                    <quote>
                        What of the fact that the poor
wretch, though he could not speak,
                        <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                        could not keep
silence?
                    </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Probably from the lost
                        <hi rend="italic">in Pisonem,</hi>
                        since St. Jerome in a
letter to Oceanus says
                        <hi rend="italic">postea vero Pisoniano vitio, cum loqui non post, tacere non poterat.</hi>
                        But here again the point is
obscure.
                    </note>
                    But to produce the most striking effect
this type should be given point by the introduction
of a comparison, such as is made by Trachalus in his
speech against Spatale, where he says:
                    <quote>
                        Is it your
pleasure, then, ye laws, the faithful guardians of
chastity, that wives should receive a title
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                            By the
                            <hi rend="italic">lex Julia et Papia Poppaea</hi>
                            childless wives were
only entitled to a tenth of their husband's estate.
                        </note>
                        and
harlots a quarter?
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb xml:id="p.293"/>
                <p>
                    In these instances, however, the reflexion may
equally well be good or bad.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand,
there are some which will always be bad, such as
those which turn on play upon words, as in the
following case:
                    <quote>
                        Conscript fathers, for I must
address you thus that you may remember the duty
owed to fathers.
                    </quote>
                    Worse still, as being more unreal
and far-fetched, is the remark made by the gladiator
mentioned above in his prosecution of his sister:
                    <quote>I have fought to the last finger.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The exact meaning is uncertain. The allusion may be to
the turning up of the thumb as a sign of defeat. See sect. 12.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    There is
another similar type, which is perhaps the worst of
all, where the play upon words is combined with a
false comparison. When I was a young man I heard
a distinguished pleader, after handing a mother some
splinters of bone taken from the head of her son
(which he did merely to provide an occasion for his
epigram), cry:
                    <quote>Unhappiest of women, your son is not yet dead and yet you have gathered up his bones!</quote>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    Moreover, most of our orators delight in
devices of the pettiest kind, which seriously considered are merely ludicrous, but at the moment of
their production flatter their authors by a superficial
semblance of wit. Take, for instance, the exclamation
from the scholastic theme, where a man, after being
ruined by the barrenness of his land, is shipwrecked and hangs himself:
                    <quote>Let him whom neither earth nor sea receives, hang in mid air.</quote>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    A
similar absurdity is to be found in the declamation,
to which I have already referred, in which a father
poisons his son who insists on tearing his flesh with
his teeth:
                    <quote>The man who eats such flesh, deserves such drink.</quote>
                    Or again, take this passage from the
theme of the luxurious man who is alleged to have
pretended to starve himself to death:
                    <quote>
                        Tie a noose
                        <pb xml:id="p.295"/>
                        for yourself: you have good reason to be angry with
your throat. 'rake poison: it is fit that a luxurious
man should die of drink!
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    Others are merely
fatuous, such as the remark of the declaimer who
urges the courtiers of Alexander to provide him with
a tomb by burning down Babylon.
                    <quote>I am burying Alexander. Shall any man watch such a burial from his housetop?</quote>
                    As if this were the climax of
indignities! Others fail from sheer extravagance.
For example, I once heard a rhetorician who was
declaiming about the Germans, say:
                    <quote>I know not where they carry their heads,</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Is this a suggestion that the Germans are monsters
                        <quote>whose heads do grow beneath their shoulders</quote>
                        or that
they are so tall that their heads are lost in the clouds?
                    </note>
                    and again when
belauding a hero,
                    <quote>He beats back whole wars with the boss of his shield.</quote>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    However, I shall never
come to an end if I try to describe every possible
form of this kind of absurdity. I will therefore turn
to discuss a point of more importance.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Rhetoricians are divided in opinion on this subject:
some devote practically all their efforts to the
elaboration of
                    <hi rend="italic">reflexions,</hi>
                    while others condemn their
employment altogether. I cannot agree entirely
with either view.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    If they are crowded too thick
together, such
                    <hi rend="italic">reflexions</hi>
                    merely stand in each other's
way, just as in the case of crops and the fruits of
trees lack of room to grow results in a stunted
development. Again in pictures a definite outline
is required to throw objects into relief, and consequently artists who include a number of objects in
the same design separate them by intervals sufficient
to prevent one casting a shadow on the other.
Further,
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    this form of display breaks up our speeches
into a number of detached sentences; every
                    <hi rend="italic">reflexion</hi>
                    is isolated, and consequently a fresh start is necessary
after each. This produces a discontinuous style, since
                    <pb xml:id="p.297"/>
                    our language is composed not of a system of limbs,
but of a series of fragments: for your nicely rounded
and polished phrases are incapable of cohesion.
Further, the colour,
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    though bright enough, has no
unity, but consists of a number of variegated splashes.
A purple stripe appropriately applied lends brilliance
to a dress, but a dress decorated with a quantity of
patches can never be becoming to anybody.
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    Wherefore, although these ornaments may seem to stand
out with a certain glitter of their own, they are
rather to be compared to sparks flashing through
the smoke than to the actual brilliance of flame:
they are, in fact, invisible when the language is of
uniform splendour, just as the stars are invisible in
the light of day. And where eloquence seeks to
secure elevation by frequent small efforts, it merely
produces an uneven and broken surface which fails
to win the admiration due to outstanding objects
and lacks the charm that may be found in a smooth
surface.
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    To this must be added the fact that those
who devote themselves solely to the production of
                    <hi rend="italic">reflexions</hi>
                    cannot avoid giving utterance to many that
are trivial, flat or foolish. For their mere number
will so embarrass their author that selection will be
impossible. Consequently you will often find that
such persons will produce a
                    <hi rend="italic">division</hi>
                    or an
                    <hi rend="italic">argument</hi>
                    as
if it were an epigram, the only qualification necessary
being that it should come toward the close of the
period and be impressively delivered.
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        You killed
your wife, though you were an adulterer yourself. I
should loathe you even if you had only divorced her.
                    </quote>
                    Here we have a division.
                    <quote>
                        Do you wish me to prove
that a love-philtre is a poison? The man would still
be living, if he had not drunk it.
                    </quote>
                    This is an
                    <pb xml:id="p.299"/>
                    argument. There are, moreover, a number of speakers
who not merely deliver many such epigrams, but
utter everything as if it were an epigram.
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    Against
these persons, on the other hand, must be set those
who shun and dread all ornament of this kind, approving nothing that is not plain, humble and effortless,
with the result that by their reluctance to climb for
fear of falling they succeed merely in maintaining a
perpetual flatness. What sin is there in a good
epigram? Does it not help our case, or move the
judge, or commend the speaker to his audience?
It may be urged, perhaps,
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    that it is a form of
ornament eschewed by the ancients. What do you
mean by antiquity? If you go back to the earliest
periods you will find that Demosthenes frequently
employed methods that were known to none before
him. How can we give our approval to Cicero, if we
think that no change should be made from the
methods of Cato and the Gracchi? And yet before
the Gracchi and Cato the style of oratory was simpler
still.
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    For my own part I regard these particular
ornaments of oratory to be, as it were, the eyes of
eloquence. On the other hand, I should not like to
see the whole body full of eyes, for fear that it might
cripple the functions of the other members, and, if I
had no alternative, I should prefer the rudeness of
ancient eloquence to the license of the moderns.
But a middle course is open to us here no less than
in the refinements of dress and mode of life, where
there is a certain tasteful elegance that offends no
one. Therefore let us as far as possible seek to increase the number of our virtues, although our first
care must always be to keep ourselves free from
vices, lest in seeking to make ourselves better than
                    <pb xml:id="p.301"/>
                    the ancients we succeed merely in making ourselves
unlike them.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    I will now proceed to the next subject for discussion, which is, as I have said, that of
                    <hi rend="italic">tropes,</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italic">modes,</hi>
                    as the most distinguished Roman rhetoricians call
them. Rules for their use are given by the teachers
of literature as well. But I postponed the discussion
of the subject when I was dealing with literary
education, because it seemed to me that the theme
would have greater importance if handled in connexion with the ornaments of oratory, and that it
ought to be reserved for treatment on a larger scale.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    By a
                    <hi rend="italic">trope</hi>
                    is meant the artistic alteration of
a word or phrase from its proper meaning to another.
This is a subject which has given rise to interminable disputes among the teachers of literature, who
have quarrelled no less violently with the philosophers than among themselves over the problem of
the
                    <hi rend="italic">genera</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">species</hi>
                    into which
                    <hi rend="italic">tropes</hi>
                    may be
divided, their number and their correct classification.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    I propose to disregard such quibbles as in no wise
concern the training of an orator, and to proceed
to discuss those
                    <hi rend="italic">tropes</hi>
                    which are most necessary and
meet with most general acceptance, contenting
myself merely with noting the fact that some
                    <hi rend="italic">tropes</hi>
                    are employed to help out our meaning and others to
adorn our style, that some arise from words used
                    <hi rend="italic">properly</hi>
                    and others from words used
                    <hi rend="italic">metaphorically,</hi>
                    and that the changes involved concern not merely
individual words, but also our thoughts and the
structure of our sentences.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    In view of these facts
I regard those writers as mistaken who have held
that
                    <hi rend="italic">tropes</hi>
                    necessarily involved the substitution of
word for word. And I do not ignore the fact that
                    <pb xml:id="p.303"/>
                    as a rule the
                    <hi rend="italic">tropes</hi>
                    employed to express our meaning
involve ornament as well, though the converse is not
the case, since there are some which are intended
solely for the purpose of embellishment.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Let us begin, then, with the commonest and by far
the most beautiful of
                    <hi rend="italic">tropes,</hi>
                    namely,
                    <hi rend="italic">metaphor,</hi>
                    the
Greek term for our
                    <hi rend="italic">translatio.</hi>
                    It is not merely so
natural a turn of speech that it is often employed unconsciously or by uneducated persons, but it is in itself
so attractive and elegant that however distinguished
the language in which it is embedded it shines forth
with a light that is all its own.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    For if it be correctly
and appropriately applied, it is quite impossible
for its effect to be commonplace, mean or unpleasing. It adds to the copiousness of language by the
interchange of words and by borrowing, and finally
succeeds in accomplishing the supremely difficult
task of providing a name for everything. A noun
or a verb is transferred from the place to which it
properly belongs to another where there is either no
                    <hi rend="italic">literal</hi>
                    term or the
                    <hi rend="italic">transferred</hi>
                    is better than the
                    <hi rend="italic">literal.</hi>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    We do this either because it is necessary or to make
our meaning clearer or, as I have already said, to produce a decorative effect. When it secures none of
these results, our metaphor will be out of place. As
an example of a necessary metaphor I may quote the
following usages in vogue with peasants when they
call a vinebud
                    <hi rend="italic">gemma,</hi>
                    a gem (what other term is
there which they could use?), or speak of the
                    <hi rend="italic">crops being thirsty</hi>
                    or the
                    <hi rend="italic">fruit suffering.</hi>
                    For the same
reason we speak of a
                    <hi rend="italic">hard</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italic">rough</hi>
                    man, there being
no
                    <hi rend="italic">literal</hi>
                    term for these temperaments.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    On the
other hand, when we say that a man is
                    <hi rend="italic">kindled to anger</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italic">on fire with greed</hi>
                    or that he has
                    <hi rend="italic">fallen into</hi>
                    <pb xml:id="p.305"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">error,</hi>
                    we do so to enhance our meaning. For none
of these things can be more literally described in its
own words than in those which we import from
elsewhere. But it is a purely ornamental metaphor
when we speak of
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        brilliance of style, splendour of
birth, tempestuous public assemblies, thunderbolts of
eloquence,
                    </hi>
                    to which I may add the phrase employed
by Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Mil.</hi>
                        xiii. 34, 35.
                    </note>
                    in his defence of Milo where he speaks
of Clodius as the
                    <hi rend="italic">fountain,</hi>
                    and in another place as
                    <hi rend="italic">the fertile field and material</hi>
                    of his client's
                    <hi rend="italic">glory.</hi>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    It
is even possible to express facts of a somewhat
unseemly character by a judicious use of metaphor,
as in the following passage:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Virg.
                        <hi rend="italic">Georg.</hi>
                        iii. 1
                    </note>
                </p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <quote>
                        <l part="N">This do they lest too much indulgence make</l>
                        <l part="N">The field of generation slothful grow</l>
                        <l part="F">And choke its idle furrows.</l>
                    </quote>
                </quote>
                <p>
                    On the whole
                    <hi rend="italic">metaphor</hi>
                    is a shorter form of
                    <hi rend="italic">simile,</hi>
                    while there is this further difference, that in the
latter we compare some object to the thing which we
wish to describe, whereas in the former this object is
actually substituted for the thing.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    It is a comparison when I say that a man did something
                    <hi rend="italic">like a lion,</hi>
                    it is a metaphor when I say of him,
                    <hi rend="italic">He is a lion.</hi>
                    Metaphors fall into four classes. In the first we
substitute one living thing for another, as in the
passage where the poet, speaking of a charioteer,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Probably from Ennius.</note>
                    says,
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="I">The steersman then</l>
                            <l part="N">With mighty effort wrenched his charger round.</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    or when Livy
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Liv. XXXVIII. liv.</note>
                    says that Scipio was continually
                    <hi rend="italic">barked at</hi>
                    by Cato.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Secondly, inanimate things may
be substituted for inanimate, as in the Virgilian.
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">And gave his fleet the rein,</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                vi. 1.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    <pb xml:id="p.307"/>
                    or inanimate may be substituted for animate, as in
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Did the Argive bulwark fall by sword or fate?</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">From an unknown tragedian.</bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    or animate for inanimate, as in the following lines:
                </p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">The shepherd sits unknowing on the height</l>
                            <l part="N">
                                Listening the roar from some far mountain
                                <lb/>
                                brow.
                            </l>
                        </quote>
                        <bibl default="false">
                            <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                            ii. 307.
                        </bibl>
                    </cit>
                </quote>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    But, above all, effects of extraordinary sublimity are
produced when the theme is exalted by a bold and
almost hazardous metaphor and inanimate objects
are given life and action, as in the phrase
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Araxes' flood that scorns a bridge,</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                viii. 728.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    or in the passage of Cicero,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Lit.</hi>
                        iii. 9. See VIII. iv. 27.
                    </note>
                    already quoted,
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    where
he cries,
                    <quote>
                        What was that sword of yours doing,
Tubero, the sword you drew on the field of
Pharsalus? Against whose body did you aim its
point? What meant those arms you bore?
                    </quote>
                    Sometimes the effect is doubled, as in Virgil's.
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">And with venom arm the steel.</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                ix. 773.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    For both
                    <quote>to arm the steel</quote>
                    and
                    <quote>to arm with venom</quote>
                    are metaphors.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    These four kinds of
metaphor are further subdivided into a number of
                    <hi rend="italic">species,</hi>
                    such as transference from rational beings
to rational and from irrational to irrational and the
reverse, in which the method is the same, and
finally from the whole to its parts and from the
parts to the whole. But I am not now teaching
boys: my readers are old enough to discover the
                    <hi rend="italic">species</hi>
                    for themselves when once they have been
given the
                    <hi rend="italic">genus.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    While a temperate and timely use of metaphor is
                    <pb xml:id="p.309"/>
                    a real adornment to style, on the other hand, its
frequent use serves merely to obscure our language
and weary our audience, while if we introduce them
in one continuous series, our language will become
allegorical and enigmatic. There are also certain
metaphors which fail from meanness, such as that
of which I spoke above
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See VIII. iii. 48.</note>
                    :
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">There is a rocky wart upon the mountain's</l>
                            <l part="N">brow.</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    or they may even be coarse. For it does not
follow that because Cicero was perfectly justified
in talking of
                    <quote>the sink of the state,</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        In
                        <hi rend="italic">Cat.</hi>
                        I. v. 12.
                    </note>
                    when
he desired to indicate the foulness of certain
men, we can approve the following passage from
an ancient orator:
                    <quote>You have lanced the boils of the state.</quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Indeed Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">De Or.</hi>
                        iii. xli. 164.
                    </note>
                    himself has demonstrated in the most admirable manner how important it is to avoid grossness in metaphor, such
as is revealed by the following examples, which he
quotes:—
                    <quote>The state was gelded by the death of Africanus,</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>Glaucia, the excrement of the senate-house.</quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    He also points out that a metaphor
must not be too great for its subject or, as is more
frequently the case, too little, and that it must not
be inappropriate. Anyone who realises that these
are faults, will be able to detect instances of them
only too frequently. But excess in the use of metaphor is also a fault, more especially if they are of the
same species.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    Metaphors may also be harsh, that is,
far-fetched, as in phrases like
                    <quote>the snows of the head</quote>
                    or
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Jove with white snow the wintry Alps bespewed.</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                From Furius, an old epic poet of the second century
(not Furius Bibaculus),
                                <hi rend="italic">cp.</hi>
                                Hor. S. ii. v. 11.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    <pb xml:id="p.311"/>
                    The worst errors of all, however, originate in the
fact that some authors regard it as permissible to
use even in prose any metaphors that are allowed to
poets, in spite of the fact that tile latter aim solely
at pleasing their readers and are compelled in many
cases to employ metaphor by sheer metrical necessity.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    For my own part I should not regard a phrase
like
                    <quote>the shepherd of the people</quote>
                    as admissible in
pleading, although it has the authority of Homer,
nor would I venture to say that winged creatures
                    <quote>swim through the air,</quote>
                    despite the fact that this
metaphor has been most effectively employed by
Virgil to describe the flight of bees and of Daedalus.1 For metaphor should always either occupy
a place already vacant, or if it fills the room of something else, should be more impressive than that
which it displaces.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    What I have said above applies perhaps with even
greater force to
                    <hi rend="italic">synecdocheè.</hi>
                    For while
                    <hi rend="italic">metaphor</hi>
                    is
designed to move the feelings, give special distinction to things and place them vividly before
the eye,
                    <hi rend="italic">synecdocheè</hi>
                    has the power to give variety to
our language by making us realise many things
from one, the whole from a part, the
                    <hi rend="italic">genus</hi>
                    from a
                    <hi rend="italic">species,</hi>
                    things which follow from things which have
preceded; or, on the other hand, the whole procedure may be reversed. It may, however, be more
freely employed by poets than by orators.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    For
while in prose it is perfectly correct to use
                    <hi rend="italic">macro,</hi>
                    the point, for the whole sword, and
                    <hi rend="italic">tectum,</hi>
                    roof, for a
whole house, we may not employ
                    <hi rend="italic">puppis,</hi>
                    stern, to
describe a ship, nor
                    <hi rend="italic">abies,</hi>
                    fir, to describe planks;
and again, though
                    <hi rend="italic">ferrunm,</hi>
                    the steel, may be used to
indicate a sword,
                    <hi rend="italic">quadrupes</hi>
                    cannot be used in the
                    <pb xml:id="p.313"/>
                    sense of horse. It is where numbers are concerned
that
                    <hi rend="italic">synecdocheè</hi>
                    can be most freely employed in
prose. For example, Livy frequently says,
                    <quote>The Roman won the day,</quote>
                    when he means that the
                    <hi rend="italic">Romans</hi>
                    were victorious; on the other hand, Cicero
in a letter to Brutus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">This letter is lost.</note>
                    says,
                    <quote>We have imposed on the people and are regarded as orators,</quote>
                    when he is
speaking of himself alone.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    This form of
                    <hi rend="italic">trope</hi>
                    is
not only a rhetorical ornament, but is frequently
employed in everyday speech. Some also apply the
term
                    <hi rend="italic">synecdoche</hi>
                    when something is assumed which
has not actually been expressed, since one word is
then discovered from other words, as in the sentence,
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">The Arcadians to the gates began to rush;</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                xi. 142. A false explanation of the historic infinitive as involving the omission of some such word as
                                <hi rend="italic">coeperunt.</hi>
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    when such omission creates a blemish, it is called an
                    <hi rend="italic">ellipse.</hi>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    For my own part, I prefer to regard this as
a figure, and shall therefore discuss it under that
head. Again, one thing may be suggested by
another, as in the line,
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Behold, the steers</l>
                                <l part="N">
                                    Bring back the plough suspended from the
                                    <lb/>
                                    yoke,
                                </l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ed.</hi>
                                ii. 61
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    from which we infer the approach of night. I am
not sure whether this is permissible to an orator
except in arguments, when it serves as an indication
of some fact. However, this has nothing to do with
the question of style.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    It is but a short step from
                    <hi rend="italic">synecdocheè</hi>
                    to
                    <hi rend="italic">metonymy,</hi>
                    which consists in the substitution of one name for
another, and, as Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Orat.</hi>
                        xxvii. 93.
                    </note>
                    tells us, is called
                    <hi rend="italic">hypallage</hi>
                    by the rhetoricians. These devices are employed to
indicate an invention by substituting the name of
                    <pb xml:id="p.315"/>
                    the inventor, or a possession by substituting the
name of the possessor. Virgil, for example, writes:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                        i. 177.
                    </note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">Ceres by water spoiled,</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    and Horace:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Neptune admitted to the land</l>
                                <l part="N">Protects the fleets from blasts of Aquilo.</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">A. P.</hi>
                                63.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    If, however, the process is reversed, the effect is
harsh.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    But it is important to enquire to what
extent
                    <hi rend="italic">tropes</hi>
                    of this kind should be employed by
the orator. For though we often hear
                    <quote>Vulcan</quote>
                    used for fire and to say
                    <hi rend="italic">vario Marte pugnatum est</hi>
                    for
                    <quote>they fought with varying success</quote>
                    is elegant and
idiomatic, while
                    <hi rend="italic">Venus</hi>
                    is a more decent expression
than
                    <hi rend="italic">coitus,</hi>
                    it would be too bold for the severe style
demanded in the courts to speak of
                    <hi rend="italic">Liber</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">Ceres</hi>
                    when we mean bread and wine. Again, while usage
permits us to substitute that which contains for that
which is contained, as in phrases such as
                    <quote>civilised cities,</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>a cup was drunk to the lees,</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>a happy age,</quote>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    the converse procedure would rarely be
ventured on by any save a poet: take, for example,
the phrase:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Ucalegon burns next.</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                ii. 311.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    It is, however, perhaps more permissible to describe
what is possessed by reference to its possessor, as,
for example, to say of a man whose estate is being
squandered,
                    <quote>the man is being eaten up.</quote>
                    Of this
form there are innumerable species.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    For example,
we say
                    <quote>sixty thousand men were slain by Hannibal at Cannae,</quote>
                    and speak of
                    <quote>Virgil</quote>
                    when we mean
                    <quote>Virgil's poems</quote>
                    ; again, we say that supplies have
                    <pb xml:id="p.317"/>
                    <quote>come,</quote>
                    when they have been
                    <quote>brought,</quote>
                    that a
                    <quote>sacrilege,</quote>
                    and not a
                    <quote>sacrilegious man</quote>
                    has been
detected, and that a man possesses a knowledge of
                    <quote>arms,</quote>
                    not of
                    <quote>the art of arms.</quote>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    The type which
indicates cause by effect is common both in poets
and orators. As examples from poetry I may quote:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Pale death with equal foot knocks at the poor man's door</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                Hor.
                                <hi rend="italic">Od.</hi>
                                I. iv. 13.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    and
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">There pale diseases dwell and sad old age;</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                vi. 275
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">
                            while the orator will speak of
                            <quote>headlong anger</quote>
                            ,
                        </l>
                        <l part="N">
                            <quote>cheerful youth</quote>
                            or
                            <quote>slothful ease</quote>
                            .
                        </l>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    The following type of
                    <hi rend="italic">trope</hi>
                    has also some kinship
with
                    <hi rend="italic">synecdochè.</hi>
                    For when I speak of a man's
                    <quote>looks</quote>
                    instead of his
                    <quote>look,</quote>
                    I use the plural for
the singular, but my aim is not to enable one thing
to be inferred from many (for the sense is clear
enough), but I merely vary the form of the word.
Again, when I call a
                    <quote>gilded roof</quote>
                    a
                    <quote>golden roof,</quote>
                    I diverge a little from the truth, because gilding
forms only a part of the roof. But to follow out
these points is a task involving too much minute
detail even for a work whose aim is not the
training of an orator.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Antonomasia,</hi>
                    which substitutes something else for
a proper name, is very common in poets: it may be
done in two ways: by the substitution of an epithet
as equivalent to the name which it replaces, such as
                    <quote>Tydides,</quote>
                    <quote>Pelides,</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The son of Tydeus=Diomede, the son of Peleus = Achilles.</note>
                    or by indicating the most
striking characteristics of an individual, as in the
phrase
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Father of gods and king of men,</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                i. 65.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    <pb xml:id="p.319"/>
                    or from acts clearly indicating the individual, as in
the phrase,
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">The arms which he, the traitor, left</l>
                                <l part="N">Fixed on the chamber wall.</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                iv. 495. This third example does not correspond
with the twofold division given by
                                <hi rend="italic">utroque</hi>
                                and may be
spurious.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    This form of
                    <hi rend="italic">trope</hi>
                    is rare in oratory,
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    but is occasionally employed, For although an orator would
not say
                    <quote>Tydides</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>Pelides,</quote>
                    he will speak of
certain definite persons as
                    <quote>the impious parricides,</quote>
                    while I should have no hesitation in speaking of
Scipio as
                    <quote>the destroyer of Carthage and Numantia,</quote>
                    or of Cicero as
                    <quote>the prince of Roman orators.</quote>
                    Cicero himself, at any rate, availed himself of this
licence, as, for example, in the following case:
                    <quote>Your faults are not many, said the old praeceptor to the hero,</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Muren.</hi>
                        xxix. 60. The passage continues (a quotation
from some old play)
                        <quote>But you have faults and I can correct them.</quote>
                        Phoenix is addressing his pupil Achilles.
                    </note>
                    where neither name is given, though both
are clearly understood.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand,
                    <hi rend="italic">onomatopoea,</hi>
                    that is to say, the
creation of a word, although regarded with the
highest approbation by the Greeks, is scarcely permissible to a Roman. It is true that many words
were created in this way by the original founders of
the language, who adapted them to suit the sensation
which they expressed. For instance,
                    <hi rend="italic">mugitus,</hi>
                    lowing,
                    <hi rend="italic">sibilus,</hi>
                    a hiss, and
                    <hi rend="italic">murmur</hi>
                    owe their origin to this
practice.
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    But to-day we consider that all has been
done that can be done in this line, and do not venture
on fresh creations, in spite of the fact that many
of the words thus formed in antiquity are daily
becoming obsolete. Indeed, we scarcely permit ourselves to use new derivatives, so they are called,
which are formed in various ways from words in
common use, such as
                    <hi rend="italic">Sullaturit,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Cic.
                        <hi rend="italic">ad Att.</hi>
                        IX. x. 6.
                    </note>
                    <quote>he wishes to be a second Sulla,</quote>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italic">proscripturit,</hi>
                    <quote>
                        he wishes to have
                        <pb xml:id="p.321"/>
                        a proscription,
                    </quote>
                    while
                    <hi rend="italic">laureati posies,</hi>
                    <quote>laurelled door-posts,</quote>
                    for
                    <hi rend="italic">lauru coronati,</hi>
                    <quote>crowned with laurel,</quote>
                    are similar formations.
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    * * * * * *
* * * * * * * * *
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        This passage is too corrupt to admit of emendation or
translation. There seem to be references to
                        <hi rend="italic">vio</hi>
                        for
                        <hi rend="italic">eo</hi>
                        and to
                        <hi rend="italic">arqtitollens.</hi>
                        for which cp.
                        <hi rend="italic">arquitenens.</hi>
                        Septemntriones can
hardly be selected for censure, as it is not uncommon.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    These facts make
                    <hi rend="italic">catachresis</hi>
                    (of which
                    <hi rend="italic">abuse</hi>
                    is a
correct translation) all the more necessary. By this
term is meant the practice of adapting the nearest
available term to describe something for which no
actual term exists, as in the line
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">A horse they build by Pallas' art divine,</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                II. xv. It is an abuse to say
                                <hi rend="italic">aedficant,</hi>
                                which means
literally "they make a house.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    or as in the expression found in tragedy,
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">To Aigialeus</l>
                            <l part="N">His sire bears funeral offerings,</l>
                        </quote>
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                            Perhaps from the Medus of Pacuvius It is an abuse to
use
                            <hi rend="italic">parental</hi>
                            of funeral offerings made by father to son.
                        </note>
                    </quote>
                    The following examples are of a similar character.
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    Flasks are called
                    <hi rend="italic">acetabula,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Lit. vinegar flasks.</note>
                    whatever they contain,
and caskets
                    <hi rend="italic">pyxides,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>
                        made of boxwood.
                    </note>
                    of whatever material they are
made, while
                    <hi rend="italic">parricide</hi>
                    includes the murder of a
mother or a brother. We must be careful to
distinguish between
                    <hi rend="italic">abuse</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">metaphor,</hi>
                    since the
former is employed where there is no proper term
available, and the latter when there is another term
available. As for poets, they indulge in the abuse
of words even in cases where proper terms do exist,
and substitute words of somewhat similar meaning.
But this is rare in prose.
                    <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                    Some, indeed, would give
the name of
                    <hi rend="italic">catachresis</hi>
                    even to cases such as where
we call temerity valour or prodigality liberality.
I, however, cannot agree with them; for in these
                    <pb xml:id="p.323"/>
                    instances word is not substituted for word, but thing
for thing, since no one regards prodigality and liberality as meaning the same, but one man calls certain
actions liberal and another prodigal, although neither
for a moment doubts the difference between the two
qualities.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                    There is but one of the
                    <hi rend="italic">tropes</hi>
                    involving change of
meaning which remains to be discussed, namely,
                    <hi rend="italic">metalepsis</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italic">transumption,</hi>
                    which provides a transition
from one
                    <hi rend="italic">trope</hi>
                    to another. It is (if we except
comedy) but rarely used in Latin, and is by no means
to be commended, though it is not infrequently
employed by the Greeks, who, for example, call
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">*xei/rwn</foreign>
                    the centaur
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">*(/hsswn</foreign>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">*xei/rwn</foreign>
                        and
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">h(/sswn</foreign>
                        both mean inferior.
                    </note>
                    and substitute the epithet
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">qoai/</foreign>
                    (swift) for
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">o)/ceiai</foreign>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">cp. Od.</hi>
                        xv. 298.
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">*qoo/s</foreign>
                        is used elsewhere to express
sharpness.
                    </note>
                    in referring to sharp-pointed
islands. But who would endure a Roman if he
called Verres
                    <hi rend="italic">sus</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Verres =boar; Catus=wise.</note>
                    or changed the name of Aelius
Catus to Aelius
                    <hi rend="italic">doctus?</hi>
                    <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                    It is the nature of
                    <hi rend="italic">metalepsis</hi>
                    to form a kind of intermediate step between the
term transferred and the thing to which it is transferred, having no meaning in itself, but merely
providing a transition. It is a
                    <hi rend="italic">trope</hi>
                    with which to
claim acquaintance, rather than one which we are
ever likely to require to use. The commonest
example is the following:
                    <hi rend="italic">cano</hi>
                    is a synonym
for
                    <hi rend="italic">canto</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">canto</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">In the sense of to repeat.</note>
                    for
                    <hi rend="italic">dico,</hi>
                    therefore
                    <hi rend="italic">cano</hi>
                    is a
synonym for
                    <hi rend="italic">dico,</hi>
                    the intermediate step being provided by
                    <hi rend="italic">canto.</hi>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
                    We need not waste any more time
over it. I can see no use in it except, as I have
already said, in comedy.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
                    The remaining
                    <hi rend="italic">tropes</hi>
                    are employed solely to
adorn and enhance our style without any reference
to the meaning. For the
                    <hi rend="italic">epithet,</hi>
                    of which the correct
translation is
                    <hi rend="italic">appositum,</hi>
                    though some call it
                    <hi rend="italic">sequens,</hi>
                    <pb xml:id="p.325"/>
                    is clearly an ornament. Poets employ it with special
frequency and freedom, since for them it is sufficient
that the epithet should suit the word to which it is
applied: consequently we shall not blame them
when they speak of
                    <quote>white teeth</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>liquid wine.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Georg.</hi>
                        III. 364.
                    </note>
                    But in oratory an epithet is redundant
unless it has some point. Now it will only have
point when it adds something to the meaning, as for
instance in the following:
                    <quote>O abominable crime, O hideous lust!</quote>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>
                    But its decorative effect is greatest
when it is metaphorical, as in the phrases
                    <quote>unbridled greed</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Cic. in
                        <hi rend="italic">Cat.</hi>
                        I. x. 25.
                    </note>
                    or
                    <quote>those mad piles of masonry.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic"> Pro Mil.</hi>
                        xx. 53.
                    </note>
                    The
epithet is generally made into a
                    <hi rend="italic">trope</hi>
                    by the addition
of something to it, as when Virgil speaks of
                    <quote>disgraceful poverty</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>sad old age.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                        vi. 276 and 275. Here the addition is
                        <hi rend="italic">metonymy, turpis</hi>
                        and
                        <hi rend="italic">tristis</hi>
                        both substituting
                        <hi rend="italic">effect</hi>
                        in place of
                        <hi rend="italic">cause: cp.</hi>
                        § 27.
                    </note>
                    But the nature
of this form of embellishment is such that, while
style is bare and inelegant without any epithets
at all, it is overloaded when a large number are
employed.
                    <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>
                    For then it becomes long-winded and
cumbrous, in fact you might compare it to an army
with as many camp-followers as soldiers, an army, that
is to say, which has doubled its numbers without
doubling its strength. None the less, not merely
single epithets are employed, but we may find a
number of them together, as in the following passage
from Virgil:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                        iii. 475. I have translated 476 (
                        <hi rend="italic">cura deum, bis Pergameis erepte ruinis</hi>
                        ) as well to bring out Quintilian's meaning. Quintilian assumes the rest of quotation to be known.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <quote>
                        <l part="F">Anchises, worthy deigned</l>
                        <l part="N">Of Venus' glorious bed, [beloved of heaven,</l>
                        <l part="N">Twice rescued from the wreck of Pergamum.]</l>
                    </quote>
                </quote>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
                    Be this as it may, two epithets directly attached
to one noun are unbecoming even in verse. There
are some writers who refuse to regard an
                    <hi rend="italic">epithet</hi>
                    as a
                    <hi rend="italic">trope,</hi>
                    on the ground that it involves no change. It
                    <pb xml:id="p.327"/>
                    is not always a
                    <hi rend="italic">trope,</hi>
                    but if separated from the word to
which it belongs, it has a significance of its own and
forms an
                    <hi rend="italic">antonomasia.</hi>
                    For if you say,
                    <quote>The man who destroyed Numantia and Carthage,</quote>
                    it will
be an
                    <hi rend="italic">antonomasia,</hi>
                    whereas, if you add the word
                    <quote>Scipio,</quote>
                    the phrase will be an
                    <hi rend="italic">epithet.</hi>
                    An epithet
therefore cannot stand by itself.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="44 " unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Allegory,</hi>
                    which is translated in Latin by
                    <hi rend="italic">inversio,</hi>
                    either presents one thing in words and another in
meaning, or else something absolutely opposed to the
meaning of the words. The first type is generally produced by a series of metaphors. Take as an example:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">O ship, new waves will bear thee back to sea.</l>
                                <l part="N">What dost thou? Make the haven, come what may,</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">Hor. Od. i. xiv. 1.</bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    and the rest of the ode, in which Horace represents
the state under the semblance of a ship, the civil
wars as tempests, and peace and good-will as the
haven.
                    <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>
                    Such, again, is the claim of Lucretius:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lucr.</hi>
                        IV. 1.
                    </note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">Pierian fields I range untrod by man,</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    and such again the passage where Virgil says,
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">But now</l>
                                <l part="N">A mighty length of plain we have travelled o'er;</l>
                                <l part="N">'Tis time to loose our horses' steaming necks.</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">Georg. II. 541.</bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="46" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, in the Bucolics
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Buc.</hi>
                        IX. 7.
                    </note>
                    he introduces
an allegory without any metaphor:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">Truth, I had heard</l>
                            <l part="N">Your loved Menalcas by his songs had saved</l>
                            <l part="N">All those fair acres, where the hills begin</l>
                            <l part="N">To sink and droop their ridge with easy slope</l>
                            <l part="N">Down to the waterside and that old beech</l>
                            <l part="N">With splintered crest.</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb xml:id="p.329"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="47" unit="section"/>
                    For in this passage, with the exception of the
proper name, the words bear no more than their
literal meaning. But the name does not simply denote the shepherd Menalcas, but is a pseudonym for
Virgil himself. Oratory makes frequent use of such
allegory, but generally with this modification, that
there is an admixture of plain speaking. We get
allegory pure and unadulterated in the following
passage of Cicero:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">From an unknown speech.</note>
                    <quote>
                        What I marvel at and complain
of is this, that there should exist any man so set on
destroying his enemy as to scuttle the ship on which
he himself is sailing.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="48" unit="section"/>
                    The following is an example
of the commonest type, namely, the mixed allegory:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Mil.</hi>
                        ii, 5.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        I always thought that Milo would have other storms
and tempests to weather, at least in the troubled
waters of political meetings.
                    </quote>
                    Had he not added
the words
                    <quote>at least in the troubled waters of political meetings,</quote>
                    we should have had pure allegory:
their addition, however, converted it into a mixed
allegory. In this type of allegory the ornamental
element is provided by the metaphorical words and
the meaning is indicated by those which are used
literally.
                    <milestone n="49" unit="section"/>
                    But far the most ornamental effect is produced by the artistic admixture of simile, metaphor
and allegory, as in the following example:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Mur.</hi>
                        xvii. 35.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        What
strait, what tide-race, think you, is full of so many
conflicting motions or vexed by such a variety of
eddies, waves and fluctuations, as confuse our popular
elections with their wild ebb and flow? The passing
of one day, or the interval of a single night, will
often throw everything into confusion, and one little
breath of rumour will sometimes turn the whole
trend of opinion.
                        <milestone n="50" unit="section"/>
                    </quote>
                    For it is all-important to follow
the principle illustrated by this passage and never to
                    <pb xml:id="p.331"/>
                    mix your metaphors. But there are many who, after
beginning with a tempest, will end with a fire or a
falling house, with the result that they produce a
hideously incongruous effect.
                    <milestone n="51" unit="section"/>
                    For the rest, allegory
is often used by men of little ability and in the
conversation of everyday life. For those hackneyed
phrases of forensic pleading,
                    <quote>to fight hand to hand,</quote>
                    <quote>to attack the throat,</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>to let blood</quote>
                    are all of
them allegorical, although they do not strike the
attention: for it is novelty and change that please
in oratory, and what is unexpected always gives special
delight. Consequently we have thrown all restraint
to the wind in such matters, and have destroyed the
charm of language by the extravagant efforts which
we have made to attain it.
                    <milestone n="52" unit="section"/>
                    Illustrative examples also
involve allegory if not preceded by an explanation;
for there are numbers of sayings available for use like
the
                    <quote>Dionysius is at Corinth,</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The allusion must be to the fact that Dionysius II,
tyrant of Syracuse, on his expulsion from the throne,
migrated to Corinth and set up as a schoolmaster. Its
application is uncertain, but it would obviously be a way of
saying
                        <quote>How are the mighty fallen I</quote>
                    </note>
                    which is such a
favourite with the Greeks. When, however, an allegory
is too obscure, we call it a riddle: such riddles are,
in my opinion, to be regarded as blemishes, in view of
the fact that lucidity is a virtue; nevertheless they
are used by poets, as, for example, by Virgil
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ecl.</hi>
                        iii. 104; the solution is lost.
                    </note>
                    in the
following lines:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">Say in what land, and if thou tell me true,</l>
                            <l part="N">I'll hold thee as Apollo's oracle,</l>
                            <l part="N">Three ells will measure all the arch of heaven.</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    Even orators sometimes use them,
                    <milestone n="53" unit="section"/>
                    as when Caelius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The references are to the licentious character of Clodia.
                        <hi rend="italic">Coa</hi>
                        was probably intended to suggest
                        <hi rend="italic">coitus,</hi>
                        while
                        <hi rend="italic">nola</hi>
                        is best
derived from
                        <hi rend="italic">nolle,</hi>
                        and is to be regarded as the opposite of
                        <hi rend="italic">coa.</hi>
                    </note>
                    speaks of the
                    <quote>
                        Clytemnestra who sold her favours
for a farthing, who was a Coan in the dining-room
and a Nolan in her bedroom.
                    </quote>
                    For although we
know the answers, and although they were better
known at the time when the words were uttered,
                    <pb xml:id="p.333"/>
                    they are riddles for all that; and other riddles are,
after all, intelligible if you can get someone to explain
them.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="54" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, that class of allegory in which
the meaning is contrary to that suggested by the
words, involve an element of irony, or, as our
rhetoricians call it,
                    <hi rend="italic">illusio.</hi>
                    This is made evident to
the understanding either by the delivery, the character of the speaker or the nature of the subject.
For if any one of these three is out of keeping with
the words, it at once becomes clear that the intention of the speaker is other than what he actually
says In the majority of
                    <hi rend="italic">tropes</hi>
                    it is, however,
                    <milestone n="55" unit="section"/>
                    important to bear in mind not merely what is said,
but about whom it is said, since what is said may
in another context be literally true. It is permissible to censure with counterfeited praise and
praise under a pretence of blame. The following will
serve as an example of the first.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Cic.
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Cluent.</hi>
                        xxxiii. 91.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        Since Gaius
Verres, the urban praetor, being a man of energy and
blameless character, had no record in his register of
this substitution of this man for another on the panel.
                    </quote>
                    As an example of the reverse process we may take
the following:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">cp. §</hi>
                        20.
                    </note>
                    <quote>We are regarded as orators and have imposed on the people.</quote>
                    <milestone n="56" unit="section"/>
                    Sometimes, again,
we may speak in mockery when we say the opposite
of what we desire to be understood, as in Cicero's
denunciation of Clodius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        From the lost speech
                        <hi rend="italic">in Clodium et Curionem.</hi>
                    </note>
                    :
                    <quote>
                        Believe me, your well known integrity has cleared you of all blame, your
modesty has saved you, your past life has been your
salvation.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="57" unit="section"/>
                    Further, we may employ
                    <hi rend="italic">allegory,</hi>
                    and
disguise bitter taunts in gentle words I y way of wit,
or we may indicate our meaning by saying exactly
the contrary or. . .
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The passage is hopelessly corrupt. The concluding
portion of the sentence must have referred to the use of
proverbs, of which it may have contained an example. This
is clear from the next sentence. Sarcasm, urbane wit and
contradiction are covered by the first three clauses, but there
has been no allusion to proverbs such as
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">paroimi/a</foreign>
                        demands.
                    </note>
                    If the Greek names for these
                    <pb xml:id="p.335"/>
                    methods are unfamiliar to any of my readers, I would
remind him that they are
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">sarkasmo/s, a)stei+smo/s, a)nti/frasis</foreign>
                    and
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">paroimi/a</foreign>
                    (sarcasm, urbane wit, contradiction and proverbs).
                    <milestone n="58" unit="section"/>
                    There are, however, some
writers who deny that these are species of
                    <hi rend="italic">allegory,</hi>
                    and assert that they are actually
                    <hi rend="italic">tropes</hi>
                    in themselves:
for they argue shrewdly that allegory involves an
element of obscurity, whereas in all these cases our
meaning is perfectly obvious. To this may be added
the fact that when a
                    <hi rend="italic">genus</hi>
                    is divided into
                    <hi rend="italic">species,</hi>
                    it
ceases to have any peculiar properties of its own: for
example, we may divide tree into its species, pine,
olive, cypress, etc., leaving it no properties of its own,
whereas allegory always has some property peculiar
to itself. The only explanation of this fact is that
it is itself a species. But this, of course, is a matter
of indifference to those that use it.
                    <milestone n="59" unit="section"/>
                    To these the
Greeks add
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">mukthrismo/s</foreign>
                    or mockery under the
thinnest of disguises.
                </p>
                <p>
                    When we use a number of words to describe something for which one, or at any rate only a few words
of description would suffice, it is called
                    <hi rend="italic">periphrasis,</hi>
                    that is, a circuitous mode of speech. It is sometimes
necessary, being of special service when it conceals
something which would be indecent, if expressed in
so many words: compare the phrase
                    <quote>To meet the demands of nature</quote>
                    from Sallust.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Presumably from the Histories.</note>
                    <milestone n="60" unit="section"/>
                    But at times it
is employed solely for decorative effect, a practice
most frequent among the poets:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="F">Now was the time</l>
                                <l part="N">When the first sleep to weary mortals comes</l>
                                <l part="N">Stealing its way, the sweetest boon of heaven.</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                ii. 268.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="61" unit="section"/>
                    Still it is far from uncommon even in oratory, though
                    <pb xml:id="p.337"/>
                    in such cases it is always used with greater restraint.
For whatever might have been expressed with greater
brevity, but is expanded for purposes of ornament, is
                    <hi rend="italic">a periphrasis,</hi>
                    to which we give the name
                    <hi rend="italic">circumlocution,</hi>
                    though it is a term scarcely suitable to describe one
of the virtues of oratory. But it is only called
                    <hi rend="italic">periphrasis</hi>
                    so long as it produces a decorative effect:
when it passes into excess, it is known as
                    <hi rend="italic">perissology:</hi>
                    for whatever is not a help, is a positive hindrance.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="62" unit="section"/>
                    Again,
                    <hi rend="italic">hyperbaton,</hi>
                    that is, the transposition of a
word, is often demanded by the structure of the
sentence and the claims of elegance, and is consequently counted among the ornaments of style.
For our language would often be harsh, rough, limp
or disjointed, if the words were always arranged in
their natural order and attached each to each just
as they occur, despite the fact that there is no real
bond of union. Consequently some words require
to be postponed, others to be anticipated, each
being set in its appropriate place.
                    <milestone n="63" unit="section"/>
                    For we are like
those who build a wall of unhewn stone: we cannot
hew or polish our words in order to make them fit
more compactly, and so we must take them as they
are and choose suitable positions for them.
                    <milestone n="64" unit="section"/>
                    Further,
it is impossible to make our prose rhythmical except
by artistic alterations in the order of words, and
the reason why those four words in which Plato
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        At the beginning of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Repiblic.</hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">kate/bhn xfe\s ei)s *peiraia=.</foreign>
                    </note>
                    in the noblest of his works states that he had gone
down to the Piraeus were found written in a number
of different orders upon his wax tablets, was simply
that he desired to make the rhythm as perfect as
possible.
                    <milestone n="65" unit="section"/>
                    When, however, the transposition is confined to two words only, it is called
                    <hi rend="italic">anastrophe,</hi>
                    that
is, a reversal of order. This occurs in everyday
                    <pb xml:id="p.339"/>
                    speech in
                    <hi rend="italic">mecum</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">secure,</hi>
                    while in orators and
historians we meet with it in the phrase
                    <hi rend="italic">quibus de rebus.</hi>
                    It is the transposition of a word to some
distance from its original place, in order to secure
an ornamental effect, that is strictly called
                    <hi rend="italic">hyperbaton:</hi>
                    the following passage will provide an example:
animadverti, indices, omnem accusatoris orationenm in duas
                    <hi rend="italic">divisam esse partes.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cic. pro Cluent.</hi>
                        i. 1.
                    </note>
                    (
                    <quote>I noted, gentlemen, that the speech of the accuser was divided into two parts.</quote>
                    )
In this case the strictly correct order would be
                    <hi rend="italic">in duas partes divisam esse,</hi>
                    but this would have been harsh
and ugly.
                    <milestone n="66" unit="section"/>
                    The poets even go so far as to secure
this effect by the division of words, as in the line:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">
                            Hyperboreo septem subiecta trioni
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                                <hi rend="italic">Georg.</hi>
                                iii. 381.
                            </note>
                        </l>
                        <l part="N">
                            (
                            <quote>Under the Hyperborean Wain</quote>
                            ),
                        </l>
                    </quote>
                    a licence wholly inadmissible in oratory. Still there
is good reason for calling such a transposition a
                    <hi rend="italic">trope,</hi>
                    since the meaning is not complete until the two words
have been put together.
                    <milestone n="67" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, when
the transposition makes no alteration in the sense, and
merely produces a variation in the structure, it is rather
to be called a
                    <hi rend="italic">verbal figure,</hi>
                    as indeed many authorities
have held. Of the faults resulting from long or confused
                    <hi rend="italic">hyperbata</hi>
                    have spoken in the appropriate place.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">VIII. ii. 14.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    I have kept
                    <hi rend="italic">hyperbole</hi>
                    to the last, on the ground of
its boldness. It means an elegant straining of the
truth, and may be employed indifferently for exaggeration or attenuation. It can be used in various
ways.
                    <milestone n="68" unit="section"/>
                    We may say more than the actual facts, as
when Cicero says,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Phil.</hi>
                        II. xxv. 63.
                    </note>
                    "He vomited and filled his lap
and the whole tribunal with fragments of food, or
when Virgil speaks of
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">win rocks that threaten heaven.</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                i. 162.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    <pb xml:id="p.341"/>
                    Again, we may exalt our theme by the use of simile,
as in the phrase:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Thou wouldst have deemed</l>
                                <l part="N">That Cyclad isles uprooted swam the deep.</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                viii. 691.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="69" unit="section"/>
                    Or we may produce the same result by introducing
a comparison, as in the phrase:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Swifter than the levin's wings;</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                v. 319.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    or by the use of indications, as in the lines:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">She would fly</l>
                                <l part="N">Even o'er the tops of the unsickled corn,</l>
                                <l part="N">Nor as she ran would bruise the tender ears.</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                vii. 808.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    Or we may employ a metaphor, as the verb to
                    <hi rend="italic">fly</hi>
                    is
employed in the passage just quoted.
                    <milestone n="70" unit="section"/>
                    Sometimes,
again, one
                    <hi rend="italic">hyperbole</hi>
                    may be heightened by the
addition of another, as when Cicero in denouncing
Antony says:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic"> Phil.</hi>
                        II. xxvii. 67.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        What Charybdis was ever so
voracious? Charybdis, do I say? Nay, if Charybdis
ever existed, she was but a single monster. By
heaven, even Ocean's self, methinks, could scarce
have engulfed so many things, so widely scattered
in such distant places, in such a twinkling of the
eye.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="71" unit="section"/>
                    I think, too, that I am right in saying that
I noted a brilliant example of the same kind in the
Hymns
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">A lost work.</note>
                    of Pindar, the prince of lyric poets. For
when he describes the onslaught made by Hercules
upon the Meropes, the legendary inhabitants of the
island of Cos, he speaks of the hero as like not to
fire, winds or sea, but to the thunderbolt, making
the latter the only true equivalent of his speed and
power, the former being treated as quite inadequate.
                    <milestone n="72" unit="section"/>
                    Cicero has imitated his method in the following
                    <pb xml:id="p.343"/>
                    passage from the Verrines:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">v. vi. 145.</note>
                    <quote>
                        After long lapse of
years the Sicilians saw dwelling in their midst, not
a second Dionysius or Phalaris (for that island has
produced many a cruel tyrant in years gone by), but
a new monster with all the old ferocity once familiar
to those regions. For, to my thinking, neither Scylla
nor Charybdis were ever such foes as he to the ships
that sailed those same narrow seas.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="73" unit="section"/>
                    The methods
of hyperbole by attenuation are the same in number.
Compare the Virgilian
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ecl.</hi>
                        iii. 103. Describing a flock of starved sheep.
                    </note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">Scarce cling they to their bones,</l>
                    </quote>
                    or the lines from a humorous work
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Unknown.</note>
                    of Cicero's,
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">Fundum Vetto vocat quem possit mittere funda;</l>
                            <l part="M">Ni tamen exciderit, qua cava funda patet.</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            Vetto gives the name of farm to an estate which
might easily be hurled from a sling, though it
might well fall through the hole in the hollow
sling, so small is it.
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    But even here a certain proportion must be observed.
For although every
                    <hi rend="italic">hyperbole</hi>
                    involves the incredible,
it must not go too far in this direction, which
provides the easiest road to extravagant affectation.
                    <milestone n="74" unit="section"/>
                    I shrink from recording the faults to which the lack
of this sense of proportion has given rise, more
especially as they are so well known and obvious.
It is enough to say that
                    <hi rend="italic">hyperbole</hi>
                    lies, though
without any intention to deceive. We must therefore be all the more careful to consider how far we
may go in exaggerating facts which our audience
may refuse to believe. Again,
                    <hi rend="italic">hyperbole</hi>
                    will often
cause a laugh. If that was what the orator desired,
                    <pb xml:id="p.345"/>
                    we may give him credit for wit; otherwise we can
only call him a fool.
                    <milestone n="75" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Hyperbole</hi>
                    is employed even
by peasants and uneducated persons, for the good
reason that everybody has an innate passion for
exaggeration or attenuation of actual facts, and no
one is ever contented with the simple truth. But
such disregard of truth is pardonable, for it does not
involve the definite assertion of the thing that is not.
                    <hi rend="italic">Hyperbole</hi>
                    is, moreover, a virtue,
                    <milestone n="76" unit="section"/>
                    when the subject
on which we have to speak is abnormal. For we are
allowed to amplify, when the magnitude of the facts
passes all words, and in such circumstances our
language will be more effective if it goes beyond
the truth than if it falls short of it. However, I
have said enough on this topic, since I have already
dealt with it in my work on the causes of the decline
of oratory.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
